Hi, these lesson rules tell
you the A-star algorithm.
It is another optimization of
the Dijkstra's algorithm for
the case when you have a specific source
and specific target, and at any point,
we have an estimation of how long does it
take to get from this point to the target.
This estimation doesn't have
to be exactly precise, but
if it is good enough it can
speed up your search a lot.
An example of such
estimations is very simple.
If you have the coordinates
of your target point, and
you have a phone with GPS controller,
and you know the GPS coordinates of your
current point, you can have
an estimation based on the distance
by the straight line between those
two points and the speed of your car.
So,this is the kind of
information we can use to
greatly improve the performance
of the Dijkstra's algorithm.
So, let's first understand the notion
of the directed search, and
to accomplish directed search, we will
need the notion of potential function.
So, we can take any function
mapping vertices to real numbers,
and it will be called
a potential function, and then,
the value of this potential function on
a vertex is called this vertex' potential.
This potential function
defines new edge weights.
If we had edge weight L of
u v on the initial graph,
then we can denote by L pi
of u v the new edge weight,
which is equal to the old edge weight
minus the potential of the starting
vertex, plus the potential of
the ending vertex of that edge.
And it turns out that if we replace
the old edge weights with these
new edge weights,
it doesn't change the shortest paths.
Well, of course it does change
the distances between vertices.
What I'm saying is only
that the paths themselves,
which were shortest in the initial graph,
they're also the shortest
paths between the same pair of vertices
in the new graph and vice versa.
The shortest paths in the new graph with
new edge weights are also the shortest
path between the same pair of
vertices in the initial graph.
And to prove this, I need this lemma.
For any potential function mapping
vertices to the real numbers, for
any two fixed vertices s and
t in the graph and
any path P between them, the length
of this path in the new graph with
new edge weights is equal to the length
of this path in the initial graph minus
the potential of the starting vertex, and
plus the potential of the ending vertex.
Why is this important?
Well, because if you fix the starting and
ending vertex, then for any path it slacks
in the initial graph, and it slacks in
the new graph, differed by a constant.
Because this constant only depends
on the starting vertex and
the ending vertex, and we fixed that.
And so, if some path worth
the shortest path between s and t,
then it will stay the shortest path
between s and t In the new graph,
because all the paths just add
a constant to their length.
And so, the paths which were shorter than
others, they stay shorter than others.
And the same goes vice versa,
if the path was shortest in the new graph,
it was also shown in the initial graph.
And now let's prove this lemma,
we consider some particular
path P from s to t, and
we also denote s as v1 and t as Vk and
the intermediate vertices V2,
V3 and so on, Vk minus one
are the vertices of this path.
Now we consider the length of this path
in the new graph, with the new edgeways.
By definition, it is equal to the sum of
the length of the edges of this path,
which is l pi(v1,v2) + l pi (v2,v3),
and so on.
And then we can rewrite each l pi
from vi to vi plus 1 by definition,
and we know that l pi of v1 to
v2 is equal to l of v1 to v2
minus the potential of v1
plus the potential of v2.
So, this first line is equal
to l pi (v1, v2).
And each of the next lines is similar,
it corresponds to
the length of the edge in the new
graph with the new edge weight.
So we write each edge on its own line, and
now we can notice that there
are somes which cancel out.
For example pi(v2) here, and
pi(v2) here are with different signs,
so they cancel out.
And the same will happen with pi(v3) and
pi(v3) here and
the same and the same will
happen with Pi (Vk-1)- Pi(Vk-1).
So, most of the terms,
including this Pi(Vk-2) will cancel out.
The only thing that is left is
the sum of the length of the initial
edges minus the first potential of
the starting verdicts minus pi(v1) and
plus Plus pi(Vk), the last verdicts.
Those are the only two summons of the form
pi of something which don't cancel out.
And then, we can rewrite this as
the first summoned is the length
of this path in the initial graph.
l(P), minus the potential
of the starting vertex,
because v1 is the same as s, and
plus the potential of the last vertex,
and Vk is the same as t.
So, the length of
the path in the new graph
is equal to the length of
the path in the initial graph,
minus the potential of starting vertex,
plus the potential of the target vertex.
So, we've proved our lemma,
so we know that the shortest
path in the initial graph and in the new
graph with new edge rates, are the same.
Although their lengths differ by some
constant depending on the starting and
ending vertex of the path.
Now, we can formulate an algorithm which
can be called Dijkstra with potentials.
So, we take some potential function pi,
and we'll launch the Dijkstra
algorithm with new edge weights l pi
instead of the initial edge weight l.
And the result endurance path is also
a shortest path in the initial graph.
So, the result of this algorithm is
the same as the result of the initial
Dijkstra algorithm.
But, depending on the result of the
potential function pie maybe it will come
from the vertex to the target vertex t
faster than with the initial edge weights,
because the order of vertices that this
algorithm considers can be different.
So, this is the idea of optimization, but
does any potential function feed us in
this case, if we want run Dijkstra
algorithm using the new edge weights?
Well, the answer is no, because for
any edge (u,v) the new length
l pi(u,v) must be negative,
so that we can apply Dijkstra
algorithm for these edge weights.
Such pie, such potential function for
which this is true that
all the new edge lines will be
non negative, is called feasible.
Now, the intuition behind
the potential functions the following.
Pi(v) is going to be an estimation
of the distance from
current the vertex v to the target vertex
t, so how far is it from here to t?
If we have such estimation, we can
often avoid going to wrong direction,
and that's why we'll get directed search.
And typically in practice,
pi(v) a lower bound on the distance
from the current point to the target.
For example,
on a real map a path from the current
point to target cannot be shorter than,
if you manage to go directly on a straight
line from the current point to the target.
This is often not possible,
because of houses or mountains,
but if this is possible,
this is the shortest path possible at all.
And our real path cannot be
shorter than the straight line
segment between the current point and
the end point.
So A* algorithm is basically
this Djikstra with potentials.
What does Djikstra with potentials do?
It goes in iterations,
and at each iteration it
picks the vertex v which minimizes
the current estimate of distance to v.
And what will be equal to?
We know that any path in the new
graph differs from the same path in
the old graph by minus potential
of the starting vertex,
plus potential of the ending vertex.
So, we are going to pick
the minimizing dist of v,
which is the distance estimate if we
ran the regular Djikstra algorithm on
the same graph, which is basically,
the length of the best known path from
the source vertex to v
minus pi(s) plus pi(v).
Now notice that pi of s
summoned is the same for all v.
So, vertex v which
minimizes this expression
is the same v that minimizes
just dist[v] + pi(v).
In the some sense, this is basically
the most promising vertex,
because pi of v is an estimate of
the distance from v to the target.
And so, we pick vertex v with the minimum
current estimate of the distance from
source vertex to v plus the distance
from v to the target vertex.
And this is in term, an estimation of the
shortest path from s to t going through v.
So this is why the search is directed.
We always go, not just to
the closest vertex to s, which is
still not unprocessed, but we also want
it to be close enough to the target.
And this is why while we're searching, we
avoid going away directly from the target.
And then, as soon as we find
the vertex t as the vertex minimizing
this expression in the Dijkstra's
algorithm on this new graph, we stop.
So, of course, this algorithm could still
go through the whole graph because before
it gets to the target.
But in practice, if you have a good
estimate of the distance left
from the current point of the target,
we will get to the target and
extract it much earlier.
And on the way there, we avoid a lot
of turns in the wrong direction.