Talking about the performance of A*,
it can only be seen in practice.
It is an empirical algorithm, and
it depends on the quality
of the potential function.
And, in the case when this potential
function gives a lower bound
on the distance from the current
point to the target,
which is most often the case,
we have the following picture.
The worst case is if the potential
function is always equal to zero for
all the vertices.
This is always feasible
potential function, but
then the algorithm will work
the same as the Dijkstras algorithm.
It will not work better,
but it will work the same.
And the best case, is if your lower
bound on the distance to the target
is always actually equal to the distance
to the target from the current V.
Then, the edge weights will be zero,
if and
only if this edge lies on the shortest
path to the target vertex.
So, it will be very easy to distinguish
the edges through which you should go,
and the edges through
which you shouldn't go.
If the edge has void zero,
then it leads you to the target.
Otherwise, it is not optimal
to go through this edge.
So you only go through the edges with
void zero, and then you will only visit
edges which lie on the shortest
paths from the source to the target.
And so, you will explore the minimum
possible number of edges
at all before getting to the target,
so this is the best case.
And in practice, depending on
the quality of your lower bound,
you'll be somewhere in between.
And it can be actually shown that
the better your lower bounds,
the tighter they are, the better will
be the performance of the A* algorithm.
And in the next video,
we will see how to actually implement
a bi-directional version of this A*
algorithm to improve it even more.