Hi.
In the previous video,
you've learned the A* algorithm.
Which is an optimization of the regular
Dijkstra shortest path algorithm using
additional information.
In the previous lesson, you've learned
that you can use a bidirectional search
to optimize Dijkstra's algorithm.
Now, we're going to join those two ideas
to optimize the A* algorithm further.
And to get the bidirectional A* algorithm.
So bidirectional A* algorithm is basically
the same as Bidirectional Dijkstra.
But with the use of potentials.
So now we need two potential functions.
One potential function pi
f(v) estimates the distance
from the current point to the target.
This is needed for the forward search.
But also we need an estimation for
the backward search using Dijkstra's
algorithm from the target.
So we need another potential pi r(v).
Which estimates the distance from
the source to the vertex, v.
Now we have a problem because,
under these two potentials,
we can have different edge weights.
Because the new edge weight
according to pi f is the initial
edge weight minus potential
of u plus potential of v.
And the new edge weight under the reverse
potential is the initial weight
minus potential of v plus potential of u.
And we need these two variables
to be actually equal.
Because in our
Bidirectional Dijkstra's algorithm.
We use the fact that we're
going through the same graph.
But just in different directions,
forward and backward.
But for it to work correctly,
we need the fact that
the edges have the same weight going in
forward direction or backward direction.
So, how to solve this problem?
So we need that l pi f (u,
v) = l pi r of (u, v).
And if we rewrite by definition,
we will see that this is equivalent
to having pi f(u) + pi
r(u) = pi f(v) + pi r(v).
For any pair of vertices
connected by an edge.
Actually, we can make
an even stronger claim.
That we need a constant value
of pi f(u) + pi r(u) for any u.
If this is true, then, of course, for
any two different vertices u and v.
pi f(u) + pi r(u) = pi f(v) + pi r(v).
And then all the edge weights
will be equal both in forward and
backward directions.
And the solution for this is to
take any feasible potential, pi f,
for the forward search.
Take any feasible potential function for
the reverse search.
And then create new potential functions.
pf(u) = half the difference of
the forward and backward potential.
And the reverse potential, pr(u), is just
=- the potential for the forward search.
If we pick such potentials,
then the sum of pf(u) and
pr(u) will be equal for any u.
So this will be constant.
And the only thing that we
need to prove is that these
potentials are both feasible.
The forward one is feasible for
the forward direction.
And the reverse one is feasible for
the backwards direction.
We will prove this for the forward
direction and for the reverse direction.
It is just symmetric.
So Lemma states that if pi f is
feasible potential for forward search.
And pi r is a feasible potential for
the reverse search.
Then their half difference is a feasible
potential for forward search.
Let's prove this.
First, we know that pi f
is a feasible potential.
And so for any edge, (u, v),
length of this edge minus
potential of u plus potential
of v is greater equal to the 0.
Also, we know that pi r is a feasible
potential for the backwards search.
And so the length of this edge minus
potential of the ending vertex, now, v.
Plus the pi r(u) is also greater or
equal than 0.
Notice that, in the first line,
we subtract by f(u) and add pi f(v).
And in the second line, we subtract,
vice versa, pi r(v) and we add pi r(u).
This important.
Now, we can sum up those inequalities.
And we'll get the 2l of the edge
from u to v -pi f(u)- pi r(u) and
+ pi f(v)- pi r(v).
All this is greater than or equal to 0.
Now, if we divide these inequality by 2.
We'll get that the length of the edge
minus half difference of potentials on u.
Plus half difference of potentials
on v is more than or equal to 0.
And this means that the potential,
which is pf.
Which is half the difference between pi f
and pi r, is a feasible potential, indeed.
Now that we've proven our Lemma,
we have a very useful tool.
If we have some kind of graphs
with additional information for
which we have good potential function.
You can first take the graph with
its regular potential function.
Then we can reverse the graph.
Take the potential function for
the reverse graph.
And then we can combine those two
potentials into new potentials.
Which lead to equal edge weights under
both forward and backward search.
And it allows us to launch
bidirectional A* algorithm
as Bidirectional Dijkstra
with potentials algorithm.
And it will be the best of both worlds.
It will be both bidirectional and
directed surge.
And so it will work probably faster than
both the just Bidirectional Dijkstra.
And adjusted A* based on
regular Dijkstra's algorithm.
The question which is left is,
where to get those potentials?
And in the next videos,
we will discuss some of the examples of
where we can get good potentials from.