Hi, today we are going to
revisit the Knapsack problem,
the problem that we already discussed
in the Greedy Algorithms module.
In this very first segment of this lesson,
we will recall the definition of this
problem, as well as motivate its study
by providing a few examples of
applying this problem in real life.
Our first example is the following.
Assume that you are given a time slot,
say two or three minutes, and
together with this time slot,
you are given a set of TV commercials.
For each commercial, you know its
revenue and you know its duration,
that is length in minutes, and
your goal is to maximize the revenue.
That is, you would like to select some
subset of your available TV commercials,
so that the total revenue is
as large as possible while
the total length does not exceed
the length of your available time slot.
In our second example, you are given a
fixed budget and your goal is to purchase
a number of computers so
that to maximize the total performance.
Again, we assume that the part of your
input in this case is a set of available
computers or machine and for each machine
you know its price and its performance.
Both the considerated problems
can be easily seen to be
special cases of the following general
problem known as the Knapsack Problem.
In this problem,
you are given a set of items together
with the total capacity of the knapsack.
For each item you know its value and
its weight.
For example, the value of the green item
here is four, while its weight is 12.
And your goal is to select the subset of
items such that the total value is as
large as possible while the total weight
is at most, the capacity of the knapsack.
In our case, the total capacity
of the knapsack is equal to 15.
There are two versions
of the knapsack problem.
Fractional knapsack and
discrete knapsack.So, for
the fractional version, which you are
already familiar with, you can take any
fraction off of any item, while in
the discrete version, for each item,
you either take the whole item in your
knapsack or you do not take it at all.
So, in turn, the discrete
version has two variants also.
So, the first variant is
knapsack with repetitions.
So in this case, you are given
an unlimited quantity of each item.
While in the knapsack without repetitions,
you are given just a single
copy of each item.
So we know already that the fractional
knapsack problem can be solved
by a simple greedy algorithm.
Such an algorithm at each
iteration just picks an element,
an item with the currently maximal
value per unit of weight.
This strategy, however, doesn't work for
the discrete version of
the knapsack problem.
So instead of using greedy strategy,
we will design a dynamic programming
solution to find an optimal value.
Now let me give you a toy example.
Assume that our input consists of
a knapsack of total capacity of ten and
four items shown on the slide.
Then the optimal value for
the knapsack without repetitions problem
is equal to 46 and it can be obtained
by taking the first item and
the third item into your knapsack.
At the same time for the knapsack
with repetitions problem.
The optimal value in this case is
equal to 48 and it can be obtained
by taking one copy of the first item and
two copies of the last item.
Finally, for the fractional knapsack
problem, the optimal value is equal
to 48 and a half and
can be obtained by taking the first item,
the second item, and
half of the last item.
Let's also use this example to show
that greedy algorithm fails for
the discrete version of
the knapsack problem.
Recall that the greedy strategy for
this problem is to first compute the value
per unit of weight for each item.
In our case, the value per unit of weight
for the first item is equal to five,
for the second item it is equal to
four and two thirds, for the third
item it is equal to four, and for the last
item it is equal to four and one half.
So the first item has maximal
value per unit of weight so
we take it into our solution.
The next available item with the maximal
value per unit of weight is the second
one, so we take it also into the solution.
Now the remaining capacity is too
small to add any other element.
So this is our constructed solution,
and it has weight,
it has value 44 which is not optimal,
we know it already.
For example here, by replacing
the second item by the third item,
we will increase the total value.
This actually means that taking an element
with a maximal value per unit
of weight is not a safe step.
Just by doing this we can lose
a possibility to construct
an optimal solution.
Right, so this means actually that
we need some other algorithm to
solve this problem optimally.
And we will design such an algorithm based
on the dynamic programming technique in
the next video.