We conclude this lesson with
a few important remarks.
The first remark is about
a trick called memoization.
Usually when designing a dynamic
program and algorithm, you start
with analyzing the structure of an optimal
solution for your computational problem.
You do this to come up with the right
definition of a sub-problem that will
allow you to express the solution for
a sub-problem through solutions for
smaller sub-sub-problems.
So, when you write down this recurrence
relation you can actually transform it
to an ISA alternative algorithm or
a recursive algorithm.
The corresponding i 20 algorithm
just solves all sub-problems,
going from smaller ones to larger ones.
And for this reason it is also
sometimes called a bottom up algorithm.
On the other hand, the recursive
algorithm to solve a sub-problem
makes recursive calls to
smaller sub-sub-problems.
And for this reason it is sometimes
called the top down approach.
Well if you implement
a recursive algorithms
straightforwardly it might turn out to
be very slow because it will recompute
some radius many, many, many times.
Like with three-dimensional numbers for
example.
However, there is a simple trick,
and it is called memorization,
that allows you to avoid re-computing
many times the same thing.
Namely, you can do the following,
when solving sub-problems,
right after solving it you store its
solution into a table, for example.
And when you make a recursive call
to solve some sub-problem, before
trying to solve it, you check in a table
whether its solution is already stored.
And if its solution is already in
the table which means that it was
already computed then you
just return it immediately.
So this recursive call,
turns out to be just a table look up.
So this is how a recursive
algorithm with memoization works.
Let's see how a recursive
algorithm with memoization for
the Knapsack problem looks like.
For simplicity let's assume that
we're talking about the Knapsack
we use repetitions.
In this case, we need to compute our
sub-problem for a Knapsack of size w,
is just the optimal rate of
a Knapsack of total weight w.
So we computed as follows,
we computed by recursive procedure.
First of all, we check whether its
solution is already in a hash table.
We use hash table to
store pairs of objects.
So, for weight w, we store value
of w if it is already computed.
If it is already in the table, we return
it immediately, otherwise we just
compute it and we make recursive
calls to compute the values for
the sub-problem on w minus wi, okay?
And when the value is computed,
we just store it in our hash table.
So this way, we use memoization
by storing this in the hash table
to avoid recomputing
the same thing once again.
So once again, an iterative
algorithm solves all sub-problems
going from smaller ones to larger ones,
right?
And eventually solves the initial problem.
On the other hand the recursive
algorithm goes as follows.
So it stars from the initial problem and
it makes recursive calls to
smaller sub-sub-problems, right?
So in some sense an iterative algorithm
and the recursive algorithm are doing
the same job, especially if we need to
solve just old range of sub-problems.
However, a recursive algorithm might
turn to be slightly slower because
it solves the same
sub-problems on one hand.
On the other hand, when making
a recursive call you also need to
put the return address on stamp,
for example.
So, the recursive algorithm
has some overhead.
There are however cases when you do not
need to solve all the sub-problems and
the Knapsack problem is nice
illustration of this situation.
So, imagine that we are given an input
to the Knapsack problem where all
the weight of n items together
with total weight of the Knapsack
are divisible by 100, for example.
This means that we are actually
not interested in sub-problems
where the weight of the knapsack is
not divisible by 100, why is that?
Well just because for
any subset of items since all the weight
of items is divisible by 100 their
total weight is also divisible by 100.
So in this case an iterative
algorithm still will solve just
whole range of sub-problems.
While a recursive algorithm will
make only those recursive calls
that I actually needed to
compute the final solution.
So, it will make only recursive
course through sub-problems
whose weight are divisible by 100.
The final remark of this lesson
is about the running time.
So if you remember the running time of
words that we recently designed in this
lesson was the log of n multiplied by w.
And this running time looks like
polynomial, however it is not.
And this is why, so consider for
example, the following input.
I mean, I assume that the total weight of
the knapsack is as shown on this slide.
This is a very huge number,
roughly ten to the 20,
I mean 20 digits of
decimal representation.
At the same time, the input size is
really tiny, just 20 digits, right?
So this is not gigabytes of data,
just 20 digits but on this input
already our algorithm will need to
perform roughly ten to the 20 operations.
This is really huge, for
example we can't do this on our laptops,
and this is because to represent the value
of W, we only need log W digits.
So, in case of the Knapsack problem,
our input is proportional not to n plus W,
but to n plus log W.
Okay, and if you represent the running
time in terms of n and log W,
then you get the following expression,
n multiplied by 2 to the log W,
which means that our algorithm is
in fact exponential time algorithm.
Put it otherwise, it can only process
inputs where W is not large enough,
it's roughly less than 1 billion,
for example.
Okay, and in fact, we believe that it is
very difficult to construct an algorithm
that will solve this problem in polynomial
time, in truly polynomial time.
In particular, we will learn later in
this presentation that this problem
is considered to be so difficult that for
solving the Knapsack problem for
example, in polynomial time,
one gets $1 million.