Hello everybody,
welcome to the course on graph algorithms.
The first unit in this course,
we're going to be talking about various
algorithms to compute various
sorts of decompositions of graphs.
But to begin with,
we're going to start with the very
basics about what is a graph,
what are they good for, and how do we
sort of interpret them and draw them.
So to start with,
a graph is sort of an abstract idea, and
it's an abstraction that sort of
represents connections between objects.
Graphs are useful both in computer
science and elsewhere in the world,
because they can be used to
describe many important phenomena.
For example, the Internet often
can be thought of as a graph,
where you've got various web pages and
theyre connected to each other by links.
And this is sort of a very, very high
level view of the Internet that sort
of pays no attention to the content of
a given page and other things like that.
On the other hand,
if you want to do something like Google's
page rank algorithm, make sort of heavy
use of this very high level view of
the Internet and connectivity within it.
Another example is maps,
you can think of maps as a graph,
sort of where you have intersections
that are connected by roads.
And this is a view that would
be very useful if you, say,
wanted to plot a course
between two locations.
You need to find some connections,
some path along this map that gets
you from one place to the other.
Social networks can also
be interpreted as graphs.
You have people connected by friendships
or following relationship or
whatever, and this provides you
another example of graph structure.
You can also sort of use
more complicated things,
if you have some sort of robot arm that
can be in many possible configurations.
What you could do is,
you could think of the configurations,
some of them are connected to
each other by various motions.
And then if you want to
solve problems like,
how do I best reconfigure this robot arm
from this position to this other position,
you again, want to sort of consider
this graph relating these things to each
other in order to figure
out how best to do that.
Okay, so these are the sorts of problems
that we would like to be able to deal with
using graph theory.
So what is a graph?
Well, the formal definition of an
undirected graph we'll talk about directed
ones in a few lectures is that
it's a collection V of vertices.
And then a collection E of edges,
each of which connects a pair
of vertices to each other.
So when you draw them on the paper what
you do is your verses are usually drawn as
points or circles or something.
And the edges are lines or curves or
something that connect
pairs of these point.
So for example the graph drawn on
the screen has four Vertices labelled A,
B, C, and D and it also has
four edges one between A and B,
one between A and C, one between A and
D and one between C and D.
And so to make sure that
were all in the same page in
we draw the following graph below,
how many edges does it have?
Well, the graph here has 12 edges.
You can sort of count them all and
each of these segments between two
of these points gives us an edge.
And so, there are 12 of them.
Now, there's one thing that sort of
fits into this definition of graphs that
I gave that is a little bit weird perhaps,
or unusual.
One thing that you might have is loops,
this would be an edge that
connects a vertex to itself.
So here we just have the one vertex A, and
then a loop that connects A to itself.
And there are some instances in
which you might want to use this.
Sometimes you actually do have traffic
circle that just goes in a loop or
something like that.
But only sometimes this is the sort
of a thing we we're talking about.
Also sometimes you can have multiple
edges between the same pair of vertices.
So in this picture we have two vertices
A and B and two edges between them.
And somehow if you're just talking about,
can I get from A to B?
It doesn't matter if there's one edge or
two between them.
But sometimes having
both of them is relevant.
On the other hand a lot of the time,
these loops and
multiple edges are just a sort of a that
we don't really need to deal with.
So often times you work
with what are known as
simple graphs which don't have loops and
don't have multiple edges.
And so, this is sort of the basics of
what a graph is that we've just covered.
Next time we're going to talk
about a couple of things.
First thing we're going to talk about how
to represent graphs on a computer and
then we're going to talk a little bit
about how we talk about runtimes for
graph algorithms.
So I hope this has been
a useful introduction and
I'll see you at the next lecture when
we talk about these other things.