Hello everybody,
welcome back to our graph algorithms.
Of course,
today we're going to be talking about
how to represent graphs on a computer.
And then after that we are going to talk
a little about how to talk about graph
runtime instead of how it depends
on one graph you are using.
So the first thing is graph
representations, so from last time recall,
the graph is a thing that consists of
a bunch of vertices sometimes called nodes
and also a bunch of edges that
connect pairs of these vertices.
And we're going to want to do is we're
going to want to do a lot of computations
on graphs to determine various
properties of them, but
before we can get to any of that, we
first need to talk about how to actually
represent a graph inside a computer.
And there are in fact
several ways to do this, and
exactly how we do it will affect
the runtimes of some of these algorithms.
So we're going to spend a little
bit of time talking about that.
So, the first thing to do is well you want
your vertices and you want your edges.
A natural way to do this is just
store a giant list of edges.
Each edge is a pair of vertices so
this is a big list of pairs of vertices.
But now what we have is we've got
these four vertices, A, B, C, and D.
And then we just store a list.
One is an edge between A and B, and
then there's an edge between A and C, and
there's an edge between A and D, and
there's an edge between C and D.
And this is a perfectly good way to
store this graph on a computer, but
there are other ways of thinking about it.
One of them is the following.
So at least, that you have a simple graph.
We're only didn't really matter is which
pairs of vertices have edges between.
And so, if I gave you a pair of vertices.
So, it's the only thing that you
need to know is you need to know,
is there an edge between
the more is there not.
So we can do is we can just
rebuild a look-up table for this,
we build a matrix where you have an entry
that's 1 if there is an edge between that
pair of vertices and a 0 if there's not.
So for example, in this graph there
is an edge between A and D and
therefore the AD entry
of this matrix is 1.
There isn't an edge, however,
between B and C, so the BC entry is 0.
And so you just fill this in, you get
this nice 4 by 4 matrix of 0s and 1s.
It is another way of
representing this graph.
On the other hand there is sort of a third
maybe a hybrid way of looking at things.
And the idea here is that for
each vertex in the graph it's going to
have a bunch of neighbors, it's going to
have other vertices that have edges from
the one that we're considering to them.
And another way of
representing the graph is for
each vertex we can just keep
a list of its neighbors.
So vertex A in this graph
is adjacent to B, C, and D.
B is adjacent to A.
C is adjacent to A and D.
D is adjacent to A and C.
So for each of these vertices we store
a list of just all of it's neighbors and
that's another way to represent the graph.
Now for example,
just to be sure we're on the same page.
If we have the following graph.
What are the neighbors of vertex C?
Well, we just draw all the edges
that leave C and it connects to A,
and B, and D, and F, and H, and I.
And, those are its neighbors.
Okay, but so we have these three
ways of representing a graph.
And it turns out the different basic
operations you want to perform
could be faster or slower depending
on which representation you have.
For example, if you want to determine if
there's an edge between this specific pair
of vertices.
This is very fast in the adjacency
matrix representation.
All you have to do is check
the appropriate entry of the matrix.
See if it's 0 or 1.
And that's your answer, constant time.
However, when you have an edge list, the
only thing that you can really do is scan
the entire list of edges to see
if that particular edge shows up.
That takes time proportional
to the number of edges.
For the adjacent lists,
it's a little bit faster than that.
What you do is you pick one end of
this edge that you're looking for and
then look it for all it's neighbors who
wants to know if A is adjacent to B,
you look at the list of A's neighbors and
see if B is on the list.
And so the time there is proportional
to the degree of the vertex.
The number of neighbors
that this one guy has.
Now another thing you might want to do
is list all of the edges in the graph.
And the adjacency matrix
is terrible here because
the only thing you do there is you scan
through every entry of the matrix.
And each one gives you an edge, but
that takes time proportionate to
the number of vertices squared.
However, the edge list
does this very easily.
It just lists all the edges in
order which is what it does.
The adjacency list is about as good
though, because you just need to,
for each vertex,
you find all of its neighbors.
Those are a bunch of edges.
And you just do this for every vertex,
and this actually counts each edge twice,
because if there's an edge between A and
B you count both.
That A is neighbor of B and
that B is a neighbor of A.
But the only counts them twice so
the time is still proportional
to the number of edges.
Finally, if you want to list all
the neighbors of a given vertex,
the adjacency matrix is
pretty slow here again.
Because the only thing you can really do
is scan through that row of the matrix,
and find all the ones.
Now, in the edge list representation,
you have scan through all the edges
In your graph to see which ones
include the vertex you want.
Whereas the adjacency list, you just
scan through the list of neighbors of
the vertex, and it's very fast.
Now, it turns out that for many problems
that we'll be considering this on, and
throughout most of the rest of this unit
on what we really want is the adjacency
risk representation of our graph, just
because a lot of the operations that we
need, we really want to be able to
find neighbors of a given vertex.
Okay, so that's how we represent graphs.
Let's spend a little bit of time to
talk about runtimes of graph algorithms.
So, when we talk about algorithm runtimes,
it's generally a function
of the size of the input.
And for the most of
the algorithms we've seen so far,
the input sort of has one size parameter,
n.
And so you runtimes like o of n squared or
o of n cubed, or something to that effect.
However, graph algorithms, well, the graph
sort of has two measures of its size.
The number of vertices and
the number of edges.
And so graph algorithms runtimes depend
in some way on both of these quantities.
You could have runtimes like
O size of E plus size of E,
which is generally considered
to be linear time.
But you can also have O of size of E,
times size of E or
size of V to the three-halves or
V log V plus E.
And there are many different possibilities
for types of runtimes that we have.
And an interesting question now is, again,
if you sort of only have one parameter,
it's easy to compare.
N log N runtime versus N
squared versus N cubed.
But if you want to say which one's faster,
say one algorithm runs in time size of V
to the three-halves and
the other one runs in time size at E.
It's not actually clear
which one's faster.
And in fact which algorithm is
faster actually depends on which
graph you're using.
In particular depends
on the density how many
edges you have in terms of
the number of vertices.
If you have many, many,
many edges O of E is going to be worse.
However, if you have few
edges its going to be better.
And in terms of density theres
sort of two extremes to consider.
On the one hand, you have dense graphs.
Here, the number of edges is roughly
proportional to the square of the number
of vertices, meaning that almost
every pair of vertices or
some large fraction of the pairs of
vertices actually have edges between them.
If you're banned, you're going on tour and
want to like plot a route between a bunch
of cities, well there is actually
some transportation option
that would get you between basically
any pair of cities on the map.
Now, it might be indirect or
take a while but
you should still probably plot all of
these out in order to plan your tour, just
what will matter is not whether or not
it's possible to get between two cities,
but how hard it is to get
between these cities.
But for this time,
you actually want sort of a dense graph,
that talks of all pairs relations
between these vertices.
On the other end of the spectrum,
we have sparse graphs.
Here the number of edges is small
relative to the number of vertices,
often as small as roughly equal
to the number of vertices or
some small constant times
the number of vertices.
And in a sparse graph,
what you have instead is that each vertex
has only a few edges coming out of it.
And this is actually very reasonable for
a lot of models you want to think about.
If you think of the internet as a graph,
well, there are billions of
web pages on the internet, but
any given web page is only going to
have links to a few dozen others.
And so the number or
the degree of any given vertex,
the number of neighbors that any given
vertex has, is much smaller than the total
number of vertices, so
you end up with a very sparse graph.
Now a lot of things like this, like
the Internet, like social networks, like
actual maps that you've drawn on a piece
of paper, these tend to be sparse graphs.
Whether or not your graph is sparse or
dense will affect the runtime
of your algorithms and
may even help determine which of
your algorithms you want to be run.
Okay, so that's it for today.
Now that sort of the basics are out of
the way we're going to actually talk about
some of the algorithms and in particular
we're going to talk about how to explore
graphs and sort of figure out which
vertices can be reached from which others
so come back next time and
we'll talk about that.