We now convert our recurrence relation
into a dynamic programming algorithm.
We start by implementing a procedure
that computes the minimum and
maximum value of the subexpression
(i,j) through optimal values for
smaller sub subexpressions.
So the procedure is called MinAndMax(i,j).
So we first declared two intervals,
max and min.
Initially min is equal to plus infinity,
max is equal to minus infinity, or
to a very large number,
or to very small number.
Then we go through all possible
values of k between i and j- 1.
I mean between,
we just go through all possibilities
of splitting our subexpression (i,
j) into two sub subexpressions from
i to k and from k plus 1 to j.
When such a splitting is fixed,
we compute four possible values, applying
opk to either two maximum values of this
subexpression or two minimum values or
two maximum and minimum value or
two minimum and maximum value.
When such two values are computed,
we just check whether one of them can
improve our minimum or maximum values.
If it improves we update the min or
max variable.
Finally we return the minimum value and
the maximum value for our subexpression.
Our current relation expresses
the solution for an expression (i,j) for
a solution for smaller sub subexpressions.
What do we mean by saying smaller?
Well, we mean just that they are shorter,
right?
So once again when we compute the value
for a subexpression (i,j) we rely on
the fact that those are values for shorter
subexpressions are already computed.
This means that our algorithm
needs to compute the solutions for
all subproblems in order
of increasing length.
Namely, in order of increasing
value of j minus i, right?
So for this problem we have roughly
quadratic number of subproblems.
Namely our subproblem, i, i, j,
is parameterized by the value of i and
j which in turn range from 1 to n.
Right, so it makes sense in this
case to store the values for
all subproblems in a two
dimensional table of size n by n.
Recall also that we need
to recall our subproblems
in the order of increasing value of j- 1.
We can do this just by going
through all subproblems in an order
shown on the slide.
So, why this order?
Well this is simply because it goes
through all possible values of i,
j in order of increasing
j minus y as required.
So lets take a look.
On this diagonal we have
all the cells where I,
where j- i is equal to 0, right?
So the first cell here is 1, 1.
The second cell is 2, 2.
The third cell is 3, 3 and so on.
We then proceed to this
cell here i is equal to 1,
j is equal to 2, so the difference is 1.
We then proceed to this cell.
This is the cell 2,
3 with the difference 1 again.
We then proceed to this cell which is 3,
4 and so on.
So on this cell we have on this
diagonal we have all the cells i,
j where i- j = 0.
On this diagonal we have all cells i,
j where j- i = 1.
For this diagonal,
this difference is equal to two.
For this diagonal, this difference
is equal to three and so on.
The resulting value for
our initial subproblem will be computed
as the value of the last cell.
Right, because of this cell responds to
the initial subexpression from one to n.
Now everything is ready to
write down an algorithm.
In the algorithm we will maintain
two tables, m and capital M.
The first one for storing the minimum
values for all subexpressions, and
the second one for storing the maximum
values for all subexpressions.
We start by initializing
these tables as follows.
So when subexpression
contains just one digit,
which means that when j = i,
then there is nothing,
actually to minimize or
maximize because there are no operations.
So there is no order on operations.
So, because of that we just initialize
the main diagonals of this table with
the most current point in digits.
This is with the following loop.
So m(i,i) and M(i,i) = di.
Then we go through all possible
subproblems in order of increasing size.
And this is done as follows.
We gradually increase
the parameter s from 1 to n- 1.
This is done in the following loop.
When s is fixed, i goes from 1 to n- s.
And j is computed as i + s.
This is done to go through
all possible payers (i,j)
such that j- i = s.
Right when i and
j are fixed we call the procedure min and
max to compute the minimum and
maximum value of the subexpression (i,j).
All right.
So finally we return the value of
capital M of 1,n as the result for
our initial problem because
this subexpression,
1 n corresponds to our initial problem.
Containing all digits from 1 to n.
Okay so the running time
of this algorithm is cubic.
Namely, big O of nq.
And these can be seen by noting
that we have two nested loops.
The first one with n-1 iterations,
the inner one is
with n-s iterations, which is at most n.
Also, inside these two loops we have
a call to min and max procedure.
The running time of min and
max procedure is proportional
to j-i which is also at most n.
So the right end time however
algorithm is it must O and
n times n time n, which is n cubed.
This slide shows an example
on how a table's m and
capital M look like if we ran
a well reason on our toy example,
namely expression 5- 8 + 7 x 4- 8 + 9.
Let's just go through this
example step by step.
So we start by filling in the values
on the main diagonal in both matrices.
So this is 5, this is 8,
this is 7, this is 4, 8, 9.
So this response to subexpression
consisted of just one digit.
So there is nothing to maximize or
minimize.
So we do the same for capital M matrix.
We then proceed to the second diagonal.
Well with -3 here and
this corresponds to this subexpression
again in this case there
is just one operation.
So there is nothing to minimize or
maximize here,
because there will just be one
other when we have Just one sign.
So we put -3 here this corresponds to
the problem, to the subproblem one, two.
Let me put all the indices
here by the way.
Then we proceed through the cell to 3,
which corresponds to this subproblem.
Again, there is nothing to maximize or
minimize so we continue in the same way.
In this case it is not so interesting and
then we proceed to the third
day namely to this cell.
So this can respond to
the subexpression 1,3 which
consists of three digits and
two operations, minus and plus.
So we know that one of them is the last
operation in the optimal order
when computing minimal value for example.
So as soon as this is minus.
This will split the subexpression into
two sub subexpression, 5 and 8 + 7.
So for both the subexpressions we already
know their maximum and minimum values.
So once again,
this subexpression corresponds to (1, 1),
this subexpression corresponds to (2, 3).
Sort of from second to third digits, and
third digit from first to first digit.
So we know that for the first
subexpression we know already it's minimum
value it is here, and
it's maximum value, it is here.
So for the second subexpression,
we already know it's minimum value,
it is here.
It is 15, and then its maximum value.
It is also 15.
So by going through all possible
pairs of obviously maximum and
minimum values, in this case,
they're all the same.
We compute the minimum value,
which is just 5- 15.
It is minus ten.
However, this was only the first
case of splitting this
sub expression into two sub expressions.
And as a possibility
would be the following so
we can split it into
the following two subexpressions.
So this corresponds to 1,
2 and this corresponds to 3,3.
Right?
So, for one two we know its minimum value,
it is minus three,
and its maximum value,
it is also minus three.
For 3, 3 we know its maximum value.
It is here, seven.
Its minimum value and its maximum value.
So then we can compute- 3 + 7,
which gives us just 4.
So for the maximum value of
the subexpression (1,3) we select 4.
For the minimum value we select -10.
So we proceed filling in this
table in a similar fashion.
So we then put 36 here in this cell,
then -20 in this cell,
and then parallel we put 60 here,
20 here, and so on.
So, in the end we see the value 200 here.
And this is the maximum value
of our initial expression.
This still doesn't give us
the optimal load rate itself, but
we will be able to reconstruct
it from these two tables.
Now we are sure that the maximum value
of our initial expression is 200,
and we will find out the optimal ordering,
or the optimal sizing in a minute.