In this last video of this lesson, we
show a method of reconstructing an actual
solution from two tables computed by
our dynamic programming algorithm.
Okay, here on this slide we see
two tables, m and capital M.
Computed by our dynamic program and
algorithm which contain minimal and
maximal values respectively for
all possible subexpressions
of our initial expression.
Let me first put in this for
all the rows and
columns of these two matrices,
as well as numbers for our initial digits.
Well, in particular, we see by
reading the contents of this cell
capital M of (1,6) that the maximal value
of our initial expression is equal to 200,
and our goal is to unwind
the whole solution, I mean,
parenthesizing of the initial expression,
from these two tables.
So our first goal on this way
is to understand from which two
subexpressions of the initial
expression the value 200 was computed.
Well, let's see, when computing
the value for the maximal value for
subexpression (1,6),
we tried all possible splittings
of the expression (1,6)
into two subexpressions.
Well, let's just go through all of them.
The first possibility is to split
it into two subexpressions (1,1),
which corresponds just
to the first digit which
is just 5, and subexpression (2,6),
with a minus sign between them, right.
So for both these two subexpressions
we already know minimal values and
maximal values.
Well, let me mark them.
So this is the minimal value for
the subexpression (1,1).
This is the maximal value for
subexpression (1,1).
For (2,6), this is the minimal value,
-195, and this is a maximal value, 75.
So we would like to
maximize this subexpression
one minus subexpression two, which means
that we would like the first subexpression
to be as large as possible and the second
subexpression to be as small as possible.
Well, this means that we need to
try to take the maximal value of
the first subexpression which is five and
the minimal value of the second
subexpression which is -195.
Well, we see that in this case,
5 minus -195 is the same as 5 plus 195,
which equals exactly 200, right,
which allows us to conclude, actually,
that the value 200 can
be obtained as follows.
So, we subtract the minimum
value which is -195
over the second subexpression from 5,
right.
So we restored the last
operation in an optimal
parenthesizing of the initial expression.
However, we still need to
find out how to obtain
-195 out of the second subexpression.
Well, let's do this.
Okay, so
we need to find how the minimum value
of the subexpression (2,6) was obtained.
Well, there are several possible
splittings, once again,
of the subexpression (2,6) into
two smaller sub-subexpressions.
The first of them is to
split (2,6) into (2,2),
which just corresponds to
the digit 8 plus (3,6).
Well, in this case, we would like
the value to be as small as possible and
our sign is plus in this case, which
means that we would like the value of
subexpression (2,2) to be
as small as possible and
the value of subexpression (3,6)
also to be as small as possible.
And you already know these values,
they are in our tables,
so the minimal value of
subexpression (2,2) is 8,
while the minimum value of subexpression
(3, 6) is minus 91, right.
So we see that the sum of these
two values is not equal to -195,
right, which means that plus
is not the last operation
in the optimal parenthesizing
that gives the minimum
value of subexpression (2, 6), right.
So let's check the next one.
Another possibility to split
the subexpression (2, 6) is the following.
We split it into subexpression (2,
3) times subexpression (4, 6), right.
So once again, we would like to find
the minimum value of subexpression (2, 6).
Well, let's see just all possibilities.
The minimum value of subexpression (2,
3) is 15.
It's maximal value is also 15.
As to subexpression (4,6),
its minimum value is -13.
It's maximal value is 5.
And we would like the product of these
two values to be as small as possible.
Well, it is not difficult to
see that if we take just 15 and
multiply it, which is a minimum
value of subexpression (2,3),
and multiply it by the minimum
value of the subexpression (4,6),
which is -13, then we get exactly -195.
And this, in turn, allows us to get -195
from the subexpression (2,6).
We can do as follows.
We can first compute the sum of 8 and 7.
This gives us 15.
And then to multiply it by the result
of the second subexpression.
Well, now it remains to find out how to
get -13 out of this subexpression for
6, but in this small example,
it is already easy to get -13.
Well, we just first compute
the sum of 8 and 9 and
then subtract it from 4, right.
So this way we reconstructed
the whole solution, I mean,
an optimal parenthesizing, or an optimal
ordering, of our arithmetic operations,
leading to this value,
to this maximal value, 200.
Let's just check it once again that our
parenthesizing leads to the value 200,
indeed.
So we first compute the sum of 8 and 9.
This gives us 17.
We then subtract 17 from 4.
And this gives us -13.
We then compute the sum of 8 and 7.
This gives us 15.
We multiply 15 by -13.
It gives us -195, and, finally,
we subtract this number from 5,
and we get 200, indeed.
So we reconstructed the whole solution.
In general, I mean for
an expression consisting of n digits and
n minus 1 operations they can respond, an
algorithm makes roughly quadratic number
of steps, because it needs to reconstruct
n minus one operations, I mean,
an order of n minus one operations,
going from last one to the first one.
And for each operation, it potentially
needs to go through all possible
splittings into two subexpressions,
and this number is at most M.
So the running time is bigger of ten
times M, which is bigger of M squared.
And this technique is quite general.
It applies in many cases in
the dynamic problem in algorithms.