In this video, we're going to explore when
variables are created, how long they exist
in
computer memory, and what happens when two
variables
have the same name and two different
functions.
Here we see functions convert to minutes
which we explored in the function
visualization lecture.
We have added function covert to seconds,
which coverts
a number of hours to an equivalent number
of seconds.
Convert to seconds does its work by
calling convert
to minutes and then multiplying the result
by 60.
Let's use the visualizer to explore this.
We'll quickly step over the function
definitions to
function objects are created.
Convert to minutes for
[UNKNOWN]
one of these function objects, and convert
seconds for first to the other.
Now we are about to execute an assignment
statement.
The first step is to evaluate the right
hand side which is a function call.
Python first evaluates the argument and
creates an object for that value.
Next, ifound creates a frame on the call
stack
and stores the memory address of two in
the parameter,
[INAUDIBLE].
As a reminder, this area is called the
call stack.
It is shown as an upside down stack of
frames.
During execution of a function call a new
stack frame is created.
Whenever a function exits, the current
stack frame is erased.
And execution of the previous function
continues.
The first line in the body
of convert_to_seconds is another
assignment statement.
The right-hand side is a function call.
We follow the same rules as always,
evaluate the
argument, num_hours, which contains the
memory address of value two.
Then, a stack form is created for the call
on convert_to_minutes,
and its parameter, mem_hours, contains the
memory address of that value.
There are two variables called mem_hours.
One of them is in the frame for the call
on convert_to_minutes, and one of them
is in the frame for the call on
convert_to_seconds.
Python keeps these two running functions
in separate areas of memory
so it does not get confused about which
variable to use.
Back to tracing the execution.
The first line in the body of convert the
minutes is an assignment state.
On the right hand side there's an
expression numerous x 60.
Which num_hours do we use?
The answer is that python looks in the
current stack frame.
Num_hours refers to two so num_hours type
60 evaluates to 120.
The second step of the assignment is to
assign 120
to variable minutes.
If minutes does not exist in the current
stack frame Then it will be created.
Each stack frame contains its own set of
variables.
In the frame for convert to minutes are
variables, num hours, and minutes.
The frame for convert to seconds currently
only has variable num hours.
Although, by the end of its execution, it
will also have both minutes and seconds.
The stack frame for the main
program currently has convert_to_minutes
and convert_to_seconds.
Although by the assignment statement on
line 20 is done
executing, variable seconds will exist
there.
We're now about to return the value
of variable minutes, and exit the current
function.
But where do we return to?
The answer is always, to the next frame on
the call stack.
The current stack frame is created during
this call on convert_to_minutes.
When this call is complete, the current
stack frame
is erased, and Python produces the return
value as the
value of this function call expression.
This call is on the right-hand side of an
assignment statement.
To complete the assignment variable
minutes will be created, and
Python will store the memory address of
the return value.
Let's watch that happen.
Notice that the frame for convert to
minutes has been erased, and variable
minutes has
been created in the frame for convert
to seconds Here we have another assignment
statement.
The right-hand side, minutes times 60,
evaluates to whatever 120 times 60 is.
And a new variable seconds will be
created,
and contain the memory address of that new
value.
Next we return seconds.
Seconds refers to 7,200 so that's the
value that gets
produced by the call on convert to seconds
on line 20.
[BLANK_AUDIO]