Hello.
Welcome to the Coursera course on Neural
Networks for Machine Learning.
Before we get into the details of neural
network learning algorithms, I want to
talk a little bit about machine learning,
why we need machine learning, the kinds of
things we use it for, and show you some
examples of what it can do.
So the reason we need machine learning is
that the sum problem, where it's very hard
to write the programs, recognizing a three
dimensional object for example.
When it's from a novel viewpoint and new
lighting additions in a cluttered scene is
very hard to do.
We don't know what program to write
because we don't know how it's done in our
brain.
And even if we did know what program to
write, it might be that it was a
horrendously complicated program.
Another example is, detecting a fraudulent
credit card transaction, where there may
not be any nice, simple rules that will
tell you it's fraudulent.
You really need to combine, a very large
number of, not very reliable rules.
And also, those rules change every time
because people change the tricks they use
for fraud.
So, we need a complicated program that
combines unreliable rules, and that we can
change easily.
The machine learning approach, is to say,
instead of writing each program by hand
for each specific task, for particular
task, we collect a lot of examples, and
specify the correct output for given
input.
A machine learning algorithm then takes
these examples and produces a program that
does the job.
The program produced by the linear
algorithm may look very different from the
typical handwritten program.
For example, it might contain millions of
numbers about how you weight different
kinds of evidence.
If we do it right, the program should work
for new cases just as well as the ones
it's trained on.
And if the data changes, we should be able
to change the program runs very easily by
retraining it on the new data.
And now massive amounts for computation
are cheaper that paying someone to write a
program for a specific task, so we can
afford big complicated machine learning
programs to produce these stark task
specific systems for us.
Some examples of the things that are best
done by using a learning algorithm are
recognizing patterns, so for example
objects in real scenes, or the identities
or expressions of people's faces, or
spoken words.
There's also recognizing anomalies.
So, an unusual sequence of credit card
transactions would be an anomaly.
Another example of an anomaly would be an
unusual pattern of sensor readings in a
nuclear power plant.
And you wouldn't really want to have to
deal with those by doing supervised
learning.
Where you look at the ones that blow up,
and see what, what caused them to blow up.
You'd really like to recognize that
something funny is happening without
having any supervision signal.
It's just not behaving in its normal way.
And then this prediction.
So, typically, predicting future stock
prices or currency exchange rates or
predicting which movies a person will like
from knowing which other movies they like.
And which movies a lot of other people
liked.
So in this course I'm mean as a standard
example for explaining a lot of the
machine learning algorithms.
This is done in a lot of science.
In genetics for example, a lot of genetics
is done on fruitflies.
And the reason is they're convenient.
They breed fast and a lot is already known
about the genetics of fruit flies.
The MNIST database of handwritten digits
is the machine equivalent of fruitflies.
It's publicly available.
We can get machine learning algorithms to
learn how to recognize these handwritten
digits quite quickly, so it's easy to try
lots of variations.
And we know huge amounts about how well
different machine learning methods do on
MNIST.
And in particular, the different machine
learning methods were implemented by
people who believed in them, so we can
rely on those results.
So for all those reasons, we're gonna use
MNIST as our standard task.
Here's an example of some of the digits in
MNIST.
These are ones that were correctly
recognized by neural net the first time it
saw them.
But the ones within the neural net wasn't
very confident.
And you could see why.
I've arranged these digits in standard
scan line order.
So zeros, then ones, then twos and so on.
If you look at a bunch of tubes like the
onces in the green rectangle.
You can see that if you knew they were 100
in digit you'd probably guess they were
twos.
But it's very hard to say what it is that
makes them twos.
Theres nothing simple that they all have
in common.
In particular if you try and overlay one
on another you'll see it doesn't fit.
And even if you skew it a bit, it's very
hard to make them overlay on each other.
So a template isn't going to do the job.
An in particular template is going to be
very hard to find that will fit those twos
in the green box and would also fit the
things in the red boxes.
So that's one thing that makes recognizing
handwritten digits a good task for machine
learning.
Now, I don't want you to think that's the
only thing we can do.
It's a relatively simple for our machine
learning system to do now.
And to motivate the rest of the course, I
want to show you some examples of much
more difficult things.
So we now have neural nets with
approaching a hundred million parameters
in them, that can recognize a thousand
different object classes in 1.3 million
high resolution training images got from
the web.
So, there was a competition in 2010, and
the best system got 47 percent error rate
if you look at its first choice, and 25
percent error rate if you say it got it
right if it was in its top five choices,
which isn't bad for 1,000 different
objects.
Jitendra Malik who's an eminent neural net
skeptic, and a leading computer vision
researcher, has said that this competition
is a good test of whether deep neural
networks can work well for object
recognition.
And a very deep neural network can now do
considerably better than the thing that
won the competition.
It can get less than 40 percent error, for
its first choice, and less than twenty
percent error for its top five choices.
I'll describe that in much more detail in
lecture five.
Here's some examples of the kinds of
images you have to recognize.
These images from the test set that he's
never seen before.
And below the examples, I'm showing you
what the neural net thought the right
answer was.
Where the length of the horizontal bar is
how confident it was, and the correct
answer is in red.
So if you look in the middle, it correctly
identified that as a snow plow.
But you can see that its other choices are
fairly sensible.
It does look a little bit like a drilling
platform.
And if you look at its third choice, a
lifeboat, it actually looks very like a
lifeboat.
You can see the flag on the front of the
boat and the bridge of the boat and the
flag at the back, and the high surf in the
background.
So its, its errors tell you a lot about
how it's doing it and they're very
plausible errors.
If you look on the left, it gets it wrong
possibly because the beak of the bird is
missing and cuz the feathers of the bird
look very like the wet fur of an otter.
But it gets it in its top five, and it
does better than me.
I wouldn't know if that was a quail or a
ruffed grouse or a partridge.
If you look on the right, it gets it
completely wrong.
It a guillotine, you can why it says that.
You can possibly see why it says
orangutan, because of the sort of jungle
looking background and something orange in
the middle.
But it fails to get the right answer.
It can, however, deal with a wide range of
different objects.
If you look on the left, I would have said
microwave as my first answer.
The labels aren't very systematic.
So actually, the correct answer there is
electric range.
And it does get it in its top five.
In the middle, it's getting a turnstile,
which is a distributed object.
It does, can't, it can do more than just
recognize compact things.
And it can also deal with pictures, as
well as real scenes, like the bulletproof
vest.
And it makes some very cool errors.
If you look at the image on the left,
that's an earphone.
It doesn't get anything, like an earphone.
But if you look at this fourth batch, it
thinks it's an ant.
And for you to think that's crazy.
But then if you look at it carefully, you
can see it's a view of an ant from
underneath.
The eyes are looking down at you, and you
can see the antennae behind it.
It's not the kind of view of an ant you'd
like to have if you were a green fly.
If you look at the one on the right, it
doesn't get the right answer.
But all of its answers are, cylindrical
objects.
Another task that neural nets are now very
good at, is speech recognition.
Or at least part of a speech recognition
system.
So speech recognition systems have several
stages.
First they pre-process the sound wave, to
get a vector of acoustic coefficients, for
each ten milliseconds of sound wave.
And so they get 100 of those actors per
second.
They then take a few adjacent vectors of
acoustic coefficients, and they need to
place bets on which part of which phoneme
is being spoken.
So they look at this little window and
they say, in the middle of this window,
what do I think the phoneme is, and which
part of the phoneme is it?
And a good speech recognition system will
have many alternative models for a
phoneme.
And each model, it might have three
different parts.
So it might have many thousands of
alternative fragments that it thinks this
might be.
And you have to place bets on all those
thousands of alternatives.
And then once you place those bets you
have a decoding stage that does the best
job it can of using plausible bets, but
piecing them together into a sequence of
bets that corresponds to the kinds of
things that people say.
Currently, deep neural networks pioneered
by George Dahl and Abdel-rahman Mohammed
of the University of Toronto are doing
better than previous machine learning
methods for the acoustic model, and
they're now beginning to be used in
practical systems.
So, Dahl and Mohammed, developed a system,
that uses many layers of, binary neurons,
to, take some acoustic frames, and make
bets about the labels.
They were doing it on a fairly small
database and then used 183 alternative
labels.
And to get their system to work well, they
did some pre-training, which will be
described in the second half of the
course.
After standard post processing, they got
20.7 percent error rate on a very standard
benchmark, which is kind of like the NMIST
for speech.
The best previous result on that benchmark
for speak independent recognition was
24.4%.
And a very experienced speech researcher
at Microsoft research realized that, that
was a big enough improvement, that
probably this would change the way speech
recognition systems were done.
And indeed, it has.
So, if you look at recent results from
several different leading speech groups,
Microsoft showed that this kind of deep
neural network, when used as the acoustic
model in the speech system.
Reduced the error rate from 27.4 percent
to 18.5%, or alternatively, you could view
it as reducing the amount of training data
you needed from 2,000 hours down to 309
hours to get comparable performance.
Ibm which has the best system for one of
the standard speech recognition tasks for
large recovery speech recognition, showed
that even it's very highly tuned system
that was getting 18.8 percent can be
beaten by one of these deep neural
networks.
And Google, fairly recently, trained a
deep neural network on a large amount of
speech, 5,800 hours.
That was still much less than they trained
their mixture model on.
But even with much less data, it did a lot
better than the technology they had
before.
So it reduced the error rate from sixteen
percent to 12.3 percent and the error rate
is still falling.
And in the latest Android, if you do voice
search, it's using one of these deep
neurall networks in order to do very good
speech recognition.