Hi, in this video,
you will learn what a hash function is,
how could we apply it to solve our
problem with IP addresses, and
why it is not straightforward
to make it to work.
Remember the direct addressing
approach worked particularly fast, but
it used a lot of memory that's
because it encoded IP with numbers and
those numbers were sometimes huge.
So we had to create an array of size 2
to the power of 32 just to store all
those numbers.
What if we could encode our IP
addresses with smaller numbers,
for example, numbers from 0 to 999?
We'll still need the code for different
IP addresses, which are active currently
to be different because we want a separate
counter for each IP in our solution.
Let's define a hash function.
So if you have universal object S for
example.
A set of all IP addresses or a set of all
files stored on your computer or a set
of all words or cures in the programming
language, so that is our universe.
And we will call it a set S.
And now we want to encode each object
from that universe with a small number.
A number from 0 to m- 1 where m
is a positive integer number.
While any function,
which encodes some object from S
as a number from 0 to m- 1,
is called a hash function.
And m is called the cardinality
of hash function h.
So what are the desirable properties
of the hash function in our problem?
First, h should be fast to compute
because we need to encode some object for
each query.
Second, we want different values for
different objects
because we want a separate counter for
each IP address in our problem from them.
And also, we want to use direct addressing
scheme because it was very fast,
but we want to use a direct addressing
scheme with a small amount of memory.
And it's only logical to use in this
case direct addressing scheme with O(m)
memories.
Just create an area a of size m, and
then encode each ID with some value from
0 to m- 1, and store the corresponding
counter In the cell of this array.
The problem is that we want small
cardinality m and it won't work
if m is smaller than the number of
different objects in the universe.
Because if we have for
example 25 object in the universe and
m is only 10, then at least two
objects will have the same code from
0 to 9 because there are only 10 different
codes and there are 25 different objects.
So that won't work for
all possible universes and for small m.
In this situation, when the values of
the hash function are the same, but
the objects which are being encoded
are different, is called a collision.
So collisions cause us problems.
Because of collisions,
we cannot just directly
apply the scheme called direct
addressing with O(m) memory.
And in the next lecture,
we will see how to overcome this problem.