In this video,
we will study chaining, which is one of
the most frequently used techniques for
using hashing to store mappings from one
type of object to another type of object.
So, let us define a map.
We often want to store mapping from
some objects to some other object.
For example, I'm mapping from
IP addresses to integer numbers.
Or from filenames to the physical
location of those files on the disk.
From student ID to
the name of the student.
Or from contact name in your phone
book to the contact phone number.
The general definition of
a map from set of objects S
to the set of values V is a data
structure which has three methods.
HasKey, which tells us
whether there is an entry
in the map corresponding
to object O from set S.
Method Get, which returns to us
the value corresponding to the object O,
if there is one.
If there is no such value,
it returns a special value
telling us that there is no entry
corresponding to this object O in the map.
And the last method is set,
the most important method,
which sets the value
corresponding to object O to V.
Here, objects O are all from the set S and
values V are from the set big V.
We want to implement a map,
using hash function, and
some combination of ideas
from direct addressing, and
least based solution from
one of the previous videos.
So what we'll do is called chaining.
We will create an array of size m, where m
is the cardinality of the hash function,
and in this case, let m be eight.
This won't be an array of integers,
though.
This will be an array of lists.
So in each cell of this array,
we will store a list.
And this will be a list of pairs.
And each pair will consist of an object,
O.
And a value V,
corresponding to this object.
Let's look at an example.
For example,
our objects are IP addresses, and
the values are the corresponding counters.
As in our initial problem about web
service, and IP addresses of its class.
Now we're processing the log, and
we see an IP address, starting with 173.
And it so happens that the value of hash
function on this IP address is four.
Then, we look at the cell four,
the list there is now empty.
But we append,
in the pair of our IP address.
And the corresponding counter one,
to this list.
The value is one because this is
the first time that we encounter this AB.
Now we'll look at the next IP in the log.
It starts with 69, and
the hash value for this IP is one.
So we'll look at the cell number one, and
we append the pair of this IP address and
the corresponding counter one to the list.
Again the counter is one because this is
the first time we see this IP address.
Now it looks at the next IP address in
the log and we see that it again starts
with 173 and actually it coincides with
the first IP that we've already seen.
And the hash value is again four,
because hash function is deterministic,
it always returns the same number for
same object.
So we'll look at the cell number four,
we'll look through the whole list and
we find out that there is already a pair
containing this IP address as the key.
So instead of appending this
IP address again to the list,
we will increase the value of the counter
by one because this is the second
time we've seen our IP address.
Of course in the interface of
a general map, there is no method for
incrementing a counter, there is a method
to set so we will need to first use
method get to get the value corresponding
to this IP address, we will get one.
We will then increase it by one ourselves,
get two.
And then we will call set for
this IP address and value two.
And it will just rewrite the value
from one to two in this list element.
Then, we'll look at the next
line in our log, and
we see that this is IP starting from 91.
And it so happens that the hash value for
this IP address, again,
is four,
although this is a different IP address.
And that has to happen at some point,
because there are many,
many different IP addresses, and
only eight entries in our array.
So what do we do?
If we look at the cell number four,
there is a non-empty list there.
We go through the whole list, but
we see that our new IP address
starting from 91 is not in the list.
So we add our new IP address
to the end of this list
along with the corresponding
counter of one.
And these two IP addresses in the list for
cell number four already
make a chain together.
And if we go further and
further through the log, and we add some
IP addresses to this map,
some of the chains will become longer.
If where some point we'll need to remove
some IP address from the list we can do
that and the chain can become shorter.
But anyway, you see the general
structure that a chain maybe empty,
maybe non-empty,
starts in any cell of the array.
The array size is m, which is equal to
the cardinality of the hash function.
And for each such cell we store a list
with all the IP addresses which
occurred before and which have hash value
the same as the number of the cell.