How to implement this in code?
Well, let's just assume that we have
a hash function h from the set of all
possible objects S to the set
of numbers from 0 to m-1.
And let us denote by O and
O prime objects from set S and
by v and v prime values from set big V.
And let us have an array A,
which consists of m lists,
where m is the cardinality
of the hash function.
And those lists we'll call also chains,
and
those chains consist of pairs
of objects O and values v.
Now let us implement the first method,
HasKey, which would return whether
there is an entry in our table or
in our map for the object O.
First, we compute the value of
hash function on the object O.
We'll look at the corresponding
cell in the array A, and
we'll take the list out from there.
Then we go through this list and
when we go through it,
we'll look at pairs O prime,
v prime that are elements of this list.
If for some pair O prime is
the same as the object O for
which we are looking, we return true
because it means that there is an entry in
our map corresponding to the object O.
If we don't find any
corresponding pair in the list,
return false because that means
there is no such object and
there is no key corresponding
to this object in our map.
Because it only could be in the list
corresponding to the cell with
number h of O and we didn't find it there.
Next let's implement method Get,
which should return the value
corresponding to object O if there is one.
Otherwise, return some special
value telling us that there is no
entry corresponding to object O.
Again, we start with computing value
of hash function on object O and
looking at the cell number
h of O in the array A and
take the list,
which is stored in that cell.
Then we again go through all
the pairs in that list L,
pairs O prime, v prime, and
if for some of the pairs,
O prime is the same as the object O for
which we are looking, then we'll return
the corresponding value v prime as
the value corresponding to that object O.
If we go through the whole list and
we don't find corresponding player,
we'll return special value n/a,
which means that there is no
value corresponding to
object O in our map.
Why is that?
Because if there was some value,
it has to be in the list corresponding to
the cell number h of O because
that's the way we store our chains,
and if we didn't find it there, then there
is no entry corresponding to the object O.
Now the last, most interesting method,
Set, which accepts two arguments,
object O and the value v, which we need
to set corresponding to this object.
We need to either rewrite this value if
there was already an entry corresponding
to the object O with different value.
Or we need to create a new value in
the map corresponding to the object O if
it didn't happen to be in the map before.
We again start with computing the hash
function on the object O and looking at
the corresponding cell in the array A and
we'll take the list, we just start there.
Now we go through all the pairs
p in that list L, and
each pair p contains two fields,
first field is p.O,
which is the object of that pair, and
p.v, which is the value of that pair.
If for some pair, we see that
the object of that pair is the same
as object O for
which we need to set the value v,
then we just assign the value to the p.v,
the new value.
We will write the old value with
the new value for that object O and
then we return, we exit from the function.
Because we've already
done everything we need.
If we go through the whole list and
we don't find any pair corresponding to
our object O, it means that there was no
entry in our map corresponding
to the object O previously.
And it means that we need to
add a new pair to our list, and
we just append a new pair
containing object O and
value v to the list L,
corresponding to the cell number h of O.
Now let's look at the SM
project of the chaining scheme.
The first lemma says that if c is
the length of the longest chain in A,
then the running time of all
three methods is theta of c+1.
First, if we look at the list
corresponding to some object O,
the list in the cell number h of O,
then the length of this list can be c,
this can be the longest list itself.
And if object O is not in this list and
would call some of the methods for
this object,
we will need to scan the full list so
we'll need to scan all
c items in this list.
Also, if c is 0 so that our map is empty,
our array A is comprised of m after this.
We still need constant time to check that.
So that's why c+1 and not just c.
Another lemma is talking
about memory consumption.
So let n be the number of different
keys that we're storing in the map and
m is the cardinality of the hash function.
Then the memory consumption
is theta of n+m.
That is very easy to prove.
First, we need to store n pairs of objects
and corresponding values in the map.
That's where we get theta of n.
And we get additional theta of m
to store the array of m lists.
Although those lists can be empty,
we'll still need to use
some memory to store the pointers
to the heads of those lists,
and that's why memory
consumption is theta of n+m.