Hello everybody,
welcome back to the Data Structures and
Algorithm specialization and
the Algorithmic Toolbox course within it.
This is the last lecture in
the introductory unit and
here we're going to give sort
of an overview of the course.
And in particular, what we're going to
do is we're going to talk about sort
of the philosophy of the course, and
how it fits into the what we're going to
be teaching you within
the rest of this course.
So, there's a problem.
Algorithm design is hard, and
in particular it's hard to teach.
And by this I actually mean
something pretty specific.
Now, algorithms solve many,
many different problems.
You can use them to find paths
between locations on a map,
or find good matchings with some property,
or identify images in a photograph.
Many, many different sort of
unrelated sounding problems
can all be solved by algorithms.
And because the sorts of things that
an algorithm problem might ask you to
do are so
varied, there's no unified technique that
will allow you to solve all of them.
And this is different from what you see in
a lot of classes, when you're learning linear
algebra they talk about how do you
solve systems of linear equations.
And they teach you some technique,
like row reduction, and
then you're sort of done.
You just sort of need to practice it,
and you can solve any
system of linear equations.
They give you a system
of linear equations,
you turn the crank on this row reduction
technology and out pops an answer.
For algorithms there
isn't that sort of thing.
There's no general procedure where I give
you an algorithms problem and you sort of
plug it into this machine and turn a crank
and out pops a good algorithm for it.
And this makes it hard to teach.
If there was such a thing, we could just
teach you, here's this thing that you do.
You do this, and
you'll have a good algorithm for
any problem you might run into.
And it's harder than that.
I mean, sometimes,
in order to find a good algorithm,
it requires that you
have a unique insight.
You're working on some problem that
no one's ever looked at before.
In order to find a good algorithm for it,
you need to come up with some clever idea
that no one else has
ever come up with before.
This is why sort of algorithms are so
well studied,
why they're such an active
field of research.
There are still so many different new
things yet to be discovered there.
And we certainly can't teach you things
that haven't been discovered yet.
And we also can't teach you
things custom tailored to
the problems that you are going to run
into in your life as a programmer.
So since we can't teach you everything
you need to know about how to solve
all of your algorithm problems,
what can we teach you?
Well, there are sort of two things.
One thing that we can definitely give
you is practice designing algorithms.
We're going to have lots of homework
problems with lots of things for
you to work on, and
this will give you practice, how do you,
given a problem you haven't seen before,
come up with a good algorithm for it?
Once you have the algorithm,
how do you implement it and
make sure everything works and
runs reasonably well?
That's something you can practice.
And it turns out that for the type of
problems where they're sort of very
general and can be many different things,
I mean, it's possible to solve a lot
of them, and one of the ways to be
able to solve them is practice.
But we're also going to do more.
We're not just going to throw you in
the deep end and say, try to swim,
try to program all of these algorithms.
There is something useful.
We can't teach you a generic
procedure that will solve
any algorithms problem for you.
But what we can do is we can
give you some common tools.
Some very useful tools for
algorithm design.
And especially in this first
course in our specialization
we're really going to focus on helping
to build up your algorithmic toolbox.
And in particular, this course is going
to focus on three of the most common and
most generally applicable
algorithmic design techniques.
The first of these is greedy algorithms.
This is something where you're trying
to construct some big object, and
the way you do it is you sort of make
one decision in the most greedy,
locally optimal way you can.
And once you've made that decision you
make another decision in the most greedy,
locally optimal way you can.
And you just keep making these decisions
one at a time until you have an answer.
And surprisingly somehow making
these locally optimal decisions
gives you a globally optimal solution.
And when this happens it gives you
very clean algorithms and it's great.
That's the first thing we'll talk about.
Next, we'll talk about divide and conquer,
which is a technique where you've got
some big problem you're trying to solve.
What you do is you break it into
a bunch of little pieces, you solve all
the pieces, and then you put their answers
together to solve the original thing.
Finally we'll talk about
dynamic programming.
This is a little bit more
subtle of a technique.
This is what you get when you've got some
sort of large problem, that has sort of
a lot of, not sub-problems, but
sort of related problems to it.
And this sort of whole
family of related problems,
their solutions sort of depend on one
another in a particular type of way.
And when you have it there's
this great trick that you have,
where you sort of start at the small
problems at the bottom of the pile.
And you solve all of them.
And you sort of keep track
of all of your answers.
And you use the answers
to the small problems,
to build up to obtain answers to
the larger and larger problems.
So these are what we're
going to talk about.
Each of the techniques we're going to talk
about, how you recognize when it applies,
how do you analyze it when it applies,
and some practical techniques about
how to implement, how to use them.
All that good stuff.
So there's one other thing before
we let you go into the fun world of
greedy algorithms that you should
keep in mind throughout this course,
and that's that there are these, maybe,
different levels of algorithm design.
There's sort of different levels
of sophistication that go into it.
At sort of the very lowest level,
or top of this slide,
I guess, there is the naive algorithm.
This is sort of a thing where you
take the definition of a problem and
you turn it into an algorithm, and
we saw this for Fibonacci numbers and
greatest common divisors.
You sort of interpreted the definition
of the thing you wanted to compute as
an algorithm, and you were done.
Now, these things are often very slow,
as we saw.
Often they look like in order to find
the best way of doing something,
we enumerate all ways to do it, and
then figure out which one's the best.
On the other hand, these are slow, but
it's often a good idea to first come up
with a naive algorithm, just make sure
you have some algorithm that works.
Sometimes this works well and
often you can just be done with it.
Other times, it's too slow, but
at least you made sure that you understood
what problem you were working on and
have something that runs.
But after that,
the next thing that you want to do,
if this naive algorithm is too slow,
is you try and look at your tool box.
You say, are there any standard
techniques that I know that apply here?
Maybe there's a greedy algorithm
that solves this problem, or
maybe I have to use a dynamic program.
But if you can find one of these
standard techniques that work,
often that doesn't involve too
much effort on your part, and
gives you something
that works pretty well.
Now once you have something that works,
you often want to optimize it.
And there are lots of ways to
improve an existing algorithm.
Reduce the runtime from n-cubed
to n-squared or n-squared to n.
And to do this,
there are just a whole bunch of things.
Maybe sometimes you could just sort of
rearrange the order in which you do
the operations to cut out
some of the work that you do.
Sometimes you have to introduce
a data structure to speed things up.
There are a bunch of ways to do this.
We'll talk a little bit
about how this works.
And these three levels are things that
you should be comfortable with and
able to apply pretty well
by the end of this course.
However, sometimes these
three are not enough.
Sometimes a naive algorithm is just too
slow, the standard tools don't apply,
there's nothing that you can
really optimize to improve things.
Sometimes in order to get a workable
algorithm, what you need is magic.
You need some unique insight that
no one else has ever had before.
You need some sort of clever new idea and
these, there's only so
much we can do to teach
you how to produce magic.
We will show you some examples of things
that really did have clever ideas that
maybe you can't reproduce
the thought process like,
how do you come up with this crazy idea,
that just happens to make this work?
You should at least be able to appreciate
the sort of thought that goes into this
sort of thing.
In any case it's something to keep
in mind when looking on that,
when thinking about our problems, and
what sort of things are expected of you.
In any case, that is basically it for
the introductory segment.
We've talked a lot about sort of
why algorithms are important and
given you some examples.
We've talked about asymptotic notation,
but now it's time to let you
go to the rest of the course.
The rest of the course will keep giving
you exercises to hone your skills, and
each unit of this course will cover
one of these major techniques.
After I leave you with the end of
the introduction, Michael will pick up and
talk to you about greedy algorithms.
Next off, Neil will talk to
you about divide and conquer.
Finally, Pavel will have
a unit on dynamic programming.
Each of these, they will talk to you
about where the technique applies,
how to analyze it, how to implement it,
all that good stuff.
But this is where I leave you, I hope
you enjoyed the introduction, and I will
put you in Michael's very capable hands to
start learning about greedy algorithms
starting in the next lecture.
So, until then, farewell.