As you've seen Python has
a built-in function called help
that will show you information
about the function.
IDLE will also provide
information when you start to
type the call on that function.
For example, when you call function
help on the absolute value function,
you get a nice description
of what it does.
Also, when you start to write a call on
that function, it pops a little yellow box
in IDLE showing you the type of
the parameters and the returned type.
You can provide the same kind of
information for your own functions by
writing documentation in a particular
format called a doc strength.
We have written documentation for
the area of a triangle function
that we wrote last week.
Notice that we are using
a triple coded string
because our descriptions
spends multiple lines.
We will now run this module in order to
have area available to us in the Python
shell and when I ask for
help on area, we now see what
we have inside the doc string.
Furthermore, this first line of
the doc string is what will show up
when I start to type a call on area.
From now on, we will always provide
doc strings for our functions
both to describe what they do and
also to hook into Python's help system.