Hello everybody.
Welcome back.
Today we're going to talk
more about splay trees.
In particular,
we can tell how to implement your basic
search tree operations using a splay tree.
So remember, last time, we had this
idea to design a binary search tree,
where every time you queried a node,
you brought it to the root.
And we know that simple ways of
doing this didn't quite work out so
well, so we introduced the splay
operation, which is a little bit better.
Now, there's this problem with the splay
operation that the way that the splay
trees are built, you don't actually
guarantee the tree is always balanced.
Sometimes you'll end up
with very unbalanced trees.
And when that happens, your splay
operation will actually be very slow
because you have to sort of bring
your node up to the root one or
two steps at a time, and
it will actually take a while.
However, you'll note that if I have
this long stretched out tree, and
I splay this leaf all the way to the root,
we have rearranged the tree,
it's now a little bit more
balanced than it was before.
And so, when you use the splay
operation rather than to sort of rotate
to top operation, it's actually
the case that you can't have a long
sequence of expensive splay operations.
Because every time you have
an expensive splay operation,
it will rebalance the tree and
make it more balanced.
And so, if you keep picking really
unbalanced nodes, pretty quickly, the tree
will balance itself out, and then you'll
have nice, short login time operations.
But this does mean that we're no
longer dealing with worst case time.
Well, we need to talk about amortized
analysis, average case time.
And the big theorem that we're not going
to prove today is that the amortized cost
of first doing O(D) work, and
then splaying a node of depth
D is actually O(log(n)), where n is
the total number of nodes in the tree.
And we'll prove this later, but using it,
we can analyze our splay tree operations.
And the basic idea is that,
if you have to do a lot of work and
then splay a very deep node, we're going
to be able to pay for that work by
the fact that the splay operation will
rebalance our tree in some useful way.
And that will pay for it and so
amortized cost will only be O(log(n)).
Okay, using this,
how do we implement our operations?
So a splay tree find is
actually very simple.
First we find the node in
the way we normally would.
We then splay the node that we found and
then return it.
Pretty simple.
So how does the analysis work?
Now the node, remember,
might not be at small depth.
It could be at depth D, or
D could be as big as N.
We then do O(D) work to find the node
because that's how long
a find operation takes.
We then run a splay, so we did O(D) work,
and then we splayed a node of depth D.
And so the amortized cost is O(log(n)) for
this operation, which is what we want.
Now, the idea here is that you're paying
for the work again of finding this N
by splaying it back to the root
to rebalance the tree.
And so, if the node was really deep,
you did do a lot of work.
But you also did some
useful rebalancing work,
which means you're not going to
have to keep doing a lot of work.
Now, there's a very important
point to note here,
that it could be that we
were doing this search,
you fail to find a node with exactly
that key that you were looking for.
But when this happens,
you still have to splay the closest
node that you found in this operation.
Because otherwise, what's happening
is your operation did O(D) work, but
since you're not doing a splay,
there's nothing to amortize against.
You actually just spent O(D) work.
What you need to do is if you're doing
this big, deep search, you have to pay for
it by rebalancing the tree.
And you have to,
therefore, splay whatever node you found,
even if it does not have the right key.
Okay, so that's fine.
Let's talk about Insert.
Insert, it turns out, is also really easy.
First, you insert a node in
the same way that you would before.
And that's O of depth much work.
And then you run the splay tree find.
You find the node again, and
you splay it to the top.
It all works.
Now to get deletes to work, there's
actually a pretty clever way to do it.
If you splay your node and
successor both to the top of the tree,
you end up with this sort of
third diagram in this picture.
And you'll note that if we want
to get rid of the red node,
all we have to do is sort of promote the
blue node, its successor, into its place.
Because of the way this works out,
the blue node will never have a left
child, and things will just work.
So the code for delete is you splay
the successor of N to the root, you then
splay N to the root, and then we just need
to remove N and promote its successor.
So we let L and R be the left and
right children of N, and
basically what we have to do is we need
to make R to become L's new parent and
L R's new child, and
then set R to be the root of the tree.
And once we've rearranged a few pointers,
everything works.
Now, there is one special case here,
which is what if N is the largest key in
the entire tree, there is no successor,
you need to do something
slightly different.
I'll leave that to you to figure out.
Finally, let's talk about
the split operation.
Now, the split is actually also
very nice with splay trees.
The point is there's one case
where split entry is really easy.
It's if the key at which you're
supposed to split is right at the root.
Because then all you need to do
is you need to split things into
two subtrees by just
breaking them off the root.
And so, but with the splay tree,
it's really easy to make any
node that we want be the root.
So what we're going to do is we're going
to do a search to find the place at which
we are supposed to do our split.
Take whatever node we found,
splay it to the root, and
then we're just going to break our tree
into two pieces right at the root.
So to see pseudocode for
this, we're going to let
N be what we find when we search for
the x that we're trying to split at.
We then Splay N to the root.
Now if N's key is bigger than x,
we have to cut off the left subtree.
If the key is less than x,
we cut off the right subtree.
And if the key is actually equal to x,
well,
the x that we're trying to
split is actually in the tree.
So, I mean, you might do one, or the
other, depending on if you actually want
to keep the node in the tree, or
maybe you want to throw it away, and
we just want to return the left
subtree and the right subtree.
Now just to be clear, if we want to say,
cut off the left subtree, all we have to
do is we let L be the left child, and
we just have to sort of break the pointer
between our node and in its left child,
so that they're now separate trees.
And we just return L and
N as the two roots.
So that's how we do a split.
To do a merge, we basically have
to do the opposite of this.
And the idea is that it's very easy to
merge two trees together when you sort of
have this element that's in between
them right up there at the root.
And once again, there's an easy
way to do this with splay trees.
You just find the largest element of
the left subtree, you splay it to the top,
and then just attach the right
subtree as a child of that node.
And then you're done.
So, in summary, splay trees.
Using this, we can perform actually
all the operations that we wanted very
simply in an O(log(n))
amortized time per operation.
And so
this provides a very clean way to do this.
We left out some things
in the analysis though.
So if you'd like to see
really what the math behind
how we can show all of these things work,
please come back for the next lecture.