Hello everybody.
Welcome back.
Today we're still talking about splay
trees and we're actually going to go into
a little bit of the math behind
analyzing their run times.
So remember last time we analyzed
splay trees and in order to do so
we needed the following important result,
that the amortized cost of doing O(D)
work and then splaying a node of depth
D is actually O(log(n)) where n is
the total number of nodes in the tree.
And today we're going to prove that.
So to do this of course we need
to amortize, we need to pay for
this extra work by doing something
to make the tree simpler.
And the way we talk about this being
simple is we're going to pick a potential
function, and so that if we do
a lot of work it's going to pay for
itself by decreasing this potential.
And it takes some cleverness to find
the right one and it turns out more or
less the right potential
function is the following.
We define the rank of a node N to be
the log of the size of it's subtree,
where the size of it's subtree is just the
number of nodes that are descendants of
N in that tree.
Then the potential function for
the tree is P is just the sum over all
nodes N in the tree of the rank of N.
Now to get a feel for what this
means if your tree is balanced, or
even approximately balanced,
potential function should be approximately
linear in the total number of the nodes.
But if on the other hand,
it's incredibly unbalanced,
say just one big chain of nodes, then the
potential could be as biggest N(log(n)).
And so, a very large potential function
means that your tree is very unbalanced.
And so,
if you are decreasing the potential,
it means that you're rebalancing the tree.
So what we need to do is we need to see
what happens when you perform a splay
operation, what does it do
to the potential function.
Now, to do that,
the splay operation is composed of
a bunch of these little operations,
zig, zig zigs and zig zags and
we want to know for each operation
what does that do to the potential.
So for
example when you perform a zig operation
how does the potential function change?
Well you'll note that other than N and
P, these two nodes that were
directly affected, none of the nodes
have their subtrees change at all.
And therefore the ranks of all
the other nodes stay exactly the same.
So the change in potential
function is just the new rank of
N plus the new rank of P, minus the old
rank of N and the old rank of P.
Now, the new rank of N and
the old rank of P are actually the same,
because each of those had subtrees
that were just the entire tree.
And so this is just the new rank
of P minus the old rank of N and
it's easy to see that's at most, the newer
rank of N minus the old rank of N.
That's not so bad.
Now let's look at the zig-zig analysis
which is a little bit trickier.
So here the change in the potential is
the new rank of N plus the new rank of
P plus the new rank of Q
minus the old rank of N, and
the old rank of P and the old rank of Q.
So the new ranks minus all the old ranks.
Now the claim here is that
this is at most 3 times
the new rank of N minus
the old rank of N minus 2.
And to prove this we
need a few observations.
The first thing is that the rank of
N is equal to the old rank of Q and
that this term is actually bigger than
any other term in our expression.
And that's simply because, I mean, both
of these nodes what are their subtrees?
Well, it's N, P and Q.
And then the red, green,
blue and black subtrees.
They're the same subtrees, the same size.
They've got the same rate.
But the next thing to note is that the old
size of N's subtree and the new size of
Q's subtree, when you add them together,
it's going to be the red subtree,
the green subtree, the blue subtree, and
the black subtree plus two more nodes.
And that's actually one less than the size
of either of these two big terms.
And what that says,
when you take logarithms,
you can actually get that the size,
the rank of N, the old rank of N
plus the new rank of Q is at most
twice the new rank of N minus 2.
Because they're sort
of half the size each.
And therefore, if you combine
these inequalities together,
you can actually get the one that
we wanted on the previous slide.
Now, the zig-zag analysis
is pretty similar to this.
Here, you can show the change in
potential is at most twice the new rank
of N minus the old rank of N minus 2.
Okay, great.
So now we perform
an entire splay operation.
So we splay once, and then again,
and then again, and then again,
all the way up until we finally have
the final version of N that's the root.
And we want to know what the total
change in the potential function is over
all of these little teeny steps.
Well what is it?
Well it's at most the sum of the changes
in potentials from each steps.
The last one you have three
times the final rank of N
minus the rank of N one step before that,
minus two.
You add to that the rank of N one step
before the N minus the rank of N two steps
before the N minus 2.
Then you add three times the rank of N two
steps before the end minus the rank three
steps before the N minus 2 and
so on and so forth.
And this sum actually telescopes.
The rank of N one step before the end
there are two versions of it and
they cancel.
The rank two steps before the end,
there are two terms that cancel and
so on and so forth.
And the only terms that are left is well
you've got three times the rank of N at
the very end of your splay operation,
minus the rank of N at the very
beginning of your splay operation,
and then for each of these steps, for
each two levels the N went up the tree,
you have this copy of -2.
So that's minus the depth of the node app.
And so the change in potential is
just O of log(n) minus the depth,
which is minus the work that you did.
And note it's O of log(n)
because the rank of n is at most
log of the total number
of nodes in the tree.
And so if you add the change in potential
to the amount of work that you did,
you get out O of log(n).
And so the amortized cost of
your O of D work plus your splay
operation is just O of log(n).
Now, that shows there our splay trees
runs an O of log(n) amortized time per
operation.
And if that was all you could say there is
nothing really to be too excited about.
I mean it gets about the same run time,
maybe it's a little bit
easier to implement.
It's a little bit more annoying
because it's only amortized rather
than worst case.
Some operations will be
much more expensive than
log(n) even if on average
the operations are pretty cheap.
But another great thing is that
splay tree has also have many
other wonderful properties.
For example, if you assign weights
to the nodes in any way such
that the sum of all nodes of
their weight is equal to one,
the amortized cost of accessing a node
is actually just O(log(1/wt (N))).
And that means that if you spend a lot of
time accessing high weight nodes it might
actually be much quicker that
log(N) time per operation.
And so, and note that this run time bound
holds no matter what weights you assign.
You don't need to change
the algorithm based on the weights.
This bound happens automatically.
And so if there are certain nodes that get
accessed much more frequently than others,
you could just sort of artificially
assign them very high weights and
then that actually means that your
display tree automatically runs
faster than log(n) per operation.
Another bound is the dynamic finger bound.
The amortized cost of accessing
a node is O(log(D + 1)) where here,
D is the distance in terms of the ordering
between nodes between the last access and
the current access.
So if say you want to list all the nodes
in order or search for all the nodes
in order, it's actually pretty fast
to do a display tree because D is 1.
It's a constant per operation
rather than O of log(n).
Another bound is the working set bound.
The amortized cost of accessing
a node N is O(log(t+1)) where t is
the amount of time that has elapsed
since that node N was last accessed.
And what that means, for
example, is that if you tend
to access nodes that you've
accessed recently a lot.
So you access one node
pretty frequently and
then they move to accessing
a different node pretty frequently,
then this actually does a lot better
again than O of log(n) per operation.
Finally we've got what's known as
the dynamic optimality conjecture.
And this says if you give me any list of
splay tree operations, inserts, finds,
deletes whatever.
And then you build the best
possible dynamic search tree for
that particular sequence of operations.
You can have it completely optimized to
perform those operations as best possible.
The conjecture says that if you run
a splay tree on those operations it does
worse by at most a constant factor.
And that's pretty amazing.
It would say that if there is any binary
search three that does particularly well
on a sequence of operations than at
least conjecturally a splay tree does.
So the conclusion here is that
splay trees, they're pretty fast,
they require only O of log(n) amortized
time per operation which, remember,
it can be a problem if you're worried
that the occasional operation might take
a long time.
But in addition to this, splay trees can
actually be much better if your input
queries have extra structure, if you call
some nodes more frequently than others, or
you tend to call nearby nodes to the ones
that you most recently accessed, and
things like that.
But that's actually it for today.
That's a splay tree, that's why
they're considered to be useful.
And that's this course,
I really hope that you've enjoyed it,
I hope you'll come back for
our next course and best of luck.