We're going to start our divide and
conquer algorithms
with what might be considered
a degenerate form of divide and conquer:
Searching in an unsorted array using
linear search.
Here's an example of an array.
To find a particular element of the array,
we look at the first element, if it's not
there, we look at the second element.
We continue until we either find
the element we're interested in, or
until we reach the end of the array.
This same type of search is also used
to free elements that are stored
in a linked list.
Let me describe a real-life
use of linear search.
Twenty years ago I did consulting for
a company developing software for
one the first hand-held computers,
the Apple Newton.
The application translated words
between any two of the languages:
English, French, Italian,
German, or Spanish.
Its data was stored in
five parallel arrays.
So for example,
car was in English at the second position.
In Spanish, car is auto, so
the second position of
the Spanish array contained auto.
The program would take the user's input
word along with from and to languages.
Then it would search through
the corresponding from array, English for
example with trying to translate
car from English to Spanish.
If it found a match,
it returned the element at the same
index location and target language.
With a small dictionary of three words,
as in this example,
this linear search is quick.
However, I was brought in as a consultant
to speed up the application.
When users clicked on the translate
button, it'd take seven to ten seconds
to retrieve the translated word, an
eternity as far as the user was concerned.
There were about 50,000
words in the dictionary, so
on average it took 25,000 word
checks in order to find a match.
The next video, I'll show you how we sped
up this application using binary search.
The problem statement for
linear search is as follows:
given an unsorted array with n elements
in it and a key k, find an index,
i of the array element that's equal to k.
If no element array is equal to k,
the output should be NOT_FOUND.
Note that we say an index rather
than the index, to account for
the fact that there may be
duplicates in the array.
This might seem pedantic,
but it's important
to be as careful as possible in
specifying our problem statement.
The well known solution to this
problem is a linear search.
Iterate through the array until you
find the chosen element. If you reach
the end of the array and haven't yet
found the element, return NOT_FOUND.
We can construct a divide and conquer
recursive algorithm to solve this problem.
Our recursive function
will take four parameters:
A, the array of values;
low, the lower bound of
the array in which to search;
hgh, the upper bound of the array
in which to search; and k,
the key for which to search.
It will return either: an index
in the range low to high,
if it finds a matching value; or
NOT_FOUND, if it finds no such match.
As with all recursive solutions, we'll
need to accurately handle the base case.
In particular, base cases for this problem
will be either: be given an empty array, or
finding a match on the first element.
The subproblem is to search through
the sub array constructed by
skipping the first element.
We'll recursively search
through that smaller sub array,
and then just return the result
of the recursive search.
Although this is a recursive
routine that breaks the problem into
smaller problems,
some would argue that this shouldn't
be called divide and conquer.
They claim that a divide and
conquer algorithm should divide
the problem into a smaller subproblem,
where the smaller subproblem is some
constant fraction of the original problem.
In this case the su-problem isn't 50%,
or 80%, or
even 95% of the original problem size.
Instead, it's just one smaller
than the original problem size.
I don't know, maybe we should
call this algorithm
subtract and conquer rather than
divide and conquer.
In order to examine the runtime of our
recursive algorithm it's often useful to
define the time that the algorithm takes
in the form of a recurrence relation.
A recurrence relation defines a sequence
of values in terms of a recursive formula.
The example here shows the recursive
definition of the values
in the Fibonacci sequence.
You can see that we defined the value for
the n'th Fibonacci as the sum
of the preceding two values.
As with any recursive definition,
we need one or more base cases.
Here, we define base cases when
evaluating F(0) and F(1).
From this recursive definition, we've
defined values for evaluating F(n) for
any non-negative integer, n.
The sequence starts with 0, 1,
1, 2, 3, 5, 8, and continues on.
When we're doing run-time analysis for
divide and conquer algorithms,
we usually define a recurrence
relation for T(n).
where T stands for the worst time taken for
the algorithm, and
n is the size of the problem.
For this algorithm, the worst-case
time is when an element isn't found
because we must check every
element of the array.
In this case we have a recursion for
a problem of size n
which consists of a subproblem of size n
minus one plus a constant amount of work.
The constant amount of work
includes checking high versus low,
checking A at low equals key, preparing
the parameters for the recursive call,
and then returning
the result of that call.
Thus the recurrence is T(n)
equals T(n-1) plus c,
where c is some constant.
The base case of the recursion is in an empty
array, there's a constant amount of work:
checking high less than low and
then returning NOT_FOUND.
Thus T(0) equals c.
Let's look at a recursion tree
in order to determine how
much total time the algorithm takes.
As is normal, we're looking
at worst-case runtime,
which will occur when no
matching element is found.
In a recursion tree, we show the problem
along with the size of the problem.
We see that we have an original problem of
size n which then generates a subproblem
of size n-1, and so on all the way
down to a subproblem of size zero:
an empty array. The work column shows the
amount of work that is done at each level.
We have a constant amount of work at each
level which we represent by c, a constant.
Alternatively, we could have represented
this constant amount of work
with big theta of one.
The total work is just the sum
of the work done at each level
that's a summation from zero to n of
a constant c.
Which is n plus one times c,
or just big theta of n.
This analysis seems overly complicated for
such a simple result.
We already know that searching through n elements
of the array will take big theta of n time.
However, this method of recurrence
analysis will become more useful
as we analyze more complicated
divide and conquer algorithms.
Many times a recursive algorithm is
translated into an iterative one.
Here we've done that for
the linear search.
We search through the elements of array
A from index low to index high.
If we find a match,
we return the associated index.
If not, we return NOT_FOUND.
To summarize, what we've done is one:
created a recursive solution;
two: defined a corresponding
recurrence relation, T;
three: solved T of n to determine
the worst-case runtime; and
four: created an iterative
solution from the recursive one.
What you've seen in this video,
then, is an example
of a trivial use of our divide and conquer
technique in order to do a linear search.
In our next video we'll
look at a non-trivial use
of the divide an conquer technique for
searching in a sorted array:
the well known binary search.