Let's see how basic operations
work with binary max heaps.
What is particularly easy for
binary max heaps is finding the maximum
value without extracting it.
I mean,
it is easy to implement GetMax operation.
Well, recall that the main property of
that binary max heap tree is the following.
For each edge its top value is greater or
equals than its bottom value.
this means that if we go from
bottom to top now in our trees, the
values can only increase.
This in particular means that the maximum
value is stored at the root of our tree.
So just to implement GetMax,
we just return the value at
the root of our tree.
And this takes us just
a constant time of course.
Now let see how inserting a
new element into to the max binary heap works.
So first of all a new element should
be attached somewhere to our tree.
We cannot attach it to
the root in this case for
example, because the root
already has two children.
Therefore, we just attach it to some leaf.
Let's select for example, the leaf
seven and attach a new node to it.
The new node in this case has value 32.
Well, it is still a binary tree.
Right?
Because seven, before attaching seven,
had zero children,
now it has just one child.
So it is still a binary tree.
However, the heap property
might potentially be violated.
And it is violated actually in this case,
right?
Which is shown by this red edge.
So for this red edge the value
of it parent which is seven,
is less than the value
of its child which is 32.
So we need to fix it somehow.
So to fix it we just allow
that the new element to sift up.
So this new element has value 32,
which is relatively large with respect
to all other elements in this tree,
so we need to move it
somewhere closer to the root.
So the process of moving it closer
to the roof is called sifting up.
So the first thing to do is we
need to fix this problematic edge.
To fix it,
we perform the following simple operation.
We just swap the corresponding
two elements.
In this case, we'll swap seven and 32.
After they swap,
there is no problem on this edge.
However, it might be the case that
the new element 32 is still smaller.
Is still greater than its parent and
this is the case, in our toy example.
So the parent of 32 is now 29,
which is smaller than 32, so
we still need to fix this red problem.
And we just repeat this process,
we again swap the new element
with its parent, right?
So we swap it and
now we see that the property is
satisfied for
all edges in this binary tree.
So what we've just done is that we
let the new element to sift up.
And what is important to note here is that
we maintained the following invariant,
that the heap property at any point of
time of sifting the new element up,
the heap property is violated on at
most one edge of our binary tree.
So and if we see that
there is a problematic edge,
we just swap its two elements, right?
And each time during this process the
problematic node gets closer to the root.
This in particular implies that
the number of swaps required is at most
the height of this tree.
Which in turn means that the running
time of insertion procedure,
as well as the running time
of the sifting up procedure,
in this case is big O of the tree height.
Now let's see how the extract max
procedure works for binary max heaps.
First of all, recall that we already
know that the maximum value is stored
at the root of the tree.
However, we cannot just take and
detach the root node because it
will leave two sub trees, right?
So we need to somehow preserve
the structure of the tree.
What is easy to detach from
a binary tree is any leaf.
So let's do the following,
let's select any leaf of our tree and
let's replace the root with this leaf.
So in this case
this produces the following tree.
This potentially might
violate the heap property.
And in this case,
this does violate the property.
So the new root 12,
is less than both its children.
So the property is violated on two edges.
So 12 is a relatively
small number in this case.
So we need to
move it down to the leaves.
Great, so for
this we will implement a new procedure,
which is called SiftDown, okay?
So, similarly to SiftUp,
we are going to replace,
to replace the new element
with one of its children.
In this case we have a choice actually,
we can replace it either with its
left child or with its right child.
By thinking a little bit we
realize that it will make
more sense to replace it with
the left child in this case.
Because the left child is larger than the
right child, because after this, after we
replace 12 with 29, the right problematic
edge will be fixed automatically, right?
So this is how we are going to
perform the SiftDown procedure.
Once again, we select the largest
of two child and we replace.
the problematic
node with this larger child.
As you can see, the right problematic
edge is fixed automatically.
The left edge is also fixed,
just because we swapped two elements.
However, the new problematic node
might introduce new problems,
right closer to the bottom of the tree.
Now we see that there is
still a problematic edge, so
in this case, we have just one edge so
12 is smaller than 14, but
it is greater than seven, so
we are safe in the right tree.
In this case we swap 14 with 12 and
after that we just get a tree where
the property is satisfied on all edges.
So once again we maintain
the following invariant.
At each point of time we have
just one problematic node, and
we always solve the problematic node.
With the larger one of its children, so
that to fix both problematic edges.
Right?
And
the problematic node always
gets closer to the leaf,
which means that the total running
time of the extract max as well as
the sift down procedures is
proportional to the tree height.
Now, when we have implemented both
procedures, sifting up and sifting down,
it's not so difficult to implement
also the ChangePriority procedure.
So assume that we have an element for
which we would like to
change its priority.
This means that we are going
either to decrease its priority or
increase its priority.
Well, to fix the potential
problems that might be introduced
by changing its priority, we are going to
call either sifting up or sifting down.
Well, let me illustrate this
again on the toy example.
Assume that we are going to change
the priority of this leaf 12.
So we've just changed it.
We just increased the priority
of this element to 35.
In this case, we potentially introduced
some problems and we need to fix some.
Well we see that 35 is a relatively
large number which means that we need to
sift it up.
So we need to move it closer to the root.
So to do this we just
call SiftUp procedure.
Which repeatedly swaps
the problematic node
with its parent, so
in this case this will produce
the following sequence of swaps.
First will swap 35 with 18 this
gives us the following picture,
we see there is still a problem 35 is still
larger than its parent so we swap it again.
Now we see that 35 is
smaller than its parent.
And actually, the heap property
is satisfied for all edges.
Once again, what is important in this
case is that at each point of time,
the heap property is violated on
at most one edge of our tree.
So since our problematic node always
gets closer to the root at each step,
I mean, after each swap.
We conclude that the running time of
change priority procedure is also at most
Big O of the tree height.
There is an elegant way of removing
an element from the binary max heap.
Namely it can be done just by calling
two procedures that we already have.
So I assume that we have a particular
element that we're going to remove.
So the first step to do is we just change
its priority to plus infinity, that is,
to a number which is definitely larger than
all the elements in our binary MaxHeap.
When we call it, the change priority
procedure will sift this element
to the top of our tree,
namely to the root of our tree.
Then to remove this element it is enough
to call the extract max procedure.
So in this particular example
it will work as follows.
So assume that we're going to
remove the element 18,
which is highlighted here on this slide.
So we first change it's
priority to infinity.
Then the ChangePriority procedure
calls the SiftUp procedure.
This procedure realizes that there is,
that the property is violated on this edge.
And swaps these two elements.
Then it swaps the next two elements and
each at this point well this,
this node that we're going
to remove is at the root.
Well, to remove this node,
we just call the ExtractMax procedure.
So recall that the first step
of ExtractMax is to replace
the root node with any leaf.
So let's select, for example, 11.
So we replace,
we replace the root with 11.
Then we need to call sift down, just to
let this new root go closer to the leaves.
Well, in this case,
11 will be replaced first by 42,
then there is still a problem
on the edge from 11 to, to 18.
So we swap 11 with 18 and
finally we swap 11 with 12.
Well, once again since everything
boils down just to two procedures.
First is change priority.
And the second one is extracting the max.
And they all, they both work in time
proportional to the tree height.
So we conclude that the running time of
the remove procedure is also, at most,
Big O of the tree height.
So to summarize,
we were able to implement all
max binary heap operations in time
proportional to the tree height, and
the GetMax procedure even works in
constant time in our current implementation.
So we definitely would like
to keep our trees shallow.
And this will be the subject
of our next video.