Our goal in this video is
to design a way of keeping
the height of our binary max heap shallow.
Well, what is a natural approach to
create a tree out of n given nodes,
whose height is as small as possible.
Well, it is natural to require that all
the levels are fully packed, right.
This leads us to a notion
of a complete binary tree.
By definition a binary tree is called
complete if all its levels are filled
completely.
Except possibly the last one where
we require additionally that all
the nodes at this last level
are in left most positions.
Let me illustrate this
with a few small examples.
So this is a complete binary tree.
This is also a complete binary tree, and
this is also a complete binary tree.
So this is a binary complete tree too.
And this is our first example of
a binary tree which is not complete.
Well it is not complete
because on the last level
the two nodes shown here are not
in the left most positions.
This is also not a complete binary tree.
This binary tree is also not complete
because well this child is missing here,
right.
And this is also an example of
a binary tree which is not complete.
The first advantage of complete
binary trees is straightforward, and
it is exactly what we need actually.
Namely, the height of any complete binary
tree with n nodes is O(log n).
Intuitively, this is clear.
A complete binary tree with n
nodes has the minimum possible
height over all binary trees with n nodes.
Well, just because all the levels of
this tree, except possibly the last one,
are fully packed.
Still let me give you a formal proof.
Well, for
this consider our complete binary tree and
let me show a small example.
So I assume that this is
our complete binary tree.
So in this case, n = 10 and
the number of levels, l = 4.
Well, let's first do the following thing,
let's complete the last level.
And let's denote the result in
number of nodes by n prime.
In this case in particular
the number of nodes
in the new tree is equal to 15.
Well the first thing to note
is that n prime is at most 2n.
Well this is just because in such
a tree where all levels including
the last one are fully packed,
the number of nodes on each level
is equal to the number of nodes on
all the previous levels minus one.
Okay, so for example here the number
of nodes on the last level is 8,
and the number of nodes on
all previous levels is 7.
So we added at most seven vertices.
Now, when we have such a tree where
all the levels are packed completely,
it is easy to relate the number of
levels with the number of vertices.
Namely with the number of nodes.
Namely n prime = to 2 to the l- 1.
This allows us to conclude that l
= binary logarithm of n prime + 1.
Now, recall that n prime is at most 2n,
which allows us to write that l
is at most binary logarithm of 2n + 1
which is of course, O(log n).
The second advantage of
complete binary trees is not so
straightforward, but
fortunately it is still easy to describe.
To explain it,
let's consider again a toy example,
I mean a complete binary tree
shown here on this slide.
Let's enumerate all its nodes
going from top to down, and
on each level from left to right.
So this way the root receives number 1,
to its children receive numbers 2 and
3 and so on.
So it turns out that such a
numbering allows for each vertex,
number i for example, to be specific,
to compute the number of its parent and
the numbers of each children using
the following simple formulas.
Once again, if we have a node number i,
then its parent has
number i divided by 2 and
rounded down while its two children
have numbers 2i and 2i + 1.
To give a specific example,
I assume that i = 4,
which means that we are speaking
about about this node.
Then to find out the number of its parent,
we need to divide i by 2, this gives us 2.
And indeed, vertex number 2 is
a parent of vertex number 4.
While to find out the numbers
of two children of this node,
we need to multiply i by 2,
this gives us this node and
multiply i by 2 + 1 and
this gives us this node.
And these two nodes are indeed
children of vertex number 4, right?
And this is very convenient.
This allows us to store the whole
complete binary tree just in an array.
So we do not need to store any links for
each vertex to its parent and
to its two children.
So these links can be
computed just on the fly.
Again to give a concrete example, assume
that we are talking about vertex number 3.
So in this case i = 3.
To find out the number of its parent,
we just divide i by 2 and round down.
So this gives us vertex number 1, and
indeed vertex number 1 is
a parent of the vertex number 3.
And to find out the numbers
of its two children,
we just multiply i by 2 and
also multiply i by 2 and add 1.
This gives us, in this case,
vertices number 6 and vertex number 7.
So, and we know its indices in theory.
Okay, we have just discussed two
advantages of complete binary trees, and
it would be too optimistic to expect that
these advantages come to us at no cost.
So we need to pay something, and our cost
is that we need to keep the tree complete.
Right, we need to ensure
that at each point of time,
our binary tree is complete.
Well, to ensure this,
let's just ask ourselves
what operations change
the shape of our tree.
Essentially, these are only two
operations, namely insert and
extract max.
So, two operations, sift up and sift down,
they actually do not change
the shape of the tree.
They just swap some two
elements inside the tree.
Another operation which actually
change the shape is remove an element,
however, it does so
by calling the ExtractMax procedure.
So on the next slide we will explain
how to modify our Insert and
ExtractMax operations so that they
preserve completeness of our tree.
To keep a tree complete when we insert
something into a complete binary tree,
we just insert the new element,
as a leaf, to the leftmost vacant
position on the last level.
Well, an example is given here.
So, we insert element 30 just to the right
of the last element on the last level.
Okay, then we need to let this new element
sift up so we perform a number of swaps.
So 30 is swapped with 14,
then still there is a problem, so
30 is greater than 29,
so we swap it again.
Okay, now the property of the heap
is satisfied for all the edges.
Well, when we need to
extract the maximum value,
recall that we first replace
the root by some leaf.
Well in this case,
to keep the tree complete,
let's just select the last
leaf at the last level.
In this case it is 14.
So we'll replace 42 with 14,
and then, again,
perform a number of swaps required
to satisfy the property of the heap.
Okay, so in this case, 14 is swapped
with 30, and then 14 is swapped with 29.
This gives us a correct heap whose
underlying tree is a complete binary tree.
Well so far, so good, we now know how
to maintain the tree complete and
how to store it in an array.
In the next video we will show
the full pseudocode of the binary
max heap data structure.