In this video,
we provide the full pseudocode of
the binary max heap data structure.
Here we will maintain
the following three variables.
H is an array where our heap will stay.
MaxSize is the size of this array, and
at the same time, it is the maximum
number of nodes in our heap.
And size is the actual size of our heap.
So size is always at most maxSize.
So let me give you an example.
In this case,
we're given a heap of size 9.
And it is stored in the first nine
cells of our array H whose size is 13.
In particular, you may notice that
there are some values here, and
it is actually some garbage.
We just don't care about any
values that stay to the right
of the position numbered 9.
So our heap occupies the first
nine positions in the array.
Also let me emphasis once again
that we store just the array H and
also variables size and maxSize.
So this tree is given to us implicitly.
Namely, for any node,
we can compute the number of its parent
and the number of its two children.
And we can compute it and access
the corresponding value in this array.
For example, if we have no number three,
then we can compute
the index of its left child,
which is 2 multiplied by 3.
So the value of its right child is 18.
These implementations showing
how to find given a node i,
the index of the parent of i and
two children of i.
So they just implement our
formulas in a straightforward way.
To sift element i up, we do the following.
While this element is not the root,
namely,
i is greater than 1, and while the value
of this node is greater than the value
of its parent, we do the following.
We swap this element with his parent.
So this is done on this line.
And then we proceed with this new element.
I mean, we assign i to be equal to
Parent of i and go back to this while loop,
and we do this until
the property is satisfied.
To sift an element number i down, we first
need to select the direction of sifting.
Namely, if element number i is smaller
than one or two of its children,
we first need to select the largest
one of its two children, right?
So this is done here.
So initially, we assign to
the variable maxIndex the value of i.
Then we compute the index of
the left child of the node number i.
Then in the next if loop we first check
whether i indeed has a left child.
This is done in the following check.
We check whether l is at most size.
Namely, whether l is an index
which is in our heap, okay?
Then if H of l is greater
than H of maxIndex,
we assign maxIndex to be equal to l, okay?
Then we do the same with the right child.
We first compute its index, then we check
whether this index is indeed in our heap.
Then we check whether
the value in this node
is greater than the value of
our current maximum index.
And if it is,
then we update the value of maxIndex.
And finally, if the node i is not
the largest one among itself and
the two of its children, namely,
if i is not equal to maxIndex,
then we do the following.
We swap element number i with
element number maxIndex.
It is done here.
And then we continue sifting down
the just-swapped element.
Okay, so, this is done recursively.
However, it is not so
difficult to avoid using recursion here,
just by introducing a new while loop.
To insert a new element with priority p in
our binary max heap, we do the following.
We first check whether
we still have room for
a new element,
namely whether size is equal to maxSize.
If it is equal,
then we just return an error.
Otherwise, we do the following.
We increase size by 1,
then we assign H of size to be equal to p.
At this point we add a new leaf in our
implicit tree to the last level, to
the leftmost position on the last level.
And finally, we call SiftUp to
sift this element up if needed.
To extract the maximum value
from our binary max heap,
we first store the value of the root
of our tree in the variable result.
So result is assigned to be equal H of 1.
Then we replace the root by the last leaf,
by the rightmost leaf on the last level,
so this is done by assigning H
of 1 to be equal to H of size.
Okay?
Then we decrease the value of size by 1,
just to show that
the last leaf is not in our tree anymore.
And finally, we call SiftDown for
the root, because it was replaced by
the last leaf, which is potentially
quite small and needs to be sifted down.
And the last instruction in our
pseudocode is, we return the result.
That means the value which was
initially in the root of our tree.
Removing an element.
So as we've discussed already,
this actually boils down to calling
two procedures that we already have.
Once again, to remove element number i,
we do the following.
First, we change its priority
to be equal to infinity, so
we assign H of i plus infinity.
Then we SiftUp this node, so this will
move this node to the root of our tree.
And then we just call ExtractMax()
procedure, which will remove the root from
this tree and make necessary changes
in the tree to restore its shape.
Finally, to change the priority of
a given node i to the given value p,
we do the following.
We first assign H of i to p, okay?
Then we check whether
the new priority increased
is greater than the old priority or
is smaller.
If it is greater, then potentially we
need to sift up the new node.
So we just call sift up.
If the new priority is smaller,
then we call SiftDown for this node.
Time to summarize.
In this sequence of videos, we considered
the binary max heap data structure,
which is a popular way of implementing
the priority queue data type.
The considered implementation is
quite fast, all operations work
in logarithmic time and GetMax
procedure works even in constant time.
It is also space efficient.
In this data structure, we store a tree,
but this tree is stored implicitly.
Namely, for each node, we do not store
a connection or a link to its parent and
its two children.
Instead, we compute the index of
the corresponding nodes on the fly.
Well, in this case, we store just n
given cells in an array, nothing more.
Okay?
Another advantage of this data structure,
of this implementation,
is that it is really easy to code.
As you've seen, the pseudocode of each
operation is just a few lines of code.
Well, in the next video,
we will show how to use binary
heap to sort data efficiently.