Hello everybody.
Welcome back.
Today we are going to talk about
something a little different.
Up until this point,
we've talked about AVL trees,
we've talked about how to keep them bound,
and how to use them, to implement all of
our binary search tree operations,
and all of log on time pre-operations.
But it turns out that there are a wide
number of different binary search tree
structures that give you different ways
to ensure that your trees are balanced,
there are trepes, there are red block
trees, and today we're going to talk about
splay trees as sort of another example
of the types of things that you can do.
And to motivate this suppose that, well,
if you're searching for random elements,
one after the other, you can actually show
that no matter what splay your use or
data, searcher you use it will always
take at least log n time per operation.
That's actually the best you can do.
However, if some items are searched for
more frequently than others,
you might be able to do better.
If you take the frequently
queried items and
put them close to the root,
those items will be faster to search for.
And some of the other items might
be a little bit slower, but
you should still be okay.
To compare for example,
we've got the unbalanced tree and
the balanced one with the same entires.
But you'll note that 1, 5 and 7 are much
higher up in the unbalanced tree.
Now if we search for random things, if we
search for 11, 11 is much higher up in
the balanced tree than the unbalanced one,
so the unbalanced one is slower there.
But when we search for 1,
it takes a lot less time in
the unbalanced case, we search for
one again, we search for seven, it's again
a lot cheaper in the unbalanced case.
And if we do some sequence
of searches well,
it might turn out that's is actually
cheaper to use the unbalanced tree than
the balanced one if these
elements that tend to be higher
up in the unbalanced tree are searched for
more frequently than other elements.
So the idea here is that we'd like to have
a search tree where we can put the commons
searched common nodes near the root of the
tree so that they are cheaper to look up.
However, very often it will be the case
that we won't know ahead of time
which those commonly searched for
nodes will be.
And so if we, or
in this situation we'll need an adaptive
way to bring them close to the root.
And one natural way to do it is every
time you find a node in your tree
you do something to rearrange the tree and
bring that node up to the root.
And that way at least heuristically,
if there are elements that you search for
frequently, then since you keep
bringing them up to the root,
they'll usually stay
somewhat close to the root.
And they'll be very cheap to access.
So if we want to phrase this in a nice
simple way, one thing that you could
do is if you have your tree and you've
got this node that you searched for,
you could just bring it to the root
by just rotating to the top.
You rotate it up and again and
again and again, and
again until it ends up being the root.
Unfortunately, this simple idea
is actually not very good.
As you'll note,
we started with an unbalanced tree,
but after we did this operation,
the tree is still unbalanced.
And in fact, if you keep doing this
you'll get a bad sequence of inputs.
You can note that there's this loop here,
these five rearrangements of the tree.
Where if you keep doing the appropriate
search and then you rotate the searched
for a note all the way to the top,
they just go in this loop.
And when this happens, if you count
the total time it takes to perform
the sequence of operations, it takes O of
n squared time to perform n operations.
And so the average time per operation
is linear rather than logarithmic
which is far to slow.
So this rotate things up to the top
doesn't actually work very well,
we need something better.
And for this we're going to make
just a slight modification.
The rotate to top algorithm basically
says you look at the node and
its parent and you rearrange them and
then you, again, look at the node and
its parent and rearrange them, and
keep going until you get to the root.
The modification,
instead of just looking at the node and
its parent, you're going to look at the
node and its parent and its grandparent.
And there are a few cases here.
Firstly, there's the case where
the node and its parent and
grandparent are on the same side of it.
This is called the zig-zig case.
Then what we're going to do is we're
going to elevate the node up so
that it's now the parent of
what was its old parent, and
that's on top of what
was the old grandparent.
On the other hand,
it could be that the parent and
grandparent are on opposite sides of the
nodes, what's known as the zig-zag case.
Then you rearrange the tree as follows, so
that the node is now the new parent
parent of its old parent and grandparent.
And finally there's one more case where
the node's parent is actually the root
node, so it doesn't have a grandparent.
And then you actually just
rotate the node up And so
if we combine these operations, together
we get what's called the splay operation.
If you want to splay a node N, and
this is a way of bringing the node
N to the root of the tree,
you determine which case you are in,
the Zig-Zig, the Zig-Zag, or the Zig case.
You apply the appropriate local
operation to rearrange the tree.
And then if the parent of
the node is not null IE,
if the node is not the root of
the tree yet, you splay n again.
And you just keep splaying until
it gets to become the root.
Okay so to make sure that we're
on the same page with this.
If the take the tree up top and
we splay the highlighted node number 4,
which of these three trees, A, B,
or C, do we end up with afterwards?
Well, the answer, here, is A.
So, the point is, we start in this
configuration, we note that we're,
originally, in the zig, zig case,
two, three, and then, four.
So, we elevate four, such that three, and
then, two come down from it, as children.
And then we're in the zig zag case.
One and five are on opposite sides of
four so we elevate four, one and five
are it's new children and three and two
now hang off of one and that is exactly
what we were supposed to end up with and
so that is the answer to this question.
Okay, so
that's what the splay operation is.
Next time we're going to talk about
how to use the splay operation
to rebalance your circuitry, and
how to use it to perform all the basic
binary circuitry operations efficiently.
So I'll see you then.