>> In this video we will use binary
heaps to design the heap sort algorithm,
which is a fast and
space efficient sorting algorithm.
In fact, using priority queues, or
using binary heaps, it is not so difficult
to come up with an algorithm that sorts
the given array in time of analog n.
Indeed, given a rate a of size m,
we do the following.
First, just create
an empty priority queue.
Then, insert all the elements from
our array into our priority queue.
Then, extract the maximum one
by one from the given array.
Namely, we first extract the maximum.
This is the maximum of our array,
so put it to the last position.
Then, extract the next maximum and
put it to the left of the last position,
and so on.
This clearly gives us a sorted array,
right?
So, we know that if we use binary
heaps as an implementation for
priority queue, then all operations
work in logarithmic time.
So, this gives us an algorithm with
a running time big o of n log n.
And recall that this is
asymptotically optimal for
algorithms that are comparison-based.
And this algorithm is clearly
comparison-based, all right?
Also, know that this is a natural
generalization of selection
sort algorithm.
Recall that in selection sort algorithms,
we proceed as follows.
Given an array, we first scan the whole
array to find the maximum value.
So, then we get this maximum value and
swap it with the last element.
Then, we forget about
this last element and
we can see that only n-1 first elements.
Again, by scanning this array,
we find the maximum value, and
we swap it with the last element
in this region, and so on.
So, here in the heap sort algorithm,
instead of finding the maximum
value at each iteration, namely,
we use a smart data structure,
namely a binary heap, right?
So, the only disadvantage
of our current algorithm
is that it uses additional space.
So, it uses additional space
to store the priority queue.
Okay?
So, in this lesson we will show
how to avoid this disadvantage.
Namely, given an array A, we will
first permute its elements somehow,
so that the result in array
is actually a binary heap.
So, it satisfies binary heap property.
And then, we will sort this array, again,
just by calling extract marks and
minus one times.
Building a heap out of a given array
turns out to be surprisingly simple.
Namely, given array A of size
n where there is a following.
We first assign the value of n to is
variable size just to indicate that
we have a heap of size n.
Then, we do the following.
For each i, going down from n over two,
rounded down to one,
we just sift down the i's element.
Let me explain it on a small picture,
why, how we doing this.
So, consider the following.
The following heap, that we actually,
let me remind you,
we do not store it explicitly.
We have just an array,
in this case, of size 15.
So, this is the first node,
the second one, the third one, four,
five, six, seven.
So, if we just can see
the corresponding array of size 15,
and then imagine this
complete binary tree.
Then, the heap property might
potentially be related on many edges.
However, in this tree we have 15 nodes,
so we have 15 sub trees.
And for these sub trees, I mean the root
that the leaves of these of this tree,
the heap property is satisfied for
an obvious reason.
There are no edges in these subtrees.
So, the first node where the property
might be related is node number seven.
So, potentially,
there might be a problem in this subtree.
To fix this problem, we just call
SiftDown for node number seven.
Okay?
After this call,
this small sub tree must be here, right?
Then, we do the same for node number six.
After this call, there are no problems in
the sub tree rooted at node number six.
Then, we do the same for
four i equal to 5 and 4i equal to 4.
Then, we proceed to node number three.
Note that, at this point,
everything is fine in this subtree,
and in this subtree, right?
We already fixed everything
in these two subtrees.
So, to make, to satisfy the heap property
in the sub tree rooted at the node three,
it is enough to call SiftDown
from node number three.
Okay?
Then, we proceed to node number two.
And, again, I have to call and
SiftDown to node number two.
We fix the heap property in this sub tree,
and so on.
So, in this example, actually
the last thing that needs to be done
is to call SiftDown for node number one.
When we are done with this,
we are sure that what we have
in array A is actually a heap.
So, it corresponds to
a complete binary tree
where the heap property is
satisfied on every edge.
Let me repeat slowly what just happened.
So, we, to turn a given array into a heap,
we start repairing the heap properties
in larger and larger subtrees.
So, we start from the leaves,
and go to the root.
Initially, so,
our induction base is that the heap
property is satisfied at all the leaves.
I mean, in all subtrees rooted at
the leaves for an obvious reason.
Any subtree rooted at
the leaf has just one node,
so the property cannot be violated, right?
Then, we gradually go up and
we fix the heap property by
shifting down the current vertex.
And, finally, when we reach a root,
the property is satisfied in
the whole sub-tree, right?
So, this is just a link for
an online visualization.
You can download the slides and
play with this visualization if something
is unclear to you in this process.
Let me now mention that the running
time of this procedure is n log n.
Again, for an obvious reason.
If, so, we use a binary max heap to
implement this SiftDown down procedure.
So, we call SiftDown roughly n over two
times and each call is just log n, right?
So, we have n log n running time.
We already have everything to present, to
present the in-place heap sort algorithm.
Given an array A of size m,
we first build heap out of it.
Namely, we permute its elements so
that the resulting array corresponds to
a complete binary tree, which satisfies
the heap property on every edge.
So, we do this just by
calling BuildHeap procedure.
In particular, this BuildHeap procedure
assigns the value n to the variable size.
Then, we repeat the following
process n minus 1 times.
So, we first, we call that just
after calling to build heap,
the first element of our
array is a maximum element.
Right?
So, we would like to put it to
the last position of our array.
So, we just swap A1 with A of n.
And currently,
A of n is equal to n of size, okay?
So, we swap it.
And then,
we forget about the last element.
So, we decrease size by one.
So, we say that now our heap
occupies the first n-1 element.
And since we swapped the last
element with the first element,
we potentially need to sift
down the first element.
So, we just call SiftDown for
the element number one.
And we proceed in a similar fashion.
I mean, now the heap occupies n-1,
the first n-1 position.
So, the largest element among the first
n-1 element is the first element.
So, we swap it with element n-1.
We forget about the element
n-1 by reducing the size by 1.
And then, see if bounds a first element.
Okay?
So, we repeat this procedure n-1 times,
each time finding
the currently largest element.
So, once again, this is an improvement
of a selection sort algorithm.
And this is an in-place algorithm.
So, once again,
let me state some properties of
the resulting algorithm
which is called Heap Sort.
It is in place.
it doesn't need any additional memory.
Everything is happening
inside the given array A.
So this is in advantage of this algorithm.
Another advantage is that its
learning times is n log n.
It is as simple, as it is optimal.
So, this makes it a good alternative
to the quick sort algorithm.
So, in practice presort is usually faster,
it is still faster.
However, the heap sort algorithm has
worst case running time n log n.
While the quick sort algorithm has
average case running time n log n.
For this reason, a popular approach and
practice is the following.
It is called IntraSort algorithm.
You first run quick sort algorithm.
If it turns out the be slow, I mean,
if the recursion dips, exceeds c log n for
some constant, c, then you stop the
current call to quick sort algorithm and
switch to heap sort algorithm, which is
guaranteed to have running time n log n.
So, in this case, in this implementation,
your algorithm usually,
in most cases it works
like quick sort algorithm.
And even in these unfortunate
cases where it works in larger,
where quick sort has running
time larger than n log n,
you stop it in the right point of time and
switch to HeapSort.
So, this gives an algorithm which in many
cases behaves like quick sort algorithm,
and it has worst case running time.
That must be [INAUDIBLE] n log n.