In this video, we are going to refine
our analysis of the BuildHeap procedure.
Recall that we estimated the running time
of the BuildHeap procedure as n log n,
because it consists actually of roughly
n over 2 calls to SiftDown procedure,
whose running time is log n.
So we get n and over 2 multiplied by
log n, which is of course O(n log n).
Note, however, the following thing.
If we call SiftDown for a node which
is already quite close to the leaves,
then the running time of sifting
it down is much less than log n.
Right?
Because it is already close to the root.
So the number of swaps until
it goes to the leaves cannot
be larger than the height of
the corresponding subtree, okay?
Note also the following thing.
We actually, in our tree, we actually have
many nodes that are close to the root.
So we have just one node, which is
exactly the root, whose height is log n.
We have two nodes whose
height is log n minus 1,
we have four nodes whose height
is log n minus 2, and so on.
And we have roughly n over 4
nodes whose height is just 1.
Okay?
So it raises the question whether
our estimate of the running time
of BuildHeap procedure
was too pessimistic.
We will see on the next slide.
Let's just estimate the running
time of the BuildHeap procedure
a little bit more accurately.
Okay, so this is our heap,
shown schematically.
So this is the last level,
which is probably not completely filled.
But all the leaves on the last
level are in leftmost position.
So, on the very top level,
we have just one node,
and sifting down this node
costs logarithmic time.
At the same time, on the last level,
we have at most n over 2 nodes,
and sifting them down
makes at most one swap.
Actually, we do not need even one swap,
just zero swaps, but
let's be just generous enough and
let's allow one swap.
On the next level,
we have at most n over 4 nodes,
and sifting down for
them costs at most two swaps, and so on.
So if we just compute
the sum of everything, so
we have n over 2 nodes, for
which the cost of
the SiftDown procedure is 1.
We have n over 4 nodes on the next level,
for
which sifting them down
makes at most two swaps.
On the next level, we have n over 8.
Now it's, for each, sifting them down
costs at most three swaps, and so on.
So now let's do the following.
Let's just upper bound this
sum by the following sum.
First of all, let's take
the multiplier n out of this sum.
So what is left here is the following,
1 over 2 + 2 over 4 + 3 over 8 + 4 over
16 + 5 over 32, and so on, right?
So this can be upper-bounded
by the following sum.
So this is just the sum
from i equal to 1 to
infinity of the following fraction,
i divided by 2 to the i.
Once again, in our case, in the running
time of BuildHeap, this sum is finite.
So the maximum value of i is log n.
We do not have any nodes on
height larger than log n.
But we just upper-bound
it by an infinite sum,
where we can see they're just
all possible values of i.
And even for this sum, we will show that
the value of this sum is equal to 2.
Which gives us that the running time of
the BuildHeap procedure is actually at
most 2n.
To estimate the required sum, we start
with a simpler and more well-known sum.
So this is given by the following picture,
and the sum is given here.
So 1 over 2 + 1 over 4 + 1
over 8 + 1 over 16 and so on.
It is equal to 1.
And this can be proved
geometrically as follows.
Consider a segment of length 1.
Now, above the segment,
let's draw a segment
of size 1 over 2, of length 1 over 2.
Okay?
This is half of our initial segment.
What remains is also
a segment of size one-half.
So when we add a segment of size
1 over 4 here,
we actually get 2 times closer
to this vertical line, right?
When we add the next one,
1 over 8, we get, again,
2 times closer than we were before adding
this segment to this vertical line.
When we add 1 over 16,
again, our current distance
to the vertical line is 1 over 16,
and so on.
So if we go to infinity,
we get infinitely closer
to this vertical line,
which means that this sum is equal to 1.
Now, what about the sum
that we need to estimate?
Well, to estimate it, let's first
do the following strange thing.
Let's consider all
the segments shown above, and
let's adjust them by their right end.
So consider the segment 1 shown here.
Now consider the segment
of length 1 over 2,
the segment of length 1 over 4,
the segment of length 1 over 8, and so on.
So we continue this process to infinity.
And we know that the sum of the lengths
of all these segments is equal to 2,
of course.
Now, why we're doing this?
Well, for the following reason.
First, consider the following
vertical lines.
What we need to estimate
is the following sum,
1 over 2 + 2 over 4 + 3 over
8 + 4 over 16 and so on.
Let's see, so
this is a segment of size 1 over 2, okay.
This is two segments of size 1 over 4,
okay.
So this is three segments of
length 1 over 8, and so on.
So if we put another vertical line,
we will get four segments of
size 1 over 16, and so on.
So if we do this to infinity, we will
cover all our segments that are shown
here, which proves that
this sum is equal to 2.
Which in turn proves that
the running time of our BuildHeap
procedure is actually just linear,
it is bounded above by 2n.
Our new estimate for the running time of
the BuildHeap procedure does not actually
improve the running time
of the HeapSort algorithm.
Because the HeapSort algorithm first
builds a heap, and now we know that it can
be done in linear time, but then we
need to extract max n minus 1 times.
So we still have n log n time,
and actually we cannot do better
than n log n asymptotically.
We already know this, because it
is a comparison-based algorithm.
However, this helps to solve a different
problem faster than naively.
So assume that we're given array and
we're given a parameter k,
which is an integer between 1 and n.
And what we would like to do is
not to sort the given array, but
to find the k largest
elements in this array.
Or put it otherwise,
we need to output the last k elements
from the sorted version of our array.
So using the new estimate for
the BuildHeap procedure,
we can actually solve this problem in
linear time, when k is not too large.
Namely, when k is at most
big O(n) divided by log n.
For example, if you have an array of
size n, and you would like just to find
square root of n largest elements, then
you can solve this just in linear time.
So you do not need to sort the whole array
in time n log n to solve this problem.
So linear time is enough to solve it.
And this is how it can be done.
Given an array A of size n and
parameter k, you just build a heap out of
a given array, and then you
extract the maximum value k times.
Right?
So easy.
The running time of this
procedure is the following.
First, you need to build a heap, so
you spend a linear amount of work for
this, then you need to
extract max k times.
For this, you spend k multiplied by log n.
So if k is indeed smaller than n
divided by log n, so let me write it.
So if k is smaller than
n divided by log n,
then this is at most n.
So the whole running
time is at most linear.
So to conclude,
what we've presented here is a heap sort
algorithm which actually
sorts a given array
in place without using any additional
memory and in optimal time n log n.
We also discussed that to build
a heap out of a given array,
it's actually enough to spend
a linear amount of work.