Hi, in this video you will
learn Bellman-Ford's algorithm,
which is an algorithm for
finding shortest paths in graphs
where edges can have negative weight.
Actually, do you remember the naive
algorithm from the previous lesson about
Dijkstra's algorithm?
It turns out, it's not so naive and
Bellman-Ford's algorithm is almost
the same as the naive algorithm.
So, that naive algorithm just
relaxed edges while dist changed,
and at some point it stopped.
We didn't estimate the running
time of that algorithm.
But it turns out, that this algorithm has
benefit over Dijkstra's algorithm that
it works even for negative edge weights.
It is a little bit slower
than Dijkstra's algorithm but
it works in graphs with any edge weights.
So, here is Bellman-Ford's algorithm.
And, it takes as input,
graph and original node again.
And we will find shortest paths from this
original to all the nodes in the graph.
And there is an additional comment
that this algorithm assumes
that there are no negative
weight cycles in G.
Otherwise, it will work still but
it won't return correct distances for
some of the nodes, so.
So, if you know that there are no
negative weight cycles in G,
this algorithm will give
you the answers you need.
If there are negative weight cycles, we'll
discuss later what to do in this case.
So, this algorithm uses
the same dist values and
prev values as b f s and
Dijkstra's algorithm.
It initializes them the same way,
infinitely for distances
apart from the origin node s and
prevs just point to nowhere.
And then we repeat exactly V- 1 times.
V is the number of nodes in the graph.
We relax all the edges
in the graph in order.
So, this is the Bellman-Ford's algorithm.
And actually,
this repeat V- 1 times is excessive.
Actually, we can just return to
the naive algorithm interpretation
when it repeated relaxation of all
the edges until no relaxation is possible.
So, this can be done, and
this will even work faster
than Bellman-Ford, in the case where
there are no negative weight cycles.
However, we write this pseudo-code in
this form just because it is easier
to prove the algorithms
correctness this way.
But, you can just know
that if at some iteration
during these V- y iterations nothing
changed, no edge was actually relaxed,
we can just stop there and
the distances will already be correct.
Now, let's estimate the running
time of this algorithm.
And I state that it's proportional to
the product of number of nodes and
number of edges.
So, that is longer than Dijkstra's
algorithm which was V squared
in terms of array based implementation and
even e + v log v
in terms of heap,
binary heap implementation.
So, this is longer than that but it works
with negative edge weights, so it's good.
So initially, we just initialize dist and
prev values in time proportional
to number of nodes.
And then we'll do V- 1 iteration.
Each iteration takes time
proportional to the number of
edges because relaxation is
a constant time procedure.
So, totally we get time
proportional to VE.
And now, we'll look at an example
of how Bellman-Ford's algorithm
works on a real graph.
So the original is, again, s.
And the numbers 0 and
infinity in blue are the dis values.
And the numbers near the edges
are the edge weights.
So, what we do is we take
all the edges in order
starting from the edge with weight 4.
And we try to relax it.
And we improve the dist value for
A from infinity to 4.
We take the next edge with length 3 and
we improve the dist value
of B from infinity to 3.
We take the edge with weight -2 and
we further improve the dist value for
B from 3 to 2.
Then, we consider edge from A to C and
improve infinity to 8.
Then, we consider edge from B to C and
improve it further from 8 to -1.
Then, we consider edge from B to D and
improve from infinity to 3.
And, we consider the edge from C to D and
improve from 3 to 1.
This is just one iteration
of Bellman-Ford's algorithm.
Now, let's see what happens
on the next iteration.
We consider edge from S to A,
it doesn't improve anything.
This edge, doesn't improve anything.
This edge doesn't improve.
This edge also doesn't improve.
And this doesn't improve.
And this does improve.
And so already, on the second iteration,
nothing can be improved.
So, we actually can stop the algorithm
just after one iteration.
And it will take,
instead of VE operations,
just E operations because we made just
one iteration over all the edges.
And often,
it will work just this way in practice.
But for some graphs, of course,
we'll need many more iterations.
So now, we already know the final
distances that the Bellman-Ford
algorithm returns.
And in the next video,
we will prove that this algorithm
returns correct distances in
the absence of negative weight cycles.