Hi, in this video,
we will prove that Bellman-Ford's
algorithm returns correct distances from
origin node to all the nodes in the graph
in the absence of negative weight cycles.
First, we need the following lemma.
After k iterations of relaxations inside
Bellman-Ford's algorithm for any k,
then if we take any node u,
dist[u] after these k iterations
will be equal to the shortest path
length from S to this node u,
but among all the paths that contain,
at most, k edges.
So not all the possible paths,
just paths which contain 0, 1,
2, or, at most, k edges.
For example, after one iteration,
we state that dist
values of all the nodes will contain
the best possible shortest path,
which consists from 0 or 1 edges.
We'll prove this lemma by
mathematical induction.
And the base case is after 0 iterations,
all the dist values are infinity and
dist[S] = 0.
And this is correct because for
S, there is a path of 0 edges,
which has lines to 0.
And correct distance from S to S is 0.
And dist value is also 0.
And for all the other nodes,
there is no path that contains 0 edges.
And so the shortest path
that contains 0 edges and
goes through those nodes is infinity.
Now the induction step is if we proved for
paths with length at most k,
then we need to prove it for
paths with length at most k + 1.
So, we know that before
iteration number k + 1, dist[u]
is the smallest length of a path from S
to u, which contains at most k edges.
So what do we do on
the k + 1-th iteration?
Each path from S to u goes through
one of the incoming edges,
or like from some node v into node u.
And also, parts of length k+1 go this way.
They go k edges to some known v, and then
they go through this edge from v to u.
So when we try relaxing edge from v to u,
we compare the current dist value,
which is the smallest path length out of
the paths, which contain at most k edges,
we compare it with the smallest
length of a path from S to u,
which contains at most k + 1 edge and
goes through v.
So all parts which contain
at most k+1 edges and
go to u, they go through one
of the incoming edges (v, u).
And so we will compare with
all the possible paths
that contain at most k+1 edges and
go from S to u.
So if initially, we had the best paths,
which contain at most k edges,
after new iteration,
we have the best paths,
which contain at most k+1 edge.
Because we add one last edge
from v to u to the best path,
which contains at most
k edges from S to v.
So the lemma is proved, and
now we have two corollaries.
First that if a graph doesn't have any
negative weight cycles, then Bellman-Ford
algorithm correctly finds all
distances from the starting node S.
Why is that?
Because it does v-1 iterations.
And after v-1 iterations, for
each node, its dist value contains
the shortest path out of all paths
that contain at most v-1 edges.
But if there are no negative cycles,
then any path,
any shortest path contains
at most v-1 edge.
Because if it contains at least v edges,
then there will be a cycle inside it.
And the cycle will be non-negative, so
we can just remove this non-negative cycle
from the path, and
it will improve or stay the same.
So any shortest path contains
just v-1 edges or less, and so
Bellman-Ford algorithm correctly finds
the best shortest paths for each node.
Another corollary is harder,
even if there is a negative
cycle in the graph,
that doesn't mean that there is no correct
distance estimation from origin
to some particular node because
that particular node may be not reachable
from any of the negative weight cycles.
So if there is such node u,
then there's no negative weight
cycle from which it is reachable.
Then Bellman-Ford algorithm will correctly
find distance from after this node
by the same reason because if we
have any shortest path from S to u,
it cannot contain cycles because u is not
reachable from any negative weight cycles.
And so the cycle on the path from S
to u must be non-negative, and so
we can just remove it from the path, and
the path will improve or stay the same.
So, any path from S to u doesn't contain
cycles, and that means that any path from
S to u, which is the shortest path,
has at most v-1 edges.
And this means that Bellman-Ford's
algorithm will return actually a correct
value for the distance from S to u.
And in the next video, we will look into
what to do with the negative cycles when
they're present in the graph and
how to use it for your own profit,
potentially making yourself
a billionaire based on currency exchange