Hi, in this video you will learn to
deal with negative cycles in the graphs.
You will learn to detect whether there
is a negative cycle in the graph and
to find the negative cycle
if you know there is one.
And you will use that in the next
video to achieve infinite arbitrage.
But before that, you really need to learn
to detect negative cycles in the graphs,
and this lemma will help you.
So, it says basically that there is a
negative weight cycle in the graph if and
only if you make one additional
iteration of relaxation
in the Bellman-Ford's algorithm,
and some edge is relaxed.
First, let's prove that
if there is some change
in the last step of Bellman-Ford's
algorithm, then there is a negative cycle.
Assume for the sake of contradiction
that there are no negative cycles.
Then it means that all
shortest paths from S
to any node in the graph contain at most,
V- 1 edges.
We've already discussed that.
If they contain at least V edges,
then there is a cycle.
And this cycle is non-negative so
it can be removed, and
the path will be either improved or
just stay shortest path.
So, know this value can actually
be updated on iteration number V.
Because we already found
the optimal shortest path
length with paths that contain,
at most, V- 1 edges,
and we cannot improve anything after that.
So this is a contradiction with
the fact that the last iteration
actually relaxes some edge.
And so if it does, then there is
a negative cycle in the graph.
Now let's prove, in another side,
that if there is a negative weight cycle,
then there will be a relaxation
on the iteration number V.
Suppose again, for
the sake of contradiction,
that there is a negative weight cycle.
For example,
a cycle of length three a b c a, but
there are no relaxations
on the iteration number V.
Now let's look at the following
three inequalities.
These inequalities basically
state that edges (a, b),
(b,c), and (c,a) cannot be
relaxed on the V-th iteration.
But if we sum these inequalities,
on the left side,
you will have sum of these values for
a, b, and c.
And on the right part,
we will have sum of these values of a, b,
and c plus sum of weights
of the edges of the cycle.
And from this sum of
inequalities that follows,
that the sum of the weights
of edges is non-negative.
But we know that the cycle is
a negative weight cycle, so
this is a contradiction and so
we prove by contradiction that there will
be some relaxation on iteration number V.
So we proved our lemma, and
now we know how to detect negative
weight cycles in the graph.
We just do one additional duration
of Bellman-Ford's algorithm, and
it doesn't increase its asymptotic
complexity, its training time.
And now we can determine whether
the graph is good or bad,
whether it contains negative cycles or
not.
Now, not only to detect what
are the reason negative cycle or
not, also want to find some negative
cycle itself, at least one.
Maybe they are many of them, but
we want some negative cycle.
So first, we still need to run executive V
iterations of Bellman-Ford's relaxation.
And as we know,
if there is negative cycle, then for
some node v, it will be relaxed.
This value will be decreased on
the last iteration, so save this node.
And I state that this node is definitely
reachable from a negative cycle.
Because if it was not reachable
from the negative cycle,
then any shortest path to this node
will contain at most V- 1 edge,
and it won't be improved
on the iteration number v.
So it is reachable from a negative cycle,
and
also it is reachable from a negative
cycle with at most, v steps.
Because if you have
shortest path from s to v,
which contains negative cycle inside,
even if there are more than the edges
from this negative weight cycle to V,
then there is another cycle
on the shortest path.
And it also has to be negative,
because otherwise we can remove
it from the shortest path.
So v is definitely reachable from
a negative cycle, with at most v steps.
And we remember the previous node from
which each node was updated last time.
We store it in the prev values.
So if we go by prev links from V,
and we do that at least three times,
we will be already definitely
on this negative weight cycle.
Because we will already return to
the cycle by at most the steps, and
then we will just go around the cycle for
some amount of duration.
So if we go by V times back,
we will be on the negative cycle.
Then, only thing we need to do is just to
save the position where we started and
then go once around the cycle until we
come to the same node and we will know
that the nodes we saw during this round
trip are the nodes of the negative cycle.
So this is the algorithm, and
it works in the time of Bellman-Ford's
algorithm plus proportional
to the number of nodes.
So basically, the same running
time as Bellman-Ford's algorithm.
So now the question is, again,
if you have a negative cycle in your graph
of minus logarithms, it doesn't mean that
it is always possible to get as many
rubles as you want from $1,000 dollars.
And unfortunately,
that's not always the case.
For example, in this graph,
there is a negative cycle between euro,
British pounds and Norwegian crowns.
And you can check that if you
multiply the conversion rates
on the edges of this triangle
you will get more than one and
it means that, for
one euro can get more than one euro.
And this means in turn that you can get
infinite arbitrages if you just make
trades along the edges of this triangle
for as many times as you want.
But there is no possibility,
in this particular example,
to exchange euros for dollars.
So you cannot exchange rubles for
euros then make many loops around
this negative weight cycle.
And then exchange euros to dollars.
So this is not sufficient, and you cannot
actually get any dollars from rubles,
you cannot get any rubles from
dollars in this particular case.
And in the next video, you will learn
how to determine whether it is possible
to have an infinite arbitrage
from rubles to dollars, or
from any other currency
to any other currency.
And not only to detect that, but
to actually find a way to
implement it if it's possible.