Hello everybody, welcome back.
Today, we're going to be starting
with a new data structures topic.
In particular, we are going to be
talking about Binary Search Trees.
And today, we're going to be giving
some of introductions to the topic and
really going to try and do two things.
One is to sort of motivate the types of
the problems that we want to be able to
solve this new data structure.
And secondly, we'll talk a little
bit about why the data structures we
already know about are not up to this task
and why we really do need something new.
So to begin with let's talk about a few
problems that you might want to solve.
So one is you want to search a dictionary.
You've got a dictionary and
you want to find all the words that
start with some given string of letters.
Or similarly you've got a bunch of emails
and you'd like to find all the emails that
were sent or
received during a given period.
Or maybe you've got a bunch of friends or
class or something and you'd like to
find the other person in this class
whose height is closest to yours.
Now all of these are examples of what
we might call a local search problem.
What you want for them is you have a data
structure that stores a bunch of elements.
Each of them has some key that
comes from a linearly ordered set.
Something like a word sorted by
alphabetical order, or a date,
or a height, or something like that.
And we want this data structure
to support some operations.
Things like range search,
which should return all
of the elements whose keys
are between two numbers x and y.
Or nearest neighbors,
where given another key z,
you want to find the things closest to z
on either side in this data structure.
So, for example, if we have such data
structure storing the following numbers,
if we wanted to do a range search for
5 to 12, it should return 6, 7 and
10, the three numbers that are stored
that are between 5 and 12.
If we want the nearest neighbors
of 3 we should return 1 and
4 since those are the closest things
to we have to 3 on either side.
Now if we just wanted to do that,
it turns out you can do it,
but in practice, you really want
these data structures to be dynamic.
You want it to be possible to modify them.
So, two more operations that we would like
to be able to implement are insert and
delete.
Insert(x) adds a new element with key x,
and
Delete(x) removes an element with key x.
Fine.
So, for example, we have this array.
If we want to insert 3 into it,
we do whatever we need to,
3 is now stored in this data structure
in addition to everything else.
And then we can delete 10,
remove that and we've got slightly
different elements that we're storing.
So just to make sure we're on the same
page, if you start with such a data
structure and it's empty and
you insert 3, and then insert 8,
and then insert 5, then insert 10,
then delete 8, then insert 12 and
ask for the nearest neighbors of
7 what are you going to return?
Well, if you figure out what the data
structures stores at the end of the day,
you've inserted 3, 5, 8, 10 and 12,
8 got deleted, so,
you've only have the other four left over.
And you want the things closest
to 7 of the remaining guys,
which would be 5 and 10.
So, that should be the answer.
Okay, so this is the data structure
that we're trying to implement.
What can we say about being able to do it?
We've seen a bunch of data structures,
maybe one of them will work.
For example, we could try
implementing this by a hash table.
Hash tables are good at storing and
looking up elements very, very quickly.
Unfortunately, they're hard to search.
You can't really search for
all the elements in the hash table in
the given range more or less at all.
In some sense all the hash table
lets you do is check whether or
not a given element is stored there.
You can't find about elements in a range.
Similarly nearest neighbor is not really
a thing you can do with hash tables, but
they are good at inserts insertion into
a hash table is all of one as is deletion.
But the searching aspect doesn't work
here, so maybe we need something else.
Well, the next thing we
can try is an array.
And in an array you can do the searches,
but they're a little bit slow.
If you want to do a range
search on an array,
the best you can do is scan
through the entire array,
figure out which elements are in
the range you want and return those.
Similarly you have a nearest
neighbors search in O(n) time
by scanning through the entire array,
keeping track of the closest things on
either sides of the query, and
then returning the best ones at the end.
On the other hand, arrays,
at least if they're expandable arrays,
are still fine with insert and delete.
To insert a new element you just add
it to the next square over at the end.
To delete you can't just remove it from
the array because then you'd leave a gap,
but if you take the last element and
move it over to fill the gap.
Once again,
this delete operations is O(1) time.
Perhaps more interestingly than just
any array though is a sorted array.
Here, we're storing all of
our elements in an array, but
we're going to store
them in a sorted order.
And the critical thing about this is
it allows us to do binary search.
If we want to do a range search,
we can do a binary search to find the left
end of the range in our array and
that takes logarithmic time.
And then scan through until we hit
the right end of the range we want and
return everything in the middle.
So, the range search here
is basically log n time
at least assuming the number of things
we actually want to return is small.
Similarly nearest neighbors
is log arithmetic time.
We do a binary search to find
the thing that we're looking for and
reach to return the elements
on either side.
Unfortunately, updates to
a sorted array are hard.
You can't just insert a new element at the
end of the array, because the array needs
to remain sorted at the end and this
will generally destroy the sorted order.
If you want to insert 3,
it really needs to go between 1 and 4.
But, you can't really do that,
you can't just sort of add a new
cell in the middle of an array.
The only way to actually do this,
is you can put 3 in that plot and
then everything 4 and onwards needs
to shift over one cell to make room.
And so, insertion here is O(n) time
which is a lot longer than we want.
Similarly deletions are going to be hard.
If you delete an element, you can't just
leave a gap, you need to fill it somehow.
You can't just bring an element over
from one of the ends to fill the gap,
because that would destroy
your sorted structure.
So the only way to fill the gap
is to sort of take everything and
shift it back over 1 in order to fill
things up, and that again takes O(n) time.
A final thing to look at are linked lists.
Now here you can do
a RangeSearch in O(n) time,
you just scan through the list and
find everything in the range.
Similarly nearest neighbors
are going to be O(n).
Of course linked lists, insertion, and
deletions are very fast, O(1) at least
if you've got a doubly linked list.
These things are very good.
Unfortunately our searches are slow.
And even if you make this
a sorted linked list,
if you sort of guarantee that
everything comes in sorted order,
you still can't do better than
linear time for your searches.
Because you can't binary search a linked
list, even if it's sorted, because there's
no way to sort of jump to the middle
of the list and sort of do comparisons.
And so the moral here really is
that the data structure we've seen
up til this point don't work for
this sort of local search data structure.
And so, we're going to need something new.
And that's what we're going to start
talking about in the next lecture.