We now know how to compute the edit
distance or to compute the optimal
alignment by filling in the entries
in the dynamic programming matrix.
But it doesn't tell us yet
how to construct the alignment
two rows with the first row
representing the first sequence and
the second row representing
the second sequence.
Here's an idea.
Let's use the backtracking pointers
that we constructed while filling in
the dynamic programming matrix to reconstruct
optimal alignment between strings.
We can start by noting
that any path from (0, 0)
to (i, j) in the
dynamic programming matrix
spell an alignment of an i prefix
of A with a j prefix of B.
For example let's start the line in
the sequences, which means let's start
traveling from the point 0, 0 to the point
n, m in our dynamic programming matrix.
As soon as we move along diagonal left it
will correspond to either mismatch or
match, then we'll continue
using horizontal or
vertical edges and it will correspond
to insertions or deletions.
Then we will use once again diagonal edge.
In this case it is a match,
and you'll continue
by constructing the
n-alignment of two strings.
Please note that the constructed path
corresponds to distance A and is not
an optimal alignment because we know that
an optimal alignment distance is 5.
To construct an optimal alignment we will
use the backtracking pointers by starting
from the last vertex in this matrix
particularly from this vertex where
the added distance is recorded as 5.
Using backtracking pointers we see that
there are two possible ways to
arrive to this last vertex.
Let's arbitrarily choose one of them.
One of them corresponds to a mismatch and
another corresponds to insertion.
So let's arbitrarily choose a mismatch
edge that will correspond to
mismatch between j and i,
then from the previous point there is only
one way to move into this point and
it will correspond to an indel
that will continue further,
match, further, further, further,
further, and we will finally
arrive to the initial point at
the same time constructing the optimal
alignment between two strings.
The output alignment pseudoode
implement's this idea.
We simply look at the backtracking
pointers that enters in the node (i, j).
If they arrive to node (i, j)
by using a vertical edge
that we will simply output
one column of the alignment with
a of i in the first row.
If on the other hand it corresponds
to horizontal edge we output
column with b of j in the second row,
and
if it corresponds to a diagonal
edge we output a column
of alignment with a of i in the first
row and v of j in the second row.
It appears that we actually need
to store all backtracking pointers
to output alignment, but
this slightly modified
pseudocode tells you that you can compute
backtracking pointers by analyzing
entries in the dynamic programming
matrix and thus saving a little space.
Edit distance is just one
many applications of string comparisons
in various disciplines that range
from analyzing internet pages
to finding similar genes.
We started this lecture from
the example of gene hunt for
cystic fibrosis: one of the first
successes of the human genome project.
If you want to learn more about
comparing genes, protein, and
genomes you may enroll in the Coursera
specialization called Bioinformatics or
you can read the book Bioinformatics
Algorithms: the Active Learning Approach.