Hello.
In this lesson, you will learn
an algorithm to determine which food items
and in which amounts should you take
with yourself on a really long hike so
that to maximize their total energy value.
So, you're planning a long hike.
It will take a few days or
maybe a few weeks, but
you don't know exactly
how long will it take.
So, to be safe,
you need to get enough food with you.
And you have a knapsack which can fit
up to 15 kilograms of food in it.
And you've already bought some cheese,
some ham, some nuts, and
maybe some other food items.
You want to fit them all in the knapsack,
so
as to maximize the amount of
calories that you can get from them.
Of course you can cut the cheese.
You can cut the ham.
You can select only some of the nuts.
And then fit all of that
into your knapsack.
To solve this maximization problem,
we again need to first reformulate
it in mathematical terms.
And then it becomes an instance of
a classical fractional knapsack problem,
which goes like this.
We have n items with weights w1
through wn and values v1 though vn.
And a bag of capacity big W.
And we want to maximize the total value of
fractions of items that fit into this bag.
In this case, weights are also
weights in the real life and
values are the energy values of
the food items that you've bought.
So, here's an example,
and we will denote by
dollars the value of the item,
and the weight just by numbers.
So, for example,
the first item has value $20 and
has weight 4,
the second item has value $18 and
weight 3, and
the third item has value $14 and weight 2.
And we have a knapsack of capacity 7.
There are a few ways with which
we can fill this knapsack.
For example,
of them is put the whole first item and
the whole second item in the knapsack.
Then the total value is the sum of
the values of the first item and
the second, which is $38.
We can improve on that.
For example, take the whole first item,
the whole third item,
and only one third of the second item for
a total value of $40.
We can do even better by taking the whole
third item, the whole second item,
and only half of the first item,
and that will give us $42.
And actually it turns out that
this is the optimal thing to do.
So now we want to create
a greedy algorithm
that will solve this maximization problem,
and
we need to get some greedy choice and
make a safe move.
And to do that, we have to look
at the value per unit of weight.
So, for example for the first item,
value per unit of weight is $5,
for the second item, it's $6 per unit,
and for the third one it's $7 per unit.
So although the first
item is most valuable,
the third item has
the maximum value per unit.
And of course there is an intuition that
we should probably fit first the items
with the maximum value per unit.
And really,
the safe move is to first try to fit
the item with the maximum value per unit.
And there's a lemma that says that there
always exists some optimal
solution to our problem
that uses as much as possible of an item
with the maximum value per unit of weight.
And what do we mean by
as much as possible?
Well, either use the whole item,
if it fits into the knapsack,
or, if the capacity of the knapsack is
less than how much we have of this item,
then just fill the whole
knapsack only with this item.
Let's prove that this
is really a safe move.
We will prove looking at this example.
So, first let's suppose we
have some optimal solution,
and let's suppose that in this optimal
solution, we don't use as much as possible
of the best item with the highest
value per unit of weight.
Then take some item which we
used in this solution and
separate its usage into two parts,
one part of the same size of
how much we have of the best item, and
the second part is everything else.
Then we can substitute the first
part with the best item.
So, for example, in this case,
we substitute half of the first
item with second item.
Of course, in this part, the total
value will increase, because the value
per unit of weight is better for the best
item than for the item currently used.
And in the general case,
this will also work.
So, either we will be able to replace
some part of the item already
used by the whole best item, or
we can replace the whole item
that is already used by
some part of the best item.
And in any case,
if we can make such a substitution,
of course the total value will increase,
because the best item just has
better value per unit of weight,
so for each unit of weight,
we will have more value.
So this gives us a greedy
algorithm to solve our problem.
What we'll do is while knapsack is still
not full, we will do a greedy choice.
We will choose the item number i
which has the maximum value of
vi over wi,
which is the value per unit of weight.
And then if this item fits into knapsack
fully, then take of all this item.
Otherwise, if there is only few
space left in the knapsack,
take so much of this item as to
fill the knapsack to the end.
And then in the end, we'll return the
total value of the items that we took and
how much did we take of each item.