Hi, in this lesson, we will review what
we saw in this module about greedy
algorithms and specify what is common and
important to all greedy algorithms.
The main ingredients of any greedy
algorithm are greedy choice and
reduction to a subproblem.
You have to prove that your
greedy choice is a safe move.
And also, you have to check that the
problem that is left after your safe move
is really a subproblem.
That is, a problem of the same kind but
with fewer parameters.
After you have both,
you have a greedy algorithm.
Then, you need to estimate
its running time and
check that it's good enough for you.
Safe moves in different
problems are different.
Basically, you have to invent something
each time you have a new problem.
In the first problem it was,
select the maximum digit and put it first.
In the last problem it was select the item
with the maximum total value per weight.
And you see that in every safe move,
there's something like maximum,
or minimum, or first, or
leftmost, or rightmost.
So, always safe move is greedy,
but not all greedy moves are safe.
So, you really have to prove every time
that the move that you
invented is really safe.
Also, you can notice that sometimes we can
optimize our initial greedy algorithm
if we sort our object somehow.
So, you can maybe try to solve problem,
assuming that everything is
sorted in some convenient order.
And if you see that, because of that,
your greedy algorithm can be
implemented asymptotically faster,
then you can just apply sorting first and
then your greedy algorithm.
The general strategy is
when I have a problem,
you can try to come up with some greedy
choices, and then for some of them,
you'll be able to prove that
they're really safe moves.
And if you've proven
that this is a safe move,
then you've reduced your
problem to something.
And then you have to check that
this something is a subproblem.
That is, the problem about the same thing,
optimizing the same thing
with the same restrictions.
And then, this is a subproblem.
And then you can solve it in the same way
that you solved your initial problem.
And you have this loop from
problem to subproblem and
back to the problem, always reducing
it by the number of parameters.
And in the end of this loop,
you will have a problem so
simple that you can solve it right
away for one object or zero objects.
And then you have your greedy algorithm.