Hello and welcome to the next module,
in which we will be talking
about minimum spin entries.
To [INAUDIBLE] this title, this problem
considers the following toy example.
Assumes that we have six machines in our
office and we would like to join them.
In doing that whereby putting
wires between some pairs of them
such that each machine, each machine
is reachable from any other machine.
I assume further that we can put wires
only between some pairs of our machines.
And for each [INAUDIBLE] we're now
[INAUDIBLE] responding [INAUDIBLE] why
between them.
For example in this case we are allowed
to put a Y between these two machines and
of course this five.
And we are not allowed to join
these two machines by wire.
Okay.
Wire of the optimal solutions in this
case is shown here on the slide.
It is not difficult to check
that in this case indeed
any machine is reachable
from [INAUDIBLE] machine.
For example to reach the right
machine from the left machine
we would go as follows.
First by this edge, then by this edge,
and then by this edge.
The total cost of the shown solution
is equal to two plus one which
is three plus three
which is six plus four.
Which gives us ten plus
two which gives us 12.
So the total cost is 12, and
this is actually not the only solution
in this case because instead of using
this wire, we may use this wire.
The result in solution is shown for
you on the slide and it is not.
Again, difficult to check that, in this
case, any machine is reachable from any
other machine and
that the total cost is equal to 12.
We will soon learn read the algorithms
that will allow us to justify
that in this, for example,
the optimal total cost is indeed 12.
These two algorithms will also allow
us to solve very efficiently in
practice instances consisting
of thousands of machines.
In our second example we have a collection
cities and we would like to build roads
between some pairs of them such that
there is a path between any two cities.
And such that the sum
of the lengths of all
the roads that we are going to
build is as small as possible.
Okay?
In this case the solution looks like this.
And again we will soon learn how
to find the solution efficiently.
Formally the problem is stated as follows.
[INAUDIBLE] graph H [INAUDIBLE] and
we assume that this graph is connected.
Okay and it is given together
with positive edge weight.
What we're looking for
is that subset of edges,
e prime, such that if we leave
only these edges in the graph.
Then the resulting graph Is connected and
also the total cost of folds and
edges at E prime is as small as possible,
okay?
So why is the problem is
called minimum spending tree?
Well minimum corresponds to
the fact that we are looking for
a subset of edges or minimum total cost or
minimum total weight.
Okay.
It is called spanning because we're
looking for a subset of edges such that
if we leave only these edges, then
the result in graph is still connected so
it spans all the vertices in our graph.
And finally, the word tree corresponds
those effect that in each solution,
the set E prime is going to be.
Is going to form a tree.
We will prove this fact on the next slide.
Before proving that any
optimal solution for
minimum spanning tree problem any
optimal solution in prime forms a tree.
Let me remind you a few
useful properties of trees.
First of all, just by definition,
a tree is an undirected graph
that is connected and is acyclic,
that is it contains no cycles.
Recall that we usually
draw trees as follows.
So we draw them level by level and
look like this.
In this case, we actually.
We're actually talk about rooted trees.
This is a rooted tree and in particular,
this is a root of this tree.
At the same time, this graph
is also a tree with only
difference that there is no root
In this tree and
it is not drawn level by level.
So once again,
this graph is also connected and
there are no cycle in this graph so
it is a tree.
There is no root in this tree,
however we can take a vertex,
declare this vertex as a tree and
then hang by this vertex.
And then this will allow us to draw
this graph level by level,okay?
the next property is
that if we have a tree
with n vertices than it
necessarily has n minus one edges.
Why is that?
Well let me illustrate this
by drawling something.
Initially we have just one vertices and
zero edges.
So initially the property has
satisfied the number of edges.
Is equal to the number
of vertices minus one.
Let then introduce some new vertex.
So we'll attach it by
an edge to a previous vertex.
Then we introduce another vertex,
probably another one, and another one.
And so on.
So each time when we introduce a new edge
Introducing new [INAUDIBLE]
We also have a new edge.
So initially we had one vertex, and
zero edges [INAUDIBLE] vertices and now we
have, I'm sorry five vertices, now we have
six vertices and [INAUDIBLE] five edges.
So still the property is satisfied.
Note that we cannot introduce a new
edge without introducing a new vertex.
Because if we introduce a new edge
that would mean that we are connecting
two existing vertices by edge.
For example like this, but
this will necessarily produce a cycle
which means that this will give
us a graph which is not at three.
Okay?
The next property is that,
actually any connected graph with
the number of edges equal to the number of
vertices minus one, is necessarily a tree.
Well, let me emphasize that it is
important that here we are talking about
connected graphs.
Because for
example if a graph has the property
that the number of edges is equal to
the number of vertices minus one but
it is not connected,
that it is not necessarily a tree.
A counterexample is the following.
Assume that we have four vertices and
there is a [INAUDIBLE] and
three vertices and there is one isolated.
One isolated vertex.
In this case, we have four vertices,
and three edges, right?
So this is not a tree, but at the same
time this graph is not connected.
There is no pass for example from this
vertex to this isolated vertex, okay?
And the last property says that
an undirected graph is a tree if and
only if there is a unique path
between any two vertices.
And this is also not difficult to see
first of all if we have a tree then of
course there is a unique path
between two its vertices.
On the other hand If we have to vertacise,
and
there are at least parts between them,
then this gives us a cycle,
which means that this is not a three.
Okay, now let me get back
to proving that any optimal
solution [INAUDIBLE] problem
is indeed a three, for this,
consider some [INAUDIBLE]
solution.
So in this case we have six vertices,
and we consider some way of joining
them into some way of connecting them.
I assume that our
solution looks like this.
So you see that this is not
a tree because there is a cycle.
On these four vertices.
Well, in this cycle for
any two vertices in this cycle,
there are two paths.
Right?
For example, for this vertex and for
this vertex we can go either this way or
this way.
And this is true for any cycle,
if we have a cycle and
two vertices on this cycle we can
either go this way or this way.
And this means that there
is some redundancy here.
In this particular case, we can remove,
for example, this edge from this cycle.
Or from this solution.
This will only decrease the total
weight of this solution and
the resulting set of fedres
will still be connected.
Great this proves that any
optimal solution must be acyclic,
and since any solution is
required to be connected,
this proves that any optimal
solution is in fact a tree.