The goal of this whole lesson is to
present two greedy algorithms for
the minimum spanning tree problem.
Before going in to the details
of this algorithms,
let me present you the higher level
ideas of both these algorithms.
So the first one is the Kruskal And
the second one is you need to Prim.
The high level idea of the algorithm
by Kruskal is the following.
So, we go through all edges in
order of increasing width, and
we repeatedly at the next lightest
edge which doesn't produce a cycle.
Alternatively, the main idea
of the Prim's algorithm
is to grow a tree repeatedly so
initially it contains just one vertex,
then we attach a new vertex to it,
then a new vertex to it.
And we always attach the new
vertex to the current tree
by the lightest available edge.
Let me illustrate this
again on a toy example.
So for Kruskal's algorithm, again,
we repeatedly add the next lightest
edge that doesn't produce a cycle.
Initially, our solution is empty, so
we just add the first lightest edge.
In this case,
the lightest edge has weight 1, so
we just put this edge into our solution.
And there is also another
edge which has cost or
weight 1, so
we also add it to our solution.
The next one has weight 2.
We add it.
At the same time, the next one,
the next lightest available
edge has weight 3.
However, if we added it to our current
solution, this would produce a cycle.
So we skip this edge.
The next lightest available
edge has weight 4.
We add it because it
doesn't produce a cycle.
Then, again, we try to add the edge with
weight 5 because it is the next
lightest available edge.
However, it produces a cycle.
So we skip this edge, and instead
we add the edge of weight 6, right?
This gives us a solution, and we will soon
justify that this method indeed
gives an optimal solution.
Now, to the Prim's algorithm.
It works in a different way.
So it repeatedly grows just 1, 3.
For this, it will select a root for
this tree.
So I assume that this
highlighted vertex is going
to be the root of the tree that
we are going to construct.
At each iteration we are going to
attach a new node to this tree,
and we would like to do this by
using the lightest possible edge.
So for this vertex,
we have four edges going out of this node.
One of weight 4, one of weight 5,
of weight 6, and of weight 8.
In this case, we select,
of course, the edge of weight 4.
So we attach it.
Now our tree contains two nodes, and
we would like to attach a new node
to this tree by lightest edge.
So in this case,
this is the vertex in the middle.
And it has weight, the corresponding edge,
has weight 1 so we attach it.
The next one has weight 2.
The next one has weight 6.
And finally, the last node is attached
by an edge of weight 1, right?
So, in the next part of this lesson,
we will present the implementation
details of both these algorithms, but
we first will prove that both
these algorithms are correct.
Namely, that they produce
an optimal solution.