Mostly considerate to algorithms
construct the solution iteratively.
Namely they start with an empty solution,
with an empty set of edges.
And at each iteration they expand
the current set of edges by one edge.
But they use different strategies for
selecting the next edge,
namely the Kruskal's Algorithm.
Select the next lightest edge
that doesn't produce a cycle.
While the Prim's Algorithm
selects the next lightest edge
that attaches a new vertex
to the current tree.
What we need to prove to show that both
of these algorithm's optimal is that
this strategies are in some sense safe.
Namely, if at the current step
we have a subset of edges which
we call e prime which is a subset
of some optimal solution.
Then by adding this edge according to
one of these two strategies to the set
gives us also a set of address which is
also a part of some optimal solution.
This will justify at the end
when we have a three, this three
is also a part of some optimal solution,
which means that this is just optimal.
So in this video, we're going to prove
a lemma which is called cut property,
which will justify that both
these strategies, I indeed save.
The formal statement of
the lemma is the following.
Assume that we have a graph G with a set
of edges V and the set of edges E.
Together with this graph, we are given
a subset of its edges that we call X.
X is a subset sum, subset of
the set of edges of our graph for
which we knows that it is a part
of some optimal solution.
It is a part of some
minimum spanning tree.
I assume also that the set of vertices
is partitioned into two parts.
One part is the subset of vertices S, and
another part all
the remaining vertices V-S.
So we're given also
a set of vertices S and
this set of vertices S satisfies
the following property.
No edge from the set X joins
two vertices that such as one
lies intercept S and
the other one lies intercept V-S.
No edge from the set of X
crosses between S and V-S.
Finally, assume that E,
the edge E of the initial graph
satisfies the following property.
It is a lightest edge that
joins the vertex from S with
the vertex outside of X
with the vertex from V-S.
E is a lightest edge
across this partition.
Then what dilemma states is that if we
add the edge E to our current set X,
then what we get will also be a subset
of some minimum spanning tree.
In other words,
adding e to X in this case is a safe move.
So since this is a long statement,
let me repeat it once again
using a small example.
So I assume that this is our graph G,
so we are given a graph G.
Together with this graph G we
are given some subset of its edges
shown here on the slide in blue,
it is the set X.
So this is just subset of the set
of edges of how we graph and
assumes that we know that it is
a part of some minimum spanning tree.
So the set X is a subset of
some minimum spanning tree,
then consider some partition of
the set of vertices into two parts.
See, this is one part and
this is also remaining vertices,
this is the second part.
Then this partition is required to satisfy
the following property, no edge from x
on our picture now blue edge joins
to vertices from different parts.
In this case, it is satisfied.
Indeed, any blue edge here joins two
vertices that lie in the same part.
Next, we consider the lightest edge in our
initial graph that joins two
vertices from different parts.
Assume that this edge is e,
shown here in red.
Then what lemma states is that
if we this edge to our set X,
then the resulting set of edges will also
be a part of some minimum spanning tree.
So this tells that adding
e to our current subset which
we grow repeatedly by one edge
to the subset is a safe move then
I will proof the cut property.
This is our graph G and
this is the subset of edges X shown
here in blue and we assume that
this subset X is a part of some minimum
spanning tree which we denote by T.
In other words,
X is a subset of edges is a subset
of some minimum spanning tree T.
Now, we also have a partition of
the set of vertices into two part.
We said the vertices S and
the set of vertices V-S, all that remains.
E is a lightest edge in
the initial graph which joins
two vertices from different
parts of partition.
So E joins the vertex from
S with the vertex from V-S.
What we need to prove is if we add
the edge E to our current set X,
then what we get is also a part
of some minimum spanning tree.
Once again, what we assume about X.
We assume X is a part of some
minimum spanning tree T,
and e joins two vertices from
different parts of partition.
And what we need to prove is that
X with e added 3 is also a part
of some possibly different
minimum spanning three.
So the minimum spanning tree
which contains X plus e
is not necessarily the same as T.
So to prove this, we consider two cases.
So first, if E happens to be a part
of the minimum spanning tree T,
then there is noting to prove.
Once again, we assume that X is a part of
minimum spanning tree that we denote by if
e is also part T sub x plus e is
a part of minimum spanning tree T.
In this case, there is nothing to prove,
we are just done.
So I assume that e is not a part
of the minimum spanning tree T.
Let's then consider the wall tree T.
So it contains X, so now the edges
showing in blue show the wall tree T.
Know that if we add the edge E to
the tree T then it produces a cycle.
Because in the tree T,
there is a path between the vertices,
between the endpoints of e, and when
we add the edge e, it produces a cycle.
In this case on our example,
this is the cycle.
This is the cycle, I'm sorry.
So this is a cycle and
the edge e in the cycle joins to
vertices from different parts.
Since this is a cycle, so
the edge e joins for
example the left part with the right part.
Since this is a cycle it must eventually
at some point go from right part
to left part.
Which means that there must be an edge in
the tree T which also joins two parts.
And we denote this edge by e prime and
in our case this is this edge,
so this is e prime.
Now, I claim is that if we replace
the edge e prime by the edge e
in the current tree, is then what
we get is an optimal spanning tree.
So why is that?
First of all,
the resulting tree is still connected,
because we just removed some edge,
edge e prime from a cycle.
So this is still connected,
it was connected before.
And when we remove an edge from a cycle,
it cannot disconnect the graph.
At the same time,
the weight of the edge e prime
is at least the weight of the edge e,
because e is the lightest edge that
joins different part of partition.
Which proves that the resulting
set of edges is a tree of minimum
possible weight which in turns,
proves the cut property.