In this video, I'll talk about a
different way of learning sigmoid belief
notes.
This different method arrived in an
unexpected way.
I stopped working on sigmoid belief nets
and went back to Boltzmann machines.
And discovered that restricted Boltz
machines could actually be learned fairly
efficiently.
Given that a restricted Boltzmann machine
could efficiently learn a layer of
nonlinear features. It was tempting to
take those features, treat them as data,
and apply another restricted Boltzmann
machine to model the correlations between
those features.
And one can continue like this, stacking
one Boltzmann machine on top of the next
one to learn lots of layers of nonlinear
features.
This eventually led to a big resurgence
of interest in deep neural nets.
The issue then arose. Once you stacked up
lots of restricted Boltzmann machines,
each which is learned by modeling the
patterns of future activities produced by
the previous Boltzmann machines.
Do you just have a set of separate
restricted Boltzmann machines or can they
all be combined together into one model?
Now, anybody sensible would expect that
if you combined a set of restricted
Boltzmann machines together to make one
model, what you'd get would be a
multilayer Boltzmann machine.
However, a brilliant graduate student of
mine called G.Y.
Tay, figured out that that's not what you
get.
You actually get something that looks
much more like a sigmoid belief net.
This was a big surprise.
It was very surprising to me that we'd
actually solved the problem of how to
learn deep sigmoid belief nets by giving
up on it and focusing on learning
undirected models like Boltzmann
machines.
Using the efficient learning algorithm
for restricted Boltzmann machines.
It's easy to train a layer of features
that receive input directly from the
pixels.
We can treat the patterns of activation
of those feature detectors as if they
were pixels,
and learn another layer of features in a
second hidden layer.
We can repeat this as many times as we
like with each new layer of features
modelling the correlated activity in the
features in the layer below.
It can be proved that each time we add
another layer of features, we improve a
variational lower bound on the log
probability that some combined model
would generate the data.
The proof is actually complicated, and it
only applies if you do everything just
right,
which you don't do in practice.
But, the proof is very reassuring,
because it suggests that something
sensible is going on when you stack up
restricted Boltzmann machines like this.
The proof is based on a neat equivalence
between a restricted bolson machine and
an infinitely deep belief net.
So here's a picture of what happens when
you learn two restricted Boltzmann
machines, one on top of the other,
and then you combine them to make one
overall model, which I call a deep belief
net.
So first we learn one Boltzmann machine
with its own weights.
Once that's been trained, we take the
hidden activity patterns of that
Boltzmann machine when it's looking at
data and we treat each hidden activity
pattern as data for training a second
Boltzmann machine.
So we just copy the binary states to the
second Boltzmann machine, and then we
learn another Boltzmann machine.
Now one interesting thing about this, is
that if we start the second Boltzmann
machine off with W2 being the transpose
of W1, and with as many hidden units in
h2 as there are in v, then the second
Boltzmann machine will already be a
pretty good model of h1,
because it's just the first model upside
down.
And for a restricted Boltzmann machine,
it doesn't really care which you call
visible and which you call hidden.
It's just a bipartite graph that's
learned to model.
After we've learned those two Boltzmann
machines, we're going to compose them
together to form a single model and the
single model looks like this.
Its top two layers adjust the same as the
top restricted Boltzmann machine.
So that's an undirected model with
symmetric connections, but its bottom two
layers are a directed model like a
sigmoid belief net.
So what we've done is we've taken the
symmetric connections between v and h1
and we've thrown away the upgoing part of
those and just kept the dangering part.
To understand why we've done that is
quite complicated and that will be
explained in video 13F.
The resulting combined model is clearly
not a Boltzmann machine, because its
bottom layer of connections are not
symmetric.
It's a graphical model that we call a
deep belief net, where the lower layers
are just like sigmoid belief nets and the
top two layers form a restricted
Boltzmann machine.
So it's a kind of hybrid model.
If we do it with three Boltzmann machines
stacked up, we'll get a hybrid model that
looks like this.
The top two layers again are a restricted
Boltzmann machine and the layers below
are directed layers like in a sigmoid
belief net.
To generate data from this model the
correct procedure is,
first of all, you go backwards and
forwards between h2 and h3 to reach
equilibrium in that top level restricted
Boltamann machine.
This involves alternating Gibbs sampling,
where you update all of the units in h3
in parallel, and update all of the units
in h2 in parallel,
then go back and update all of the units
in h3 in parallel. And you go backwards
and forwards like that for a long time
until you've got an equilibrium sample
from the top-level restricted Boltamann
machine.
So the top-level restricted Bolson
machine is defining the prior
distribution of h2.
Once you've done that, you simply go once
from h2 to h1 using the generative
connections w2.
And then, whatever binary patent you get
in h1, you go once more to get generated
data, using the weights w1.
So we're performing a top-down pass from
h2, to get the states of all the other
layers,
just like in a sigmoid belief net.
The bottom-up connections, shown in red
at the lower levels, are not part of the
generative model.
They're actually going to be the
transposes of the corresponding weights.
So they're the transpose of w1 and the
transpose of w2,
and they're going to be used for
influence, but they're not part of the
model.
Now, before I explain why stacking up
Boltzmann machines is a good idea, I need
to sort out what it means to average two
factorial distributions.
And it may surprise you to know that if I
average two factorial distributions, I do
not get a factorial distribution.
What I mean by averaging here is taking a
mixture of the distributions, so you
first pick one of the two at random, and
then you generate from whichever one you
picked.
So, you don't get a factorial
distribution.
Suppose we have an RBM with 4 hidden
units and suppose we give it a visible
vector.
And given this visible vector, the
posterior distribution over those 4
hidden units is factorial.
And lets suppose the distribution was
that the first and second units have a
probability of 0.9 of turning on and the
last two have a probability of 0.1 of
turning on.
What it means for this to be factorial is
that, for example, the probability that
the first two units were both be on in a
sample from this distribution, is exactly
0.81.
Now suppose we have a different angle
vector v2, and the posterior distribution
over the same 4 hidden units is now 0.1,
0.1, 0.9, 0.9, which I chose just to make
the math easy.
If we average those two distributions,
the mean probability of each hidden unit
being on, is indeed, the average of the
means for each distribution.
So the means are 0.5, 0.5, 0.5, 0.5,
but what you get is not a factorial
distribution defined by those 4
probabilities.
To see that, consider the binary vector
1, 1, 0, 0 over the hidden units.
In the posterior for v1,
that has a probability of 0.9^4, because
it's 0.9 * 0.9 * 1 - 0.1 * 1 - 0.1.
So that's 0.43.
In the posterior for v2, this vector is
extremely unlikely.
It has a probability of 1 in 10,000.
If we average those two probabilities for
that particular vector, we'll get a
probability of 0.215,
and that's much bigger than the
probability assigned to the vector 1, 1,
0, 0 by factorial distribution with means
of 0.5.
That probability will be 0.5^4, which is
much smaller.
So, the point of all this, is that when
you average two factorial posteriors, you
get a mixture distribution that's not
factorial.
Now, let's look at why the greedy
learning works.
That is why it's a good idea to learn one
restricted Boltzmann machine.
And then learn a second restricted
Boltzmann machine that models the
patterns of activity in the hidden units
of the first one.
The weights of the bottom level
restricted Boltzmann machine, actually
define four different distributions.
Of course, they define them in a
consistent way.
So the first distribution is the
probability of the visible units given
the hidden units.
And the second one is the probability of
the hidden units given the visible units.
And those are the two distributions we
use for running our alternating mark of
chain that updates the visibles given the
hiddens and then updates the hiddens
given the visibles.
If we run that chain long enough, we'll
get a sample from the joint distribution
of v and h.
And so the weights clearly also define
the joint distribution.
They also define the joint distribution
more directly in terms of E to the minus
the energy,
but for nets with a large number of
units, we can't compute that.
If you take the joint distribution,
p(v|h), and you just ignore v, we now a
distribution for h.
That's the prior distribution over h,
defined by this restricted Boltzmann
machine.
And similarly, if we ignore h, we have
the prior distribution over v, defined by
the restricted Boltzmann machine.
And now, we're going to pick a rather
surprising pair of distributions from
those four distributions.
We're going to define the probability
that the restricted Boltzmann machine
assigns to a visible vector v as the sum
over all hidden vectors of the
probability it assigns to h times the
probability of v given h.
This seems like a silly thing to do,
because defining p(h) is just as hard as
defining p(v).
And nevertheless, we're going to define
p(v) that way.
Now, if we now leave p(v|h) alone,
but learn a better model of p(h),
that is, learn some new parameters that
give us a better model of p(h) and
substitute that in instead of the old
model we had of p(h).
We'll actually improve our model of v.
And what we mean by a better model of
p(h) is a prior over h that fits the
aggregated posterior better.
The aggregated posterior is the average
over all vectors in the training set of
the posterior distribution over h.
So, what we're going to do, is use our
first RBM to get this aggregated
posterior and then use our second RBM to
build a better model of this aggregated
posterior than the first RBM has.
And if we start the second RBM off as the
first one upside down, it will start with
the same model of the aggregated
posterior as the first RBM has.
And then, if we change the weights we can
only make things better.
So, that's an explanation of what's
happening when we stack up RBMs.
Once we've learned to stack up Boltzmann
machines, then combine them together to
make a deep belief net,
we can then actually fine-tune the whole
composite model using a variation of the
wake-sleep algorithm.
So we first learn many layers of features
by stacking up IBMs.
And then we want to fine-tune both the
bottom-up recognition weights and the
top-down generative weights to get a
better generative model and we can do
this by using three different learning
routes.
First, we do a stochastic bottom-up pass,
and we adjust the top down generative
weights of the lower layers to be good at
reconstructing the feature activities in
the layer below.
That's just as in the standard wake-sleep
algorithm Then, in the top level RBM, we
go backwards and forwards a few times,
sampling the hiddens of that RBM, and the
visibles of that RBM, and the hiddens of
the RBM, and so on.
So that's just like the learning
algorithm for RBMs.
And having done a few iterations of that,
we do contrastive divergence learning.
That is, we update the weights of the RBM
using the difference between the
correlations when activity first got to
that RBM and the correlations after a few
iterations in that RBM.
We take that difference and use it to
update the weights.
And then, the third stage, we take the
visible units of that top-level RBM by
its lower level units.
And starting there, we do a top-down
stochastic pass, using the directed lower
connections, which are just a sigmoid
belief net.
Then, having generated some data from
that sigmoid belief net, we adjust the
bottom up rates to be good at
reconstructing the feature activities in
the layer above.
So that's just the sleep phase of the
wake-sleep algorithm.
The difference from the standard
wake-sleep algorithm is that that
top-level RBM acts as a much better prior
over the top layers, than just a layer of
units which are assumed to be
independent, which is what you get with a
sigmoid belief net.
Also, rather than generating data by
sampling from the prior, what we're
actually doing is looking at a training
case, going up to the top-level RBM and
just running a few iterations before we
generate data.
So now we're going to look at an example
where we first learn some RBMs, stacking
them up,
and then we do contrastive wake-sleep to
fine-tune it,
and then we look to see what it's like.
Is it a generative model?
And also if we're recognizing things.
So first of all, we're going to use 500
binary hidden units to learn to model all
10 digit classes in images of 28 by 28
pixels.
Once we've learned that RBM, without
knowing what the labels are,
so it's unsupervised learning.
We're going to take the patterns of
activity in those 500 hidden units that
they have when they're looking at data.
We're going to treat those patterns of
activity as data and we're going to learn
another RBM that also has 500 units,
and those two are learned without knowing
what the labels are.
Once we've done that we'll actually tell
it the labels.
So the first two hidden layers are
learned without labels,
and then, we add a big top layer and we
give it the 10 labels.
And you can think that we concatenate
those 10 labels with the 500 units that
represent features,
except that the 10 labels are really one
soft match unit.
Then we train that top-level RBM to model
the concatenation of the soft match unit
for the 10 labels with the 500 feature
activities that were produced by the two
layers below.
Once we've trained the top-level RBM, we
can then fine-tune the whole system by
using contrastive wake-sleep.
And then we'll have a very good
generative model and that's the model
that I showed you in the intro video.
So if you go back, and you find the
introduction video for this course,
you'll see what happens when we run that
model.
You'll see how good it is at recognition
and you'll also see that it's very good
at generation.
In that introductory video, I promised
you, you would eventually explain how it
worked,
and I think you've now seen enough to
know what's going on when this model is
learned.