In this video I'm going to talk about
some advanced material.
It's not really appropriate for a first
course on nerual networks but I know that
some of you are particularly interested
in the urgent of deep learning.
And the content of this video is
mathematically very pretty So I couldn't
resist putting it in.
[INAUDIBLE] insight that stacking up
restrictive Boltzmann machines gives you
something like a sigmoid belief net can
actually be seen without doing any math.
Just by noticing, that a restrictive
Boltzmann machine is actually the same
thing as an infinitely deep sigmoid
belief net with shared weights.
Once again, wave sharing leads to
something very interesting.
I'm now going to describe, a very
interesting explanation of why layer by
layer learning works.
It depends on the fact that there is an
equivalence between restricted bowlser
machines, which are undirected networks
with symmetric connections, and
infinitely deep directed networks.
In which every layer uses the same weight
matrix.
This equivalence also gives insight into
why contrasted divergence learning works.
So an RBM is really just an infinitely
deep sigmoid belief net with a lot of
shared weights.
The Markoff chain that we run when we
want to sample from an RBM can be viewed
as exactly the same thing as a sigmoid
belief net.
So here's the picture.
We have a very deep sigmoid belief net.
In fact, infinitely deep.
We use the same weights at every layer.
We have to have all the V layers being
the same size as each other, and all the
H layers being the same size as each
other.
But V and H can be different sizes.
The distribution generated by this very
deep network with replicated weights is
exactly the equilibrium distribution that
you get by alternating between doing P of
V given H, and P of H given V, where both
P of V given H and P of H given V are
defined by the same weight matrix W.
And that's exactly what you do when you
take a restricted Boltzmann machine, and
run a Markhov chain to get a sample from
the equilibrium distribution.
So a top-down pass starting from
infinitely higher up.
In this directed note, is exactly
equivalent to letting a restricted
Boltzmann machine settle to equilibrium.
But that would define the same
distribution.
The sample you get at v0 if you run this
infinite directed note, would be an
equilibrium sample of the equivalent RBM.
Now let's look at inference in an
infinitely deep sigmoid belief net.
So in inference we start at v zero and
then we have to infer the state of h
zero.
Normally this would be a difficult thing
to do because of explaining away.
If for example hidden units K and J both
had big positive weights to visible unit
I, then we would expect that when we
observe that I is on, K and J become
anti-correlated in the posterior
distribution.
That's explaining a way.
However in this net, K and J are
completely independent of one another
when we do inference given V0.
So the inference is trivial, we just
multiply V0 by the transpose of W.
And put whatever we get through the
logistic sigmoid and then sample.
And that gives us binary states of the
units in H0.
But the question is how could they
possible be independent given explaining
away.
The answer to that question is that the
model above H0 implements what I call a
complementary prior.
It implements a prior distribution over
H0 that exactly cancels out the
correlations in explaining away.
So for the example shown, the prior will
implement positive correlation stream k
and j.
Explain your way will cause negative
correlations and those will exactly
cancel.
So what's really going on is that when we
multiply v0 by the transpose of the
weights, we're not just computing the
light unit term.
We're computing the product of a light
unit term and a prior term.
And that's what you need to do to get the
posterior.
It normally comes as a big surprise to
people.
That when you multiply by w transpose,
it's the product of the prior in the
posterior of your computer.
So what's happening in this net is that
the complementary prior implemented by
all the stuff above H0, exactly counts a
lot explaining why it makes inference
very simple.
And that's true at every layer of this
net so we can do inference for every
layer and get an unbiased sample with
each layer simply by multiplying V0 by W
transpose.
Then once we computed the binary state of
H0, we multiple that by W.
Put that through the logistic sigmoid and
sample and that will give use a binary
state for V1 and so on for all the way
up.
Suggestive generating from this model is
equivalent to running the alternating
mark off chain on a restricted Boltzmann
machine to equilibrium.
Performing inference in this model is
exactly the same process in the opposite
direction.
This is a very special kind of sigmoid
belief net in which inference is as easy
as generation.
So here I've shown the generative weights
that define the model, and also their
transposes, that are the way we do
inference.
And now I what want to show is how we get
the Bolton Machine Learning Algorithm out
of the learning algorithm for directed
Sigmoid belief nets.
So the learning rule for Sigmoid belief
net says that we should first get a
sample from the posterior, that what the
Sj and Si are, samples from the posterior
distribution.
And then we should change a weight, the
generative weight in proportion to the
product of the pre activity as J and the
difference between the [INAUDIBLE]
activity as i and the probability of
turning on i given all the binary states
of the ladder Sj is in.
Now if we ask how do we compute Pi,
something very interesting happens.
If you look at inference in this network
on the right, we first infer a binary
state for H0.
Once we've chosen that binary state, we
then infer a binary state for V1 by
multiplying H0 by W, putting the result
through the logistic, and then sampling.
So if you think about how Si1 was
generated?
It was a sample from what we get if we
put H0 through the weight matrix W and
then through the logistic.
And that's exactly what we'd have to, to
in order to compute PiO.
We'd have to take the binary activities
in H0 and going downwards now through the
green weights, W, we will compute the
probability of turning on unit I given
the binary states of its parents.
So the point is, the process that goes
from H0 to V1 is identical to the process
that goes from H0 to V0.
And so SI1 is an unbiased sample of PI0.
That means we can replace it in the
learning rule.
So we end up with a learning rule that
looks like this, because since we have
replicated weights, each of those lines
is the term in the learning rule that
comes from one of those green weight
matrices.
For the first green weight matrix here.
The learning rule is the presynaptic
state Sj0 times the difference between
the post synaptic state Si0 and the
probability that the binary states in H0
would turn on Si.
Which we could call PI0 but a sample with
that probability is Si1.
And so an unbiased estimate of the
relative, can be got by plugging in Si1
on that first line of the learning rule.
Similarly for the second weight matrix,
the learning rule is SI1 into SJ0 minus
PJ0 and an unbiased estimate of PJ0 is
SJ1.
And so that's an unbiased testament of
the learning rule, for this second weight
matrix.
And if you just keep going for all
wave-matrices you get this infinite
series.
And all the terms except the very first
term and the very last term cancel out.
And so you end up with the Boltzmann
machine learning rule.
Which is just SJ-zero into Si-zero, minus
SI-infinity into SI-infinity.
So let's go back and look at how we would
learn an infinitely deep sigmoid belief
net.
We would start by making all the weight
matrices the same.
So we tie all the weight matrices
together.
And we learn using those tied weights.
Now that's exactly equivalent to learning
a restricted Boltzmann machine.
The diagram on the right and the diagram
on the left are identical.
We can think of the symmetric arrow in
the diagram on the left, as just a
convenient shorthand for an infinite
directed net with tied weights.
So we first learn that restricted
Boltzmann machine.
Now we ought to learn it using maximum
likelihood learning, but actually we're
just going to use contrasted divergence
learning.
We're going to take a shortcut.
Once we've learned the first restricted
Boltzmann machine, what we could do is we
could freeze the bottom level weights.
We'll freeze the generative weights that
define the model.
We'll also freeze the weights we're going
to use for inference to be the transpose
of those generative weights.
So we freeze those weights.
We keep all the other weights tied
together.
But now we're going to allow them to be
different from the weights in the bottom
layer but they're still all tied
together.
So learning the remaining weights tied
together is exactly equivalent to
learning another restrictive Boltzmann
machine.
Namely a restricted Boltzmann machine
with H0 as its visible units, V1 as its
hidden units.
And where the data is the aggregated
posterior across H0.
That is, if we want to sample a data
vector to train this network, what we do
is we put in a real data vector, V
nought, we do inference through those
frozen waits, and we get a binary vector
at H nought, and we treat that as data
for training the next restricted
Boltzmann machine.
And we can go up for as many layers as we
like.
And when we get fed up, we just end up
with the restrictive Boltzmann machine at
the top which is equivalent to saying,
all the weights in the infinite directed
net above there are still tied together,
but the weights below have now all become
different.
Now an explanation of why the inference
procedure was correct, involved the idea
of a complementary prior created by the
weights in the layers above but of
course, when we change the weights in the
layers above, but leave the bottom layer
of weights fixed, the prior created by
those changed weights is no longer
exactly complementary.
So now our inference procedure, using the
frozen weights in the bottom layer, is no
longer exactly correct.
The good news is, it's nearly always very
close to correct and with the incorrect
inference procedure, we still get a
variational bound on the low probability
of the data.
The higher layers have changed because
they've learned a prior for the bottom
hidden layer that's closer to the
aggregated posterior distribution.
And that makes the model better.
So changing the hidden weights makes the
inference that we're doing at the bottom
hidden layer incorrect, but gives us a
better model.
And if you look at those two effects,
we prove that the improvement that you
get in the variation bound from having a
better model is always greater than the
loss that you get from the inference
being slightly incorrect.
So in this variation bound you win when
you learn the lights in hire less,
assuming that you do it with correct
maximizer [INAUDIBLE].
So now let's go back to what's happening
in contrasted divergence learning.
We have the infinite net on the right and
we have a restricted Boltzmann machine on
the left.
And they're equivalent.
If we were to do maximum likelihood
learning for the restricted Boltzmann
machine, it would be maximum likelihood
learning for the infinite sigmoid belief
net.
But what we're going to do is we're going
to cut things off.
We're going to ignore the small
derivitives for the weights you get in
the higher layers of the infinite sigmoid
belief net.
So, we cut it off were that dotted red
line is.
And now if we look at the derivatives,
the derivatives we're going to get look
like this.
They've got two terms.
The first term comes from that bottom
layer of nets.
We've seen that before, the router for
the bottom layer of weights is just that
first line here.
The second line comes from the next layer
of lights.
That's this line here.
We need to compute the activities in H1,
in order to compute the Sj1 in that
second line but we're not actually
computing derivatives for the third layer
of weights.
And when we take those first two terms,
and we combine them.
We get exactly the learning rule for one
step contrasted divergence.
So what's going on in contrasted
divergence, is we're combining weight
derivatives for the lower layers, and
ignoring the weight derivatives in higher
layers.
The question is, why can we get away with
ignoring those higher derivatives?
When the weights are small, the Markov
chain mixes very fast.
If the weights are zero, it mixes in one
step.
And if the Markoff chain mixes fast, the
higher layers will be close to the
equilibrium distribution, i.e.
They will have forgotten what the input
was at the bottom layer.
And now we have a nice property.
If the higher layers are sampled from the
equilibrium distribution, we know that
the derivatives of the log probability,
the data with respect to the weights,
must average out to zero.
And that's because the current weights in
the model are a perfect model of the
equilibrium distribution.
The equilibrium distribution is generated
using those weights.
And if you want to generate samples from
the equilibrium distribution, those are
the best possible weights you could have.
So we know the root is there is zero.
As the weights get larger, we might have
to run more iterations of Contrastive
Divergence.
Which corresponds to taking into account
more layers of that infinite sigmoid
belief net.
That will allow Contrasive Divergence to
continue to be a good approximation to
maximum likelihood and so if we're trying
to learn a density model, that makes a
lot of sense.
As the weights grow, you run CD for more
and more steps.
If there's a statistician around, you
give him a guarantee, then in the
infinite limit, you'll run CD for
infinite many steps.
And then you have an asymptotic
convergence result, which is the thing
that keeps statisticians happy.
Of course it's completely irrelevant
because you'll never reach a point like
that.
There is however an interesting point
here.
If our purpose in using CD is to build a
stack of restricted Boltzmann machines,
that learn multiple layers of features,
it turns out that we don't need a good
approximation to maximum likelihood.
For learning multiple layers of features,
CD1 is just fine.
In fact it's probably better than doing
maximum l likelihood.