Hi, in this module,
you will be working on a project based
on Advanced Shortest Paths algorithms.
The project will be organized as
a series of programming assignments
similar to those you had
in the previous modules.
However, in these programming assignments,
you will be working with real world data,
based on raw networks and social networks.
Also, you will have more freedom to
come up with your own creative ideas
about how to improve your algorithms.
You even can compete with your fellow
learners on the forums on how fast
does your algorithm solve a particular
problem in the problem assignment.
You've learned the classical
shortest paths algorithms in two
of the previous modules.
And you've learned
the Breadth First Search Algorithm,
Dijkstra's Algorithm and
Bellman Ford's Algorithm.
The advanced algorithms can
be faster thousands of times,
or sometimes of million
of times in practice.
But those are optimizations which work for
particular kinds of graphs.
For example, some algorithms
are very good for road networks and
some others are very good for
social networks.
All the advanced algorithms that we will
tell you in the lectures of these modules
are some optimizations based on
the classic Dijkstra's Algorithm.
So, it's good to go back and
recall how Dijkstra's Algorithm works, and
to make sure that you can solve
the problems based on Dijkstra's Algorithm
in the previous modules before
starting on the project.