In this lesson, we will study
the idea of bidirectional search.
And we will come up with the bidirectional
version of the Dijkstra's algorithm.
But first, let's recall what is
the problem that we are solving.
In mathematical terms,
we are given a graph G,
which can be either directed or
undirected.
But it has nonnegative edge weight.
This is important.
In all the lectures of this module,
we will work with only the graphs with
nonnegative edge weights,
such as travel times or distances.
We're also given a specific source
vertex as, and the target vertex T.
And we want to find the shortest path
between S and T in the graph G, so
the first question is why not just use the
Dijkstra algorithm that we already know?
It has pretty good worst case complexity,
E plus V times log V,
this is pretty good, right?
Can we even do better in the worse case?
Well, it turns out that we can.
Mikkel Thorup came up with an algorithm
in 1999 that solves this problem for
undirected graphs in linear time.
Linear times in terms of number of
edges and vertices of the graph.
Such algorithm is still not known for
directed graphs, but
for undirected graphs,
we can definitely do better.
And for directed graphs,
we can do better also.
But we just still don't know
the linear time algorithm.
However, we're not just interested
in the worst time complexity.
We're interested in the practical
performance of our algorithms.
And in practice,
the classical Dijkstra's algorithm,
on a graph of USA, with 20 million
variances and 50 million edges.
Will work roughly, for
several seconds, on average.
Several seconds, sounds like a good thing,
but when you use, for example,
Google maps, you don't want to wait for
several seconds.
You want the results on your
screen in a blink of an eye,
which in practice means that you
want them under 100 milliseconds.
And not only you,
but millions of people simultaneously
want those results in a blink of an eye.
So, that's why we need something
significantly faster for
such implications.
Now, let's consider how Dijkstra's
algorithm progresses through the graph.
You remember that it processes vertices
in order of increasing distance.
It starts with the source vertex S, and
then it processes it by
considering the outgoing edges and
finding the vertices on the other end of
those edges and relaxing those edges.
And so,
it goes to these vertices at distance one.
And the number near the edges
are the weights of the edges.
And the numbers inside the nodes
are the distances to those nodes.
And then it goes to another layer
of nodes at distance two, and
so, you see that Dijkstra's
algorithm actually goes in circles
around the source vertices,
and this is not coincidence.
You remember the Lemma that
when a vertex U is selected
via the ExtractMin procedure
in the Dijkstra's algorithm.
The estimate of distance, to this node.
Just a few.
It's guaranteed to be equal,
to the actual distance,
from the source vertex to protects you.
And also, all the nodes,
on the distance smaller than that,
have already been
processed by that moment.
This is guaranteed in
the Dijkstra's algorithm.
So, actually,
a circle of processed vertices grows.
And this is how it looks
if we want to find
a shortest path from source
vertex s to the target vertex t.
We start growing the circle
around the node s.
Until it touches point T, and
as soon as it touches point T,
we can actually stop
the distrust algorithm.
This is called earnest stopping.
Instead of scanning all
the vertices in the graph and
finding the distance from S to
all other vertices in the graph,
we only find the distances
to the notes we need.
To actually find the distance to the node
T, and the shortest path to node T.
This is an optimization of
distress algorithm already,
but this is the simplest one.
And here's the idea for
the bidirectional search.
Instead of going from S and growing
the circle until it touches point T,
we want to go simultaneously forward from
S, and backward from T until we meet.
And as soon as we meet, we can find
the shortest path between S and
T by combining the half of
the path from S to the mid-point,
and the half from the meeting point to T.
In the algorithm,
we won't go literally simultaneously.
We will take alternating turns from S and
from T.
We'll do a typical digstress
algorithm from us.
We will do one turn of that algorithm,
and then we will alternate to T, and
we will make one turn of the digstress
algorithm backwards from T.
To do that, we will need not only to
know the outgoing edges from each node,
but also all the incoming
edges to each node.
But other than that, we will do the
regular Dijkstra search from S forward,
and the regular Dijkstra search from T,
but backwards.
And we will alternate
the turns of those Dijkstra's.
So, then we will make one more turn from
S, and one more turn backwards from T.
And then one more turn from S, and
then one more turn backward from T.
And now, we see that the vertex in the
middle was discovered by both algorithms.
The forward one and the backward one.
And now, we can reconstruct
the shortest path from S to T, and
we can fill in the correct distances
from S to all the nodes on that path.
Now, let's see how it works compared
to the usual Dijkstra algorithm.
So, the usual distance
algorithm will cover and
scan the nodes in this big circle with
the center in s and touching point T.
What will happen in the directional search
is we will be growing two circles of
roughly the same radius until they touch.
And this area, covered by these
two smaller circles, is roughly
proportional to the number of vertices
scanned during the bidirectional search.
So, let's denote the big circle by C1,
and the two smaller circles by C2 and C3.
And the distance from S to the meeting
point V, which is roughly equal to
the distance from the meeting point V to
the target node, T, we'll denote by R.
Now, let's estimate the number
of covered vertices by the area
of the corresponding circle.
So, the area of the circle C1 is
pi times the radius of C1 squared.
The radius of C1 is 2r, so
its square is 4r squared.
And in the end area of
C1 is four pi r squared.
And the area covered by the directional
search is the sum or areas of C2 and C3.
The areas of C2 and C3 are roughly equal.
And the area of C2 is pi r squared.
So, the total area is two pi r squared.
And we see that the total area covered
by bi directional search is roughly
twice smaller than the area usually
covered by the usual distress algorithm.
So, let's see what happens actually
when the real world networks
when we use the simple distress algorithm,
and the bi directional search.
This is a part of the map of USA with 1.6
million vertices and 3.8 million arcs.
And we're finding the best shortest
path in terms of the travel time.
So here, we try to find the shortest path
from the small blue rectangle
to the small green rectangle in
the right edge of the map,
and we color it with green.
All the notes scanned by
the regular dextrose algorithm
while it was looking for the surest path.
And on the next picture here, we see
the result of the bid directional search.
And you see that there is
something similar to what we
draw on the previous slides.
So, there is something like a blue
circle around the starting point, and
there is something like a green
circle around the target vertex.
The green circle is cut in half
because of the edge of the map, but
in general,
this is the picture we imagine.
And here is another example
on the map of the full US.
And we see a full circle
around the green point,
although it is not like a real circle,
it's more like a related square.
But this is due to the way
we humans build the roads,
because we build them from north to south.
And from east, to west very often, and
that's why the circle is more like
a square rotated by 45 degrees.
And the blue point is surrounded by
something more like a half a circle,
which is cut by the shore.
So, roughly we get a 2x
speedup on the road networks,
which is good, but not great.
We were hoping for something like
thousands of times speed up.
But this is true for road networks, but
what if we look at social networks?
And in the next video, we will see
that indeed for social networks,
the bi directional search idea
works exceptionally well.
And it will work thousands of times faster
that the regular Dijkstra's algorithm.