So now we've proven that theorem.
And we can implement
the algorithm as follows.
We do the alternating turns
of forward search and
the backwards search until
we meet at some point v.
And we remember which vertices
are processed in forward search and
which vertices are processed
in the backward search.
Then, we take all those vertices which
are processed at least in one of them,
and for each of those vertices,
we minimize the sum of distance estimate
of the forward surge plus the distance
estimate of the backwards surge.
And for the node for
which this sum is minimal,
we know that there is a shortest
path going through this vertex.
And its length is equal to the sum
of these two distance estimates.
And then to reconstruct the path itself,
we can reconstruct the shortest path
from the source vertex to this
middle vertex in the forward search.
And separately,
we reconstruct the path from this vertex
to target vertex t in the backward search.
And then just join those two parts into
a single shortest path from s to t.
I won't show you the psuedocode
in the lecture, but
you can see it in the slides
which are uploaded.
So in conclusion, a few remarks.
First, the worst-case running
time of Bidirectional Dijkstra
is the same asymptotically as for
the regular Dijkstra algorithm.
And we saw that it can differ, for
example, twice for route networks, but
this is not an asymptotic difference.
And speedup in practice
depends on the graph, so for
the route networks it's
roughly 2x speed up.
But for social networks,
it can be thousands of times faster.
From the other hand, the memory
consumption is somewhat worse, but
again, it is not asymptotically worse.
It's just 2x to store two copies of G,
the G and the reversed G.
And also we'll need to store
some auxiliary arrays for
forward search and for backwards search,
so twice the memory for those also, so
roughly 2x memory consumption.
And you'll see the actual speedup
on social network's graphs
in one of the problems of the
Programming Assignment of this project.