We're going to end this week of lecture
with a quick discussion of missing values.
We've seen a preview of how Pandas
handles missing values using the None type
and NumPy NaN values.
Missing values are pretty common
in data cleaning activities.
There are couple of caveats and
discussion points which we should address.
First, the built in loading from
delimited files provides control for
missing values in a few ways.
The most germane of these,
is the na_values list,
to indicate other strings which
could refer to missing values.
Some of my sociologist colleagues for
instance, regularly
use the value of 99 in binary categories
to indicate that there's no value.
So this comes in handy.
You can also use the na_filter option
to turn off white space filtering,
if white space is an actual
value of interest.
But in practice, this is pretty rare.
In addition to rules controlling
how missing values might be loaded,
it's sometimes useful to consider missing
values as actually having information.
I'll give an example from my own research.
I often deal with logs from
online learning systems.
In particular,
I've done a couple of projects looking
at video use in lecture capture systems.
In these systems it's common for the player
for have a heartbeat functionality where
playback statistics are sent to the server
every so often, maybe every 30 seconds.
These heartbeats can get big as they can
carry the whole state of the playback
system, such as where the video play
head is at, where the video size is,
which video is being rendered to
the screen, how loud the volume is, etc.
If we load the data file log.txt,
we can see an example of
what this might look like.
In this data the first column is
a timestamp in the Unix epoch format.
The next column is the user name followed
by a web page they're visiting and
the video that they're playing.
Each row of the DataFrame
has a playback position.
And we can see that as the playback
position increases by one,
the time stamp increases
by about 30 seconds.
Except for user Bob.
It turns out that Bob has
paused his playback so
as time increases the playback
position doesn't change.
Note too how difficult it is for us to try
and derive this knowledge from the data,
because it's not sorted by time
stamp as one might expect.
This is actually not uncommon on systems
which have a high degree of parallelism.
There are a lot of missing values
in the paused and volume columns.
It's not efficient to send this
information across the network if it
hasn't changed.
So this particular system just inserts
null values into the database if
there's no changes.
One of the handy functions
that Pandas has for
working with missing values is
the filling function, fillna.
This function takes a number or
parameters, for
instance, you could pass in a single
value which is called a scalar value
to change all of the missing
data to one value.
This isn't really applicable in this case,
but it's a pretty common use case.
Next up though is the method parameter.
The two common fill values are ffill and
bfill.
ffill is for forward filling and
it updates an na value for
a particular cell with the value
from the previous row.
It's important to note that your
data needs to be sorted in order for
this to have the effect you might want.
Data that comes from traditional database
management systems usually has no
order guarantee, just like this data.
So be careful.
In Pandas we can sort either by index or
by values.
Here we'll just promote the time stamp
to an index then sort on the index.
If we look closely at the output
though we'll notice that the index
isn't really unique.
Two users seem to be able to use
the system at the same time.
Again, a very common case.
Let's reset the index, and
use some multi-level indexing instead, and
promote the user name to a second level
of the index to deal with that issue.
Now that we have the data indexed and
sorted appropriately, we can fill
the missing datas using ffill.
It's good to remember when
dealing with missing values so
you can deal with individual columns or
sets of columns by projecting them
just as we spoke about earlier.
So you don't have to fix all
missing values in one command.
It's sometimes useful to use forward
filling, sometimes backwards filling, and
sometimes useful to just
use a single number.
More recently, the Pandas team introduced
a method of filling missing values with
a series which is the same
length as your DataFrame.
This makes it easy to derive values
which are missing if you have
the underlying to do so.
For instance, if you're dealing with
receipts and you have a column for
final price and a column for discount but
are missing information from the original
price column, you can fill this
automatically using fillna.
One last note on missing values.
When you use statistical
functions on DataFrames,
these functions typically
ignore missing values.
For instance if you try and
calculate the mean value of a DataFrame,
the underlying NumPy function
will ignore missing values.
This is usually what you want but
you should be aware that
values are being excluded.