Our goal in this video is to show that
if we use both path compression and
union by rank heuristics then the average
running time of a single operation
is upper bounded by big
O of log star of N.
Before going into
the details of the proof,
let's realize a few important facts.
First of all, know that since we
are now using path compression,
it is no longer the case that the rank of
node i is equal to height of
the tree rooted at vertex i.
However, it is still true that
the rank is an upper bound.
On the corresponding height.
Let me illustrate this with a toy example.
So, I assume that we
have a tree like this.
So, this is root say vertex 5.
Here we have vertex 2 and
we have node 3, node say 6.
Assume that currently rank of this node
is 2 say 0, this is 1 and this also 0.
We now recall find of 6.
This will re-attach 6 to
the current root of this tree.
So what we get is the following,
5, 3, 1.
And also 6 now stays here, all right?
So we see that the height of
these three is equal to 1.
However the rank of the root
is still equal to 2.
Recall that find doesn't use and
doesn't change any rank values.
Also for this node 3, it's height.
The height of the tree rooted
at element 3 is equal to 0,
however the rank is equal to 1.
Well, intuitively it is clear path
compression can only decrease the height.
So for this reason,
rank is no longer equal
to the height of the corresponding tree
however the height is at most the length.
Okay.
Another important thing is the following.
It is still true that for
any root node i of rank k.
The corresponding sub 3 contains
at least 2 to the k elements.
And this can be seen by realizing that
the past compression does not affect
any root nodes.
I mean,
if we have a root node whose height is k,
then no matter how many times and
for which nodes in these sub tree
we call find with path compression,
all this nodes are still in
this subtree rooted at this nodes
exactly because this node is a root.
So any node from this
subtree cannot be attached
to some other vertex and
some other subtree.
This node is still, so once again if
we have a node who is still a root and
whose rank is k, then the corresponding
subtree contains at least 2 to
the k elements, 2 to the k nodes.
On this slide we discuss a few
more important properties.
The first one of them says that we have,
in our forest, at most n divided
by 2 to the k nodes of rank k.
Why is that?
Well, recall that if we
create a new node of rank k
then it was created by merging
two nodes of rank k-1.
Okay.
So we know that currently
this node is a root.
At the same time,
we know that the correspondence subtree
contains at least 2 to the k nodes.
If we have another another node of rank k.
Then it also contains at
least 2 to the k nodes.
Which means that if we
have too many such nodes.
I mean, too many nodes of rank k.
By saying too many, I mean that its number
is greater than n divided by 2 to the k.
Then overall, we have more than n element.
Which is a contradiction, right?
The second property is that,
when we go up,
the rank strictly increases.
Well, this was clear if we
do not use past compression.
I mean, if rank is equal to the height
of the corresponding subtree,
then this is completely clear.
Let me recall that if we have for
example a tree
of height two,
then the height of this tree is two.
The height of this subtree is one.
The height of this subtree is zero.
Let's say this is element 5.
This is 4.
This is 8.
Now we have passed compression,
so we need to check what happens
when we compress some paths.
If we call Find(5), for example, then
we'll be reattached to the current root.
But it will still be 2.
That the rank of the parent.
So let me fix this.
This is node 8.
The rank of the parent is strictly
greater than the rank of a child.
The last property is,
says that when a node
becomes an internal node it will be
an internal node forever, right.
It will not have a chance to become
a root and this is just because
the find operation doesn't
change any roots in our forest.
While union operation takes two roots and
makes one of them a child
of the other one.
So it takes two roots and
leaves only one root.
Okay.
So once again when a vertex
becomes an internal vertex,
a non root vertex,
it will be a non root vertex forever.
We now start to estimate
the running time of M operations.
First of all note that the union operation
boils down to T(all calls
to FInd) operation.
And also to some constant operations.
Namely, when we have two roots
that were found by two calls to.
To find that operation,
we need to hank one of them below other
one which is a constant operation.
We just need to change one parent.
And also possibly we need
to change the rank value.
Okay.
So for this reason when estimating
the total running time we will just assume
that we have m calls to find operation.
Paths node that each Find
operation traverses some
pass from a note to find the root
of the corresponding tree.
So we traverse some number of edges.
So the total run in time of
all the defind operations,
of all the calls to defind operation is
just the total number of edges traversed.
So this is what is written here,
we just need to count the number
of edges from parent a node
i through it's paring j,
at traverse you know these codes.
For technical reasons we will split
this number into three terms.
In the first term we will
account all the edges that
lead from a vertex to the node to
the root of the corresponding tree.
So the first term includes
all the edges that lead from
a node to another node,
which is the root in this case.
The second term include all the remaining
edges where we go from i to j.
Such as there log* of rank of
a is strictly smaller than
log* of rank of j, okay?
And their remaining term accounts for
everything else,
namely for all the edges where we go
from i to j such that j is not the root.
And that log*(rank[i]) = log*(rank[j])).
We're going to show separately for
each of these terms that it
is upper bounded by big 0 of m
multiplied by log star of m.
Let me show this on
a small example as usual.
Assumes that we have such a path
that we're going to traverse.
A path from the node at the bottom to
the root of the corresponding tree.
So the numbers shown here indicate
the ranks of the corresponding nodes.
Then these two nodes, these two edges
will be accounted in the first term.
Just because these two nodes lead from
a node to the root this thread just lead
from a node to the root of
the corresponding tree.
Well, this edge for
example will be accounted in the last
term because the rank
of this node is 17 and
the rank of this node is 21.
And log star of this numbers are equal.
At the same time, here we have 14
the rank 14, and here we have rank 17.
And the log star of these
two numbers are different.
For this reason this hatch will be
accounted in the second term, okay?
So on the next sequence of slides,
we are going to estimate separately
each of these three terms.
And for each of them, we are going to
show that it is at most big O of m
multiplied by log* of m.
The first term is easy to estimate.
Recall that in this term we account for
all the edges traversed by find operation.
Where we go from node i to its
parent j such that j is the root.
Clearly for
each call to find the operation
there are at most two side edges, right?
Which means that we have
an upper bound big O of m.
In the second term, we need to estimate
that a long number of edges traversed
it during all m calls
to the find operation.
Such that we go from node i to its
parent j such that j is not the root and
also log star of rank of i is strictly
less than log star of rank of j.
We're going to prove here that
it is upper bounded by big O of
m multiplied by log star of n.
And this is just because,
when we go up from some node to
the root of the corresponding tree,
the rank always increases.
However, the rank of the root is at most
log n, which means that during one call
to find procedure the lock star of rank
can only increase log star of n times.
Okay.
This is just because we've had an upper
bound for the rank of the root.
It is upper bounded by log
m which means that there
are only log star of m
different possibilities for
log star of rank of folds and
nodes on this.
Which means, that these can only increase,
at most, log star of m times.
And we have at most,
m calls to find the operations.
Which gives us, an upper bound m,
to get, m multiplied by log star of m.
Now it remains to estimate the last term.
Where we account for
all the address traversed during
m calls to the find operations.
Where we go from node i to node j through
its parent j such that j is not the root,
first of all.
And then the rank, the log star of rank
of i is equal to log star of n of j.
What we're going to show is that
the total number of side edges
is upper bounded by big O of m
multiplied by log star of m.
Note that this is even
better than what we need.
What we need is a recap upper
bound which is m log star of n.
Recall that we know that m is greater
than m just because m is the total number
of operations, while n is the number
of calls to make said operations.
To estimate the required term, consider
a particular node i and assume for
completeness that it's rank lies in an
interval from k plus one to two to the k.
Recall that this was the form of interval
through which the lock
star function is fixed.
Okay?
Now let's compute the total number of
nodes whose rank lies in section interval.
So we know that the total
number of nodes whose rank
is equal to k plus one is at most n
divided by two, to the k plus one.
So total number of nodes was ranked equal
to k plus two is at most n divided by two,
to k plus two.
And so on, so the total number
of nodes whose rank lies in this
interval is at most n
divided by two to the k.
Okay.
The next stop equation is that each time
when we call Find of i, it is adopted
by a new parent and since it is new.
So, at this point we know that if we have
a node i and its parent j is not the root.
Yes, this is essential.
Which means that when we go up we find
another root when we cofind a Find of i.
And at this point we will
reattach node i to this new root.
And this new root has
strictly larger rank.
And this in turn means that after
most 2 to the k calls to find of i.
Find(i) will be adopted by a new parent
whose rank, for sure,
does not lie in this interval.
Just because the rank of this
interval is at most 2 to the k.
So if we increase the rank
of the parent of i,
at least 2 to the k times, it will
be greater than 2 to the k for sure.
Right.
We now have everything
to conclude this proof.
To conclude estimating the required term.
Recall that we are estimating
the total number of address traversed
during n calls to client.
Where we go from a node i to its parent j,
such that log star of rank of a is
equal to log star of rank of j.
So we have just proved that there are at
most n divided by 2 to the k nodes
whose rank lies in the interval
from k plus 1 to 2 to the k.
We then explained why Any such node
whose rank lies in such an interval,
contributes, at most, 2 to the k to
the term that we are currently estimating.
This means that just all the nodes from,
whose rank lies in such an interval.
Contributes, at most big O
of N to this term, right?
Now it remains to note that the total
number of different intervals
is at most log star of n.
Which means that the total contribution
of all such nodes i to the estimated
term is at most big O of n
Multiplied by log star of n.
We now conclude the whole lesson.
So in this lesson we considered it
an implementation of the joins of
data structure where each set
is represented by a tree.
And for
this reason we have a forest of trees.
The ID of each set is just the root
of the corresponding tree.
We then consider it to heuristics.
The first one is called Union by rank.
It says that when merging two trees,
it makes sense to attach
a shorter one to the root of a taller one,
okay?
This helps to keep trees
in our forest shallow.
And for this we keep the rank
of each subtree rooted
at a particular node in
a separate array called rank.
We then discussed another heuristic
which is called Path compression.
The idea is the following.
When we traversed a path from a node
to the root of the corresponding tree,
we may want to reattach all the nodes
found on this path directly to the root.
Because this potentially will save us
time for further find operations, right.
We then proved that the resulting
implementation turns out
to be extremely efficient,
namely the amortized running time of each
operation is big O of log star of n.
And log star of n is an extremely
slowly growing function.
In particular, log* n is at most five for
all practical values of n.