Hi, in this video we will apply
the idea of bidirectional search
to social networks data.
And we will see that it will
work exceptionally well,
going up to thousands of times faster.
But first, let's learn
an interesting fact about our world.
So in 1929, Hungarian mathematician,
Frigyes Karinthy,
made a Small World conjecture,
which you probably heard of already.
So the conjecture was that basically
when we need to pass a message from
any person on earth to any
other person on earth, using
only personal connections in between,
we need at most six handshakes to do that.
So that we need only at most five
intermediary people to pass a message
from anyone to anyone else on earth.
This is somewhat surprising, but
it turned out to be close to truth in
different experiments which people
made after that conjecture.
And this is called the six handshakes or
six degrees of separation idea.
Now let's look at the most
popular social network,
Facebook, given that six handshakes idea.
So suppose an average person on
Facebook has around 100 friends.
Then if we consider friends
of friends of that person,
it will be 100 times 100 roughly,
that's 10,000 friends of friends.
If we consider friends of friends of
friends, that will be 100 times more or
1 million.
And if we progress with that,
we'll get that at six handshakes,
we will have 1 trillion people.
Well, that's not actually possible,
as there are only roughly
7 billion people on Earth.
So it will be much less than that,
but you get the general idea, that
the number of friends grows exponentially
when we increase the distance.
So now we want to find the shortest
path from Michael to Bob
via friends connections.
So we want to know,
actually how many handshakes do we need
to send a message from Michael to Bob.
And if Michael and
Bob turned out to be the two farthest
people on the Facebook social network,
then the regular Dijkstra's algorithm
would have to look through all
roughly 2 billion people which are on
Facebook to find that shortest path.
Now what will happen if we
consider bidirectional search?
So we'll only consider friends of
friends of friends of Michael and
friends of friends of friends of Bob.
And if we know that the six handshakes
conjecture is true, then there will be
a common person among friends of
friends of friends of Michael and
friends of friends of friends of Bob.
If we find that person in common, then
we'll find the shortest path of friends,
at most, six between Michael and Bob.
And to do that we can create a hash table,
for example,
of all the friends of friends of
friends of Michael or a sorted list.
And then search the friends of friends
of friends of Bob in that hash table or
ordered list, one by one,
to find the common person.
And how many people will we
actually consider in this case?
We'll have roughly 1 million
friends of friends of friends for
both Michael and Bob, so
in total, 2 million people.
And this will work in linear
time if we use hash tables.
So this will be actually 1,000 times
faster than using Dijkstra's algorithm,
at least in the number of friends scanned.
So this is going to work really thousands
of times faster on social networks.
And what we've just seen is a particular
case of a more general idea called
meet in the middle, and
this applies not only to graphs.
So, in general if you need to search for
some best object of some kind, for
example, the best shortest path or
a best subset of people to create a team,
then instead of searching for
all possible objects,
all the possible shortest paths or
all possible subsets of people,
we can somehow divide all
the possible objects into halves.
For example, when we are searching for
shortest paths, we can divide any path
on the first half from the source and
the second half to the target.
And when we are talking, for
example, about subsets of people,
if we have N people, we can divide any
subset of N people into two halves.
First half consists of a subset of
the first N of our two people, and
the second half consists of a subset
of the second N of our two people.
And then we can search
all the variants for
the first half separately, all the
variants for the second half separately.
And then we just need to
find the compatible halves.
So for example,
we again create a hash table or
an or at least of the first
halves which are possible.
And then for each particular second half,
we try to find
whether there's a compatible first
half to it in this hash table.
And this is in general how
meet in the middle works.
And typically, instead of searching
through all possible big N objects,
this works in time proportional
to square root of N,
because only square root of
N halves of those objects.
Square root of N of
the shortest paths halves and
square root of N for
first halves of the subset of people.
So this idea can be applied in many,
many different problems to
take a significant speed up.
So in conclusion, we understood that
the regular Dijkstra's algorithm
goes in circles of increasing
radius around the starting point.
And the bidirectional search idea
can reduce the search space.
We can scan less vertices than if we
go from one source and grow the circle.
And on the raw networks it works
roughly twice faster than the regular
Dijkstra's algorithm.
But if we use this meet in the middle
idea on the social networks,
or actually on many other problems,
then it will roughly work as
a square root of N instead of big N
if big N is the total number of
objects we need to search through.
And in social networks,
it can be thousands times faster than
the regular Dijkstra's algorithm.
And you will actually see that in one
of the problems of the programming
assignments of this project.
And in the next video,
we will actually come
up with a bidirectional version
of Dijkstra's algorithm.