Hi in the previous videos we've introduced
the idea of Bidirectional Search.
But now we need to actually specify,
how exactly will we expand the Dijkstra
algorithm to become bidirectional.
First let's recall how
Dijkstra's algorithm works, so
it needs to find the shortest path
from some vertex s to vertex t.
It initializes an auxiliary area dist,
with a values of infinity for
all the nodes but for the starting node s.
And for the starting node s,
it initialize the distance estimate to 0,
and then it goes in iterations.
On each iteration it calls ExtractMin,
to chose the unprocessed vertex u
with the smallest distance estimate.
And there is a guarantee that,
by the time vertex u is extracted
that way, it's distance estimate,
is equal to the actual distance from
the starting vertex as to the vertex u.
And then we process u, meaning that we try
to relax all the edges outgoing from u.
And then we repeat this process,
until t is extracted and
processed, so
then we know that the distance to t
is already equal to the distance estimate,
in the distance array.
Now, we need to introduce
a notion of reverse graph,
for our bidirectional search.
So the reversed graph G, R for a graph
G is the graph with the same vertices.
And reversed edges.
You have an example in
the bottom of the slide.
When we have vertices a, b and c.
And the graph G is on the left with
edges going from a to b, from a to c and
from b to c.
And in the graph Gr,
the vertices are the same, but
the edges go the other way around,
from b to a, from c to a, and from c to b.
So this is very simple, and
to build the reversed graph,
we can just copy the vertices.
And then, go through all the edges
of graph G, reverse them,
and add them to the new graph GR.
So the Bidirectional Dijkstra's algorithm,
we'll start with building
the reversed graph.
So that it can do the backward
search from the target vertex.
And then, it will start Dijkstra's
algorithm in the forward direction from,
the source vertex as in the graph G,
and also the backwards
Dijkstra's algorithm from vertex
t in the reverse graph GR.
So in the reverse graph GR,
The regular Dijkstra's algorithm will be
the same as the backwards Dijkstra's
algorithm in the initial graph of G.
And then will alternate
between Dijkstra steps in
the forward search in G, and
in the backward search in GR.
And we will stop, as soon as some vertex
v is processed, and remember that,
process means that it is extracted
from the Q with variances.
Both in the forward search and
in the backward search.
As soon as that happens, we can compute
the shortest path between s and t.
And I will show you how, in a minute.
But first the question, so
let's consider this meeting point v.
The first vertex that is processed
in both the forward search and
the backward search.
We said previously,
that as soon as we meet in the forward and
backward search, we can re-construct
the shortest path from s to t by
taking the first half from
s to the meeting point.
And then from the meeting point to t.
So, is it right, is it always the case
that as soon as we meet in some vertex,
v, there's the shortest part
from s to t that goes through v?
So, what do you think?
Well, it turns out that this is not
the case, and here's an example.
S and t, we do alternating terms
from s and from t backwards,
then from s, then from t backwards.
And inside the vertices,
we have the distances on the left
from s and on the right to t.
And then we meet, in the middle vertex.
And we see that the distance
from this vertex 2t is 5,
and the distance from s
to this vertex is 5, and
we can actually reconstruct
the path of length 10 from s to t.
But what if there was an edge,
this green one, I'll find 4.
This wouldn't contradict the progression
of neither the forward Dijkstra search,
nor the backward Dijkstra search because,
this edge has length 4,
which is bigger than 3.
And so the middle vertex
will be considered before,
the vertex to the right from
it in the forward search.
And also, the middle vertex will
be considered before the vertex
to the left from it in
the backwards search.
So, we will really meet in the middle
vertex before even considering.
The edge between the vertex
to the left of the middle,
and the vertex to
the right from the middle.
But, here we can see that
the shortest path from s to t,
doesn't actually go
through the middle vertex.
It goes around it, and
it is a length 8, instead of the path
which goes through this middle vertex and
has length 10.
So it is not always the case,
that the shortest path go
through the meeting point.
So what exactly then do we need to do,
to compute the distance?
When we found the common meeting point.