It is not always the case
that the shortest
path go through the meeting point.
So what exactly then do we need
to do to compute the distance
when we found the common meeting point,
and is it actually possible?
Well it is possible, but
it is little bit more complicated.
So let's denote by dist of
u the distance estimate in
the forward Dijkstras from source
s in G and by dist R of u.
The same but the distance estimated in
the backward Dijkstra from T in the GR.
So dist R is an estimate of the distance
from u to the target vertex T.
So after some node v is
processed in both G and GR.
I say that there exists some shortest path
from s to t which passes though some node
U which is processed either is the forward
search or backward search or in both.
And the distance from the s to t
is equal to the distance estimate
of u in the forward search,
plus the distance estimate of
the backwards search from u.
What it means is that there exist some
vertex u that chooses path from s to t,
at least some of this path from s
to t goes through this vertex u.
And this u is either processed in G,
or is processed in GR.
And also, the distance estimates for
that vertex are already correct for
both forward search and backward search.
So of course, if it is processed
in the forward search, for
example, then we know that the distance
estimated to this node is already correct.
That the distance from
source vertex to this node u
is equal to it's distance
estimate dist of u.
But if it's not yet processed in the
backwards search, in the reverse search,
then this is not guaranteed in
the general case for the dist r.
For the distance estimate
in the backwards search.
But we can show that for
some node u is actually
also a correct estimate
which is equal to the distance to the
distance from U to the target vertex t.
So there exists some nodes u and
some shortest path that this node u lies
on the shortest path and both distance
estimates from source to u and u to target
are already correct by the moment our
forward search meets our backward search.
Now, let's prove this dilemma.
So, we have these two gray circles,
which show us
this can't vertices by the forward search
from s, and by the backward search from t.
And they touch in the vertex v,
which is the meeting point.
Now first, let's prove that
if there is some node u which
is not processed by forward search and
is not processed by the backward search.
And there is the shortest path from
s to t going through this node u,
that then there is also shortest path
which goes from s to t through v.
To see that, first let's compare
the first half of the shortest path from
s to t going through u to
the shortest path from s to v.
We know that v is already processed
in the forward search and
it means that the distance from s to v
is at most the distance from s to u.
So here the green part is less than or
equal to the red part.
Also if we consider the backward the extra
search, we know that v Is processed,
but u is still not processed
in this backward search.
So, the right half,
the green right half is also less than or
equal to the red half.
So, in both halves, the green parts
are less than or equal to the red parts.
And this means that the path from s
to t going through v is shorter or
of the same length as the shortest
path from s to t going through u.
So it means that actually the path from s
to t going through v is the shortest path.
And so in this case,
our theorem is proved.
If there is at least some one vertex u
which is not processed by forward and
not processed by backwards search.
And there's a shortest path going through
the vertex then there is a shortest path,
another one which goes
through the vertex v.
Which is already processed by
both forward and backward search.
And of course both distance
estimates of v are already correct.
Because it's already processed in
both backwards and forward search.
Now let's consider another
case when there are no
varices which are unprocessed by
both forward and backward searches.
But we already meet a point v.
So let's consider then any shortest spot
from s to t, and let's consider the last
vertex u on such shortest spot that
is processed by the forward surge.
So u is the last vertex which
is on the shortest path,
which is processed by the forward search.
And then the distance estimates of u in
the forward search is already correct.
This is equal to the distance from s to u.
Let's consider the next
edge of the shortest path.
It goes to some vertex w.
And this vertex w has to be
processed by the backward search.
Why?
Because w is not processed by the forward
search because u is the last
vertex of the shortest path
which is processed by the forward surge.
And w cannot be unprocessed
by both forward and
backward search,
because it lies on the shortest path.
And so w is indeed inside
the gray circle around t,
it is indeed already processed
by the backward search.
And so the distance estimate of the
backwards search for w is already correct.
It is already equal to
the distance from w to t.
Now, what we know is that
the distance between s and
t is equal to the distance from s to u.
Which is equal to
the distance estimate of u,
dist of u plus length of
the edge from u to w.
Plus distance from w to t which is already
equal to the distance estimate of
the backward search, dist R of w.
And now what we want to prove is that
this is also equal to the sum of distance
estimate of u and
the reverse distance estimate of u.
So the first sum is the same.
And now I claim that the distance
estimate in the reverse direction
is equal to the sum of the two other
summons in the first equation.
Why is that?
Well from one point of view we know
that the distance estimate of u
is always bigger or
equal to the real distance from u to t.
Because the distance
estimate in any moment
of Dijkstra's algorithm is greater or
equal to the real distance.
From the other hand,
we know that the vertex w is already
processed in the reversed search.
And when it was processed, in particular,
the edge from u to w was relaxed
in the backwards search.
And when it was relaxed it
made sure that the distance
estimate of u in reverse
direction is at most this sum
of length of this edge plus
the distance estimate for w.
So we know that distance
estimate of u is at most.
A length of edge from u to w
plus distance estimate of w.
But this sum is the length of the shortest
path from u to t going through w.
So in fact, we know that distance
estimate of u is both greater or
equal than the true
shortest path from u to t.
And also is less than or equal to
the shortest path from F from u to t.
And this means that it is exactly equal
to the shortest path from u to t.
And that the distant from
s to t is actually equal
to the distance estimate a u plus
the reverse distance estimated of u.