Hello everybody, welcome back.
Today we're going to talk more about
binary searches, in particular we're going
to give a couple of applications
to computing order statistics.
And then a sort of additional
use of binary search trees,
to store assorted lists.
Okay, so, there's some questions
that you might want to ask.
You've got a bunch of elements that
are stored in this binary search
tree data structure.
They're assorted by some ordering.
Things we might want to do.
We might want to find
the 7th largest element.
Or maybe we want the median element,
or the 25th percentile element.
Now, these are all instances
of an order statistic problem.
We would like to be able to be given
the root of the T tree and the number k,
we should be able to return the kth
smallest element stored in the T tree.
So, the basic idea is that this
is sort of a search problem.
We sort of should treat it like one.
But to do that we need to know
which subtree to search in.
So I mean, is the case smallest
element in the left subtree?
Well, the left subtree does store
a bunch of the smallest elements.
But the real question is,
does it store k of them?
If it stores at least, k,
k's smallest element should be in there,
otherwise it won't be.
So the thing that we need to know, is how
many elements are in the left subtree?
And so, we really need a tree
where we can easily tell
how many elements are in each subtree.
Well, there's an easy fix for that.
You just add that as a new field.
So N.Size should return the number
of elements in the subtree of N.
It's a new field, it stores that, it
should satisfy the property, that the size
of N is the size of the left subtree, and
the size of the right subtree, plus one,
all added together, where if you have
null pointers, these have size zero.
Okay?
Now, we have to be a little bit careful,
just like with the height,
we couldn't just define this field and
hope that it always has the right value.
You actually need to do some work
to make sure this stays correct.
For example, when you perform a rotation,
the sizes of various subtrees will change.
Fortunately, only the sort of two nodes
that you moved around, will actually have
their subtree sizes changed, but
you do need to deal with those.
And so, we're going to have
an operation called RecomputeSize,
which just recomputes the size as the sum
of the size of its left child, and
the size of its right child, and one.
And then to do a rotation,
we should do this as we did before.
But then we need to recompute the sizes
of the two nodes that we rotated.
And you need to make sure to do
this in the right order, actually,
because the size of the parent
depends on the size of the child.
So you need to recompute the child first.
Okay, but once you got all
the sizes of nodes stored,
it's actually not hard to
compute order statistics.
So to compute the kth smallest
element in your tree, R,
what you do is we let s be the size
of the left sub tree, R.Left.Size.
Now, if k = s+1, they're exactly
s things smaller than the root.
The root is the s plus firsts
smallest element, so we return R.
Otherwise, if k < s + 1, the kth
smallest element is in the left subtree,
so recursively return the kth smallest
element of our .Left subtree.
On the other hand, if k > s+1,
we need to look in the right subtree.
Now unfortunately, it's no longer the kth
smallest element of the right subtree,
because there were already
s+1 smaller elements.
So what we actually need to
compute is the k-s-1st smallest
element in the right subtree.
But with this minor adjustment,
this algorithm works.
The runtime is all of the height
of the node that you search for,
it's basically just a binary search.
But we need to use these sizes of trees
in order to just figure out which side to
look at, instead of comparing the actual
keys, but this works perfectly well.
Now here's a puzzle that
I'm going to give you.
We're not going to do homework on this,
but it's something you should think about.
What we've shown you how to do is,
given a rank, k,
we can find the kth smallest node.
How would you do the opposite?
Given a node, figure out how many
nodes in the tree are smaller than it.
You can do it using this kind of thing,
but it takes a little bit of thinking.
Okay that was one problem.
We're going to talk about one more
application of binary search trees.
And, this problem's a little bit weird,
but
it's going to introduce
some very important ideas.
So we have an array of squares,
they're each colored black or white.
And we want to be able to perform this
flip operation, which what it does is it
sort of points at some square, x,
and every square after that index,
it flips them from black to white,
and white to black.
So, in the array pictured, we're flipping
the last four guys, and they go from being
white, white, black, white,
to being black, black, white, black.
Okay.
So, formally, we sort of want a data
structure that maintains this.
You can create an array of size n,
you can ask for
the color of the mth square, or
you can fun this flip operation,
which flips the color of all
the squares after index x.
Okay, those are the things
we want to support.
Now, we could do this by just having
an array and storing all the colors.
The problem is that the flip
would be pretty slow.
Because if you wanted to flip all of
the things with index bigger than x,
then there's no good way to do this.
You just have to sort of go through every
square of index bigger than x, and flip
them, and that could take linear time.
So it turns out that there's a nice way
to use binary search trees to solve this.
And this requires sort of
a slightly different way of
thinking about binary search trees.
Up until now we thought of a search
tree as sort of having a bunch of
elements there stored, and
they allow you to do searches on them.
And so somehow you're given the keys, and
the search tree allows you to find them.
But there's another way to do it.
And maybe a good way to illustrate it,
is by looking at the logo for our course.
So this is a binary search tree.
Every node has a letter in it.
But you'll note that this isn't
sorted in terms of these letters.
For example, O is the left child of I, but
O comes after I in alphabetical order.
These things aren't sorted alphabetically.
On the other hand, you'll note that
the binary search tree structure
actually does tell you what order these
letters are supposed to be going in.
I mean, the smallest thing here should
be A, because it's the left child,
of the left child, of the left child,
of the left child.
Then L is the next smallest, then G,
then O, R, I, then T, H, M, S.
And so, it tells us what order these
layers are supposed to be, and
they spell algorithms.
And that's the basic idea, that you can
use a tree to store some sort of sorted
list of things, in a convenient way.
So, for
example we have the following tree.
There are no actual keys stored on them,
but of this A, B, C,
D, and E, one of these is the 5th
smallest element in the tree.
Which one is it?
Well, it's D.
I mean you sort of count
the smallest sum left, then B,
then this other thing,
and D is the 5th smallest.
Okay, so what's the point?
How are we going to use
this to do our flip arrays?
What we're going to do is, instead
of storing the sequence of black and
white cells as an array,
we're going to store it as a list.
And in this list we're going to
have a bunch of nodes,
they're going to be colored black or
white, fine.
Actually, there's a bit of a clever thing.
We're actually going to want two trees,
one with the normal colors, and
one with the opposite colors.
And the reason for
this is that when we want to do flips,
we want to be able to replace
things with their opposite colors.
So, it helps to have everything
opposited already stored somewhere.
But now comes the really clever bit.
If we wanted to do this flip operation,
say we wanted to take the last three
elements of our tree and flip all of
their colors, well this second tree,
this dual tree, the last three elements
of that tree, have the opposite colors.
So all that we need to do is swap the last
three elements of the tree on the left,
the last three elements of
the tree on the right, and
we have effectively swapped those colors.
And what's even better is
that using these merge and
split operations from last time,
we can actually do this.
So let's see how this is implemented.
Firstly, to create this thing,
we just build two trees, where T1,
all of the things are colored white,
and T2, they're all colored black.
Great.
To find the color of the mth node,
you just find the mth node within T1 and
return its color.
Great.
The flip operation is the interesting bit.
If we wanted to Flip(x), what you do is,
you split T1 at x into two halves,
and you split T2 at x, and
then you merge them back together.
But you merge the left half of T1,
with the right half of T2, and
you merge the left half of T2,
with the right half of T1.
And that effectively did move around
the sort of last N bits, and it works.
And so, as the moral,
trees can actually be used for
more than just performing
searches on things.
We can use them to store these
sorted lists, and merge and
split then become very
interesting operations,
in that they can allow us to
recombine these lists in useful ways.
Okay, so that's all for
these applications.
Next time we're going to sort of talk,
we're going to give an optional lecture,
and it's going to talk about
an alternative way to implement
many of these useful binary
search tree operations.
So, please come to that, it'll be
interesting, but it's not really required.
It's another way to do some of this stuff.
But, I hope I'll see you there.