Hello everybody.
Welcome back.
Today, I'm going to be talking
about priority queues.
This popular data structure has built-in
implementations in many programming
languages.
For example in C++, Java, and Python.
And in this lesson, we will learn what is
going on inside these implementations.
We will see beautiful combinatorial
ideas that allow to store the contents
of a priority queue in
a complete binary tree,
which is in turn stored just as an array.
This give an implementation which
is both time and space efficient.
Also, it can be implemented
just in a few lines of code.
A priority queue data structure is
a generalization of the standard
queue data structure.
Recall that the queue data structure
supports the following two
main operations.
So we have a queue and
when a new element arrives,
we put it to the end of this queue
by calling the method PushBack(e).
And when we need to process the next
element we extract it from the beginning
of the queue by calling
the method PopFront().
In the priority queue data structure,
there is no such thing as the beginning or
the end of a queue.
Instead we have just a bag of elements,
but each element is assigned a priority.
When a new element arrives,
we just put it inside this bag
by calling the method Insert.
However, when we need to process
the next element from this bag,
we call the method
ExtractMax which is supposed
to find an element inside this bag
whose priority is currently maximum.
A typical use case for
priority queues is the following.
Assume that we have a machine and
we would like to use this machine for
processing jobs.
It takes time to process a job and
when we are processing the current job,
a new job may arrive.
So we would like to be able to quickly
perform the following operations.
First of all, when a new job arrives
we would like to insert it to the pool
of our other weekly jobs quickly, right?
And when we are done with the current job,
we would like to be able to
quickly find the next job.
That is,
the job with the maximum priority.
Okay, and now we are ready to state
the definition of priority queue formally.
Formally a priority queue is
an abstract data type which supports
the two main operations,
Insert and ExtractMax.
Consider a toy example.
We have a priority queue
which is initially empty.
We then insert element 5 in it,
we then insert 7,
then insert 1, and then insert 4.
So we put these elements in random
places inside this box on the left,
just to emphasize, once again,
that there is no such thing as the beginning
or the end of a priority queue.
So it is not important how the elements
are stored inside the priority queue.
What is important for us now is that if we
call ExractMax() for this priority queue,
then an element with currently
highest priority should be extracted.
In our toy example it is 7.
So if we call ExtractMax for
this priority queue,
then 7 is taken out of the priority queue.
Then, well let's insert 3
into our priority queue and
now let's call ExtractMax().
The currently highest priority is 5,
so we extract 5.
Then we ExtractMax() once again,
and now it is 4, okay?
Some additional operations that
we might expect from a particular
implementation of a priority queue
data structure are the following.
So first of all,
we might want to remove an element.
I mean, not to extract an element
with a maximum priority, but
to remove a particular element
given by an iterator, for example.
Also, we might want to find
the maximum priority without extracting
an element with a maximum priority.
So GetMax is an operation
which is responsible for this.
And also, we might want to change
the priority of a given element.
I mean, to increase or
to decrease its priority.
So ChangePriority(it,p) is
the operation responsible for this.
Let us conclude this introductory
video by mentioning a few examples of
famous algorithms that use
priority queues essentially.
Dijsktra's algorithm uses priority queues
to find efficiently the shortest path from
point a to point b on a map or in a graph.
Prim's algorithm uses priority queues to
find an optimum spanning tree in a graph,
this might be useful for
example in the following case.
Assume that you have a set of computers
and you would like to connect them
in a network by putting wires
between some pairs of them.
And you would like to
minimize the total price or
the total length of all the wires.
Huffman's algorithm
computes an optimum prefix-free
encoding of a string or a file.
It is used, for example,
in MP3 audio format encoding algorithms.
Finally, heap sort algorithm
uses priority queues
to efficiently sort the n given objects.
So it is comparison based algorithm.
It's running time is n log n,
as in particularly in the worst case.
And another advantage of this
algorithm is that it is in place,
it uses no extra memory for
sorting the input data.
So we will go through all these algorithms
in this specialization and the heap sort
algorithm will be even covered in this
lesson, in the forthcoming videos.