Hello, and welcome to the next lesson
in the Divide-and-Conquer model.
This lesson is going to be devoted to
the quick sort algorithm, which is
one of the most efficient and commonly
used in practice sorting algorithms.
Well, as usual, we start with
the overview of this algorithm.
The algorithm is comparison based,
meaning that it sorts the n given
elements by comparing pairs of them.
Its running time is also asymptotically
n log n, but not in the worst case,
as was with the merge sort algorithm,
for example, but on the average case.
This is because this
algorithm is randomized,
so it uses random numbers to
sort the given n objects.
Well, we will explain later in
this lesson what this means.
Finally, as I said before, this algorithm
is very efficient in practice and,
at the same time, not so
difficult to implement.
This is a toy example explaining the main
idea of the quick sort algorithm.
So given an array, in this case of
size 11, let's take its first element.
In this case it is 6.
And let's do the following.
Let's rearrange all
the elements in this array such
that the element 6 stays
in its final position.
All the elements that go before
it are actually at most 6.
And all the elements that go after 6,
after this element, are greater than 6.
Well, we will show that this can be done
by a single scan of the initial array.
This is how the resulting
array looks like.
So once again,
6 stays in its final position.
All the elements before it are at most 6.
All the elements after
it are greater than 6.
So we do not need to move 6 anymore.
It is already in its final position.
So what remains to be done is to sort
all the elements that go before 6 and
all the elements that go after 6.
And this can be done just with two
recursive calls to the same algorithm,
to the quick sort algorithm.
So we do this,
and immediately after these two
recursive calls, we have a sorted array.
Well, in the next video we will explain
all the details of this algorithm.