In this video we are going
to prove formally
an upper bound on the running time of
the randomized quick sort algorithm.
Namely we're going to prove that
the running time on average of
the randomized quick sort
algorithm is n log n.
That is it must be go for n log n.
And that is, that, in the worst case,
the running time is big O of n squared.
Well, before going into
the details of the proof.
Let's again, intuition.
First of all, let's know that what we need
to estimate is the number of comparisons.
Why is that?
Well because a quick
sort algorithm contains
of first the call to the partition
procedure and then to recursive calls.
Each of these two recursive calls
is going to be unwinded into
the call to partition procedure and
another to small recursive calls.
So what is going on inside the quick
sort algorithm is essentially many calls
to the partition procedure.
While inside the partition procedure,
what we do actually is to compare
all the elements of the curve and
separate who is the pivot element, right?
So what we estimate is a total
number of comparisons.
Which is not surprising
because the quick sort
algorithm is a comparison based algorithm.
Well, now let me also explain why
balanced partitions are better for us.
I will explain this intuitively.
So consider this story example.
This array of size seven.
Assume that we selected
one as the pivot element.
So we partitioned the rate
is shown here on the left.
Now let's see what we now know.
We can pair it all the elements in
this array to the pivot element
which is one in this case.
So now we know that one,
the final position of
the pivot element is just
the first position in the array.
So we known that 1 is the minimum value.
However, we know nothing about
pairs of other elements, right?
So we only learn that 1
is the minimum value.
Now consider another possibility,
consider the following balanced
partition shown on the right.
So assume that we selected
4 as the pivot element.
I claimed that in this case,
this partition is much better for
us because we saved many
subsequent comparisons.
So look, in this case, in the subsequent
trends of the partition precision,
we are not going to compare elements 3,
1, 2 with element 6, 5, 7.
Because we already know that all
the elements to the left are for a.
As in all the elements
to the right are formed.
Well the left part will stay in
a separate recursive code and
the right part well stay in
a separate recursive code.
So once again, balanced partitions
save us a lot of comparisons
that we do not need to make in the
subsequent calls to partition procedure.
Another thing I would like to
discuss with you before growing and
know details of the proof
is the following.
Our algorithm is randomized,
so its running time and
its number of comparisons depends on the
random beats used inside the algorithm,.
In particular for
any two elements there is some probability
that they are going to be compared.
And using this toy example
shown on the slide,
I would like to just build
an intuition on how to estimate
this probability on which factors
this probability depends.
So consider this small example.
So this is an array of say it's
nine containing all the digits.
And I would like to estimate
the probability that elements 1 and
9 are going to be compared if we call
randomized quick sort physics already.
So, let's see what happens.
Assume that in the very first
quarters of partition procedure,
we select the elements 3 for example
as the pivot element, so what happens?
In this case, 1 will go to the left
of 3 and 9 will go to the right side.
To the right of three, I'm sorry.
So in this case 1 and
9 will be in different parts and
they will never be compared in
as a partician procedure just because
they are already in different parts.
Okay, for the ways it means, that we
already know that 1 is smaller than 9,
because 1 is smaller than 3,
and 3 is smaller than 9, right?
We do not need to compare them.
Well then this happens if we select as
our pivot element, any of the elements,
2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7 or 9, 8, I'm sorry.
If on the other hand we select 1 and
9 as our first pivot element,
then 1 and 9 will become pivot.
Just because, well, if we select,
for example, 9 as the pivot element,
we can pivot with all the elements
of our array, in particular with 1.
So there are two cases when 1 and
9 are compared.
And this is how exactly
the case is when either 1 or
9 are selected as a first pivot.
In all other seven cases
there are not compared.
This means that the probability that
they are compared are 2 over 9.
Okay, makes sense?
Now let's try to estimate the probability
that the elements three and
four are compared.
Well I claimed that in this case
this probability is equal to 1.
And the explanation is the following,
there is no element inside RRE
that can help the randomized
weak sort algorithm to understand that 3
is smaller than 4 without comparing them.
I mean for 1 and 9,
there are seven such elements.
All they are is elements.
I mean, if we partition with
respect to any of the elements,
we already know that 1 is smaller than
9 because they go to other parts.
Different parts with
respect to this pivot.
For three and
four there is no such element.
So algorithm just must
compare these two elements
to be sure that 3 is smaller than 4.
So in this case the probability is 1.
Well this shows that the probability
of comparing two elements
depends on how close they
are in the sorted array.
In particular if they're very far apart
of each other than the probability
is small and if they are close to each
other than the probability is high.
We will use this observation in
the formal proof of our statement.
We now start to formally
prove an upper bound
on the running time of
the randomized quicksort algorithm.
For this, we introduce
the following random variable.
Let i and
j be different indices from 1 to m.
We define Xi of ij to be equal
to 1 if two elements, A'[i] and
A'[j] are compared in the [INAUDIBLE]
quick sort algorithm and
to be equal to 0 otherwise.
Once again, to estimate the running
time of the quick sort algorithm,
we would like to estimate the total number
of comparisons made, so we would like to
estimate, for any pair of elements, what
is the probability that they are compared?
As we discussed on the previous slide,
the probability that two elements
are compared depends on how close they
are in the sorted version of our array.
For this reason, we define c of
ij dependent on the sorted array.
We do not have this sorted array, right?
We are only constructing this
in the quick sort algorithm but
we use it just for the analysis, okay?
The next thing to note is the following.
For any two elements of our initial array
assorted array doesn't matter, so for
any two elements they are either compared
just once or they are not compared at all.
So, why is that?
Why just once?
Well, if two elements
are compared at some point,
this means that at this point one of these
elements is because in the partition
procedure we can put a with all of
the elements of the current summary.
So, if two elements are compared
that one of them is a pivot.
This also means that right after
the call of this partition
procedure, we are not going
to use this pivot element.
We will put the pivot element
into its final place, and
we are not going to touch it in
any of the subsequent calls.
This immediately implies
the quadratic upper bound
on the worst case right in
time with final algorithm.
Once again we have quadratic number
of possible pairs of element, and
each pair of element is as it
compared once or not compared at all.
Right so right in time with
the worst case is quadratic.
Now comes the most important
observation of this proof.
I claim that the elements A'[i] and
A'[j] are compared if and only if
the first pivot selected in
the subrange of the solitary a prime
from either side to index j is either
a prime of a, of i, or a prime of j.
Well let's see why.
First of all, when we select it pivot
the random pivot which is not in
their sub range, and then all
the elements from this sub range in this
sort of element goes either to the left or
this to the right.
So, they all stay together in
the same branch of three, okay.
So before we select a pivot
which stays inside this range,
all these elements stay
together in the same sub-array.
Now, assume that we selected
a pivot from this sub-range, and
assume that it is not A'[i] or
A'[j], for example.
In this case a prime of A and
a prime of J will be splitted apart.
They will go into different parts
with respect to this pivot, right?
At this point I must humor that all
the elements in my summary are different,
and in duality are different, okay?
So once again,
if the first selected element
from this subrange is not prime of A or
a prime of j then these two elements
are not going to be compared.
Because right after the partition
procedure uses this pivot
from this range A prime of a and A prime
of j will go to different parts, right?
If, on the other hand, the first selected
pivot from this subrange is either
A prime of a or A prime of j,
then these two elements are going
to become paired, right?
So this is the most important
observation in this proof.
Everything else is just calculations.
So if this is clear, let's then estimate
the probability that second
respondent to elements are compared.
So we know that they're compared if and
only if the first selected Pivot in this
sub range is one of these two elements.
This helps us to estimate
the probability of
not the fact that c of
i j is equal to one.
Well this is equal to two.
I mean because we have only two choices.
I mean either a prime of a, or a prime of
j divided by the total number of choices,
I mean the total number of
elements in this subrange.
And this is j minus i plus 1.
So the probability that Z of ij is
equal to 1 equals 2 divided
by g minus i plus 1.
For example, if j and i differ by 1.
So j is equal to y plus 1.
So neighboring element in the.
Then this probability is equal
to 2 divided by 1 plus 1.
This is 2 by 2, this is 1.
[INAUDIBLE] Just reflects the fact that if
there are two neighboring elements inside.
This sorted array,
then the algorithm just must compare them,
to understand that one of them is smaller.
There is no other element that
can help our algorithm to realize
that one of these element is
smaller than the other one, okay.
This in turn helps us to estimate the
expected value of this random variable.
So recall that if we have a random
variable, which takes only values zero and
one, then its expected
value is one multiplied by
the probability that it takes
value one plus zero multiplied by the
probability that it takes the value zero.
Well zero multiplied by something is zero.
So what is left is just probability.
That it takes multiplied by one.
So the expected value of CIJ is equal
to 2 divided by g minus i plus one.
The final step in our proof
is estimating the sum
random variables to see
they all possible I and J.
So, once again the expected
value of average value
of the sum of the number of comparisons
made is the expected value of the sum
of all possible x adjacent,
or for all I Js.
So the expected value of their sum
is the sum of their expected values.
So we can write the following.
The average running time is equal
to the sum overall possible
different of the expected values cij, and
we know this expected value already.
So this is a some overall
possible different ij,
in where j is greater than i of
2 divided by g minus i plus one.
Well we can take this constant two out,
and consider all the possible.
And consider a fixed i.
For this i what we have
j ranges from i+1 to n.
So what we have for
the specified time in this sum is a subset
of the following sum,
1/2+1/3+1/4 and so on.
And this is actually a known sum.
This is called harmonic series and
it is known that it grows arithmetically.
Once again,
1 over 2 plus 1 over 3 plus, and so on,
1 over n, is theta of logarithm of n.
Well, this means that, for
each they correspond in sum, which
ranges over all j from i plus 1 through n,
grows, at most, logarithmically.
This means since we have m traces for
i from one to m that
the grows vertically as m.
Okay, and this concludes our proof.