In this last video of
the Quicksort lesson,
I would like to address
two implementation issues.
So the first issue is about space
complexity of the QuickSort algorithm.
So on one hand, when sorting
an array by a Quicksort algorithm,
we do not use any additional space.
We just partition the array and
with small elements inside the array.
On the other hand, the QuickSort
algorithm is a recursive algorithm.
And when we make a recursive call we
store some information on this tech.
Right?
So on one hand it is possible to show that
the average recurrent
depths is logarithmic.
Meaning that we need only
a logarithmic additional space.
On the other hand,
there is a very nice and
elegant trick that allows to
re-implement the QuickSort algorithm,
such that it's worst case space
complexity is at most logarithmic.
So for this, let's recall that
the QuickSort algorithm contains
of the call to the partition procedure and
then of two recursive calls.
So the situation when we have
a recursive call is and,
if the procedure is called tail recursion.
And there is a known way to
eliminate such a recursive call.
Namely, instead of making this
recursive call, let's just update.
Well, in the second recursive call,
we sort the right part of our array.
I mean,
the part from index n+1 to index r.
Instead of making this recursive call,
let's replace the with a while loop,
inside this while loop we call the
partition procedure as shown on the slide.
Then we make a recursive
call to the left part, but
instead of making the recursive call for
the right part,
we'll just update the value
of l to be equal to m+1.
And then we go to the beginning
of this while loop, and
this essentially mimics
our recursive call.
So far so good.
We've just realized that we can
eliminate the last recursive call.
At the same time let's also
realize the following thing.
In our QuickSort algorithm we first
call the partition precision,
then we make two recursive calls.
And these two recursive calls
are in a sense independent.
Well it doesn't matter which comes first,
right?
So they do not depend on each other.
This means that we can as well eliminate
a recursive call through the first part.
Well, and this in turn means that we can
always select which one to eliminate.
And for us, it is better to remove
a recursive call to a longer part.
And this is why, if we always make
a recursive call during the rate
which is shorter, then we make
which is at least twice shorter
than the initial already, right?
And this in turn means that the depths of
our recursion will be at most logarithmic.
Because well,
the first recursive call is made for
an array of size of at most n over 2,
then at most n over 4 and so on.
So the depth is logarithmic,
which is good.
And this can be implemented as follows.
So we first call the partition procedure.
It gives us a value of m.
At this point,
we know the length of two parts.
And we just compare them.
If, for example,
the lengths of the first part is shorter,
then we make a recursive
call to this part.
And instead of making the recursive
call for the second part,
we just update the value of l.
In the other case when the right part is
shorter, we make the recursive call for
this part, and instead of making
the recursive call for this part,
we'll just update the value of r.
Right?
So
overall this gives us an implementation
of the QuickSort algorithm
which uses in the worst case
an additional logarithmic space.
So the next implementation issue concerns
the random bits used by our algorithm.
So I assume that we would like to have
a deterministic version of
our randomized QuickSort.
And this is a reasonable thing to want
because in practice we would like to have
such a thing as reproducibility, which
is for example essential for debugging.
So we would like our program to always
output the same, on the same dataset.
And this is why we would probably not
like to use random numbers, okay?
Then we can do the following.
The following algorithm is
known as intro sort and
is used in many practical
implementation of QuickSort.
So instead of selecting
the pivot element randomly,
let's select it as follows using, for
example, the following simple heuristic.
Each time when we're given a summary, and
we need to partition it
with respect to some pivot.
So for this we need to select pivot,
and let's select it as follows.
We take the first element of the summary,
the last element and
the middle element, for example.
Then we have three elements,
and we sort them.
We just compare them and
we select the medium value of these.
And we use this element
as our pivot element.
So this is a very simple heuristic,
it can be implemented very efficiently.
We just need three comparisons
to select this median.
And in many cases this is enough for the
QuickSort algorithm to work effectively.
However, this is not what we want, right.
We are not happy with the statement
that this algorithm works.
Works well in many cases.
We would like our algorithm to works
well just on every possible input.
Unfortunately there are pathological cases
in which these heuristics works badly.
But we can overcome this
in the following way.
While running our QuickSort algorithm,
well let's count what is the current
depths of our recursion three.
And at some point when it exceeds some
values here again, for some constant c,
then we just stop the current algorithm
and switch to some other algorithm.
For example for the heap sort algorithm.
This is another efficient algorithm,
which is,
asymptotically as good as MergeSort I
mean, it has asymptotic again.
However Greek sort is
usually faster in practice.
So, at this point,
we switch to the quick sort algorithm.
Which means that for
these pathological bad instances,
for the QuickSort with this simple
heuristic of selecting the pivot element,
we still work in the worst
case in time n log m.
Because before we exceeded the depth
c log n, we spend time n log m.
And after this,
we'll start this algorithm.
Immediately and
we run the heap sort algorithm.
So overall, we've spent time n log n.
So this gives us an algorithm
which in many cases performs like
the QuickSort algorithm and in any case,
just in the worst case, its running
time is bounded above by n log n.
So to conclude, the QuickSort algorithm
is a comparison based algorithm
whose running time is big O of n
log n in the average case, and
big O of n squared in the worst case.
What is important in this algorithm is
that it is very efficient in practice.
It is more efficient than the north
shore algorithim for example.
For this reason it is commonly
used in practice and for
this reason it is called QuickSort