Hey everyone, you've seen how to
evaluate expressions in Python.
In this lecture we're going to show you
how to remember the results of those
expressions, so
that you can use those values later.
We're going to explore this idea by
calculating the areas of some triangles.
As a reminder, if I happen to
know the height of the triangle,
I happen to know the width of the base.
Then the area of the triangle is a length
of the base times the height divided by 2.
For example of the height is 12 and
the length of the base is 20,
then the area is 20 times 12 over 2.
Let's go explore that in Python.
You already know how to
enter that expression.
And get evaluated in Python but,
since we've decided to calculate
the values of a couple of triangles,
we're actually going to show you
how to introduce the words base and
height to represent values.
This is done with assignment statements.
Here is an example.
[SOUND] What this does
is it evaluates the 20.
It associates that value with variable X.
This is called a variable, because it's
a value that can vary as you'll see.
We'll do something similar for
a variable that we'll call height and
then these two names can be used
as if they're values were there on the,
in the Python chat.
So bases value is 20,
height is associated with the value 12.
Notice that the equal symbol has a very
different meaning in programming
than in mathematics.
Because computer programs
get rather complicated,
we're going to introduce a notation for
describing variables and their values.
What we're going to do is, draw
a variable base with the box next to it.
And what happens in Python
is 20 doesn't form that box,
instead 20 like any other value Python
lives at a particular memory address.
So I'm going to pick
an arbitrary memory address.
And I'm going to mark with an X just to
make it different from other numbers.
Let's say that memory address x3,
the value 20 appears.
The assignment statement
states that x3 and
puts it in the box associated with base.
So base contains x3 and in some sense what
that means is that points to memory
address x3 where the value 20 lives.
Similarly there is a variable height.
And Python keeps track of its
value in that little box.
And its value is a memory address.
I'm going to pick x7.
These are arbitrary,
Python is in charge of that choice, and so
I don't need to worry about exactly
what the memory address is as long as
I know that this relationship between
variables and their values exists.
Getting back to our programming problem,
we can actually use base and
height in an expression.
So if I do base times height divided by 2,
I end up with the same result as if
I had typed 20 times 12 divided by 2.
We can also assign the result of
that last expression to a variable,
we'll call it area, and
let's check it's value.
What we're going to do now is we're going
to give base and height new values.
Using assignment statements again.
So let's assign the value
of 2.5 to variable base.
What this does in my picture is
it gets me a new value 2.5, and
a particular memory address perhaps, x4
and it replaces the assignment statement
replaces this x3 with value x4.
So, the base no longer points to the 20,
instead base is associated
with the 2.5.
Similarly, I can assign the height.
What this is going to do, of course, is.
Put 7 at a particular memory address,
perhaps x1 and the assignment statement
is going to take that x1, and
it's going to put it in variable height.
Making this connection so
that height now refers to the 7.
Using Ctrl+P I am going to move back
up to my old calculation of area.
And as we're just about to
see this new area is 8.75,
which is indeed what you get if you take
2.5, multiply it by 7 and divide by 2.
Every assignment statement has the form
variable is assigned expression.
Here are the rules for
executing an assignment statement.
And you should do your
best to memorize these,
because this is going to come up over and
over in the course.
Step one, evaluate the expression
on the right hand side.
The value of the expression
has a memory address.
Store that memory address in
the variable on the left hand side.
Every programming language has a set
of rules for what a legal name is.
In Python, variable names must start with
a letter or the underscore character and
it can contain letters,
numbers and underscores.
Both uppercase and
lowercase letters are allowed, badly
formed variable names cause syntax errors.
So for example,
if we try to start a variable name
with a number, we're told we can't.
Similarly, if we include a non-alphabet,
non-underscore,
non-numeric character in the variable
name, Python will complain.
Python is also case sensitive, so
seconds_in_minute is perfectly
valid variable name.
But it's different.
From any other combination of
uppercase and lowercase characters.
The first one, seconds in minute, is of
course more readable than the second one
with those capital letters, and
choosing good names is important,
because programs can easily be used,
read, and improved on for years.
Every programming language
has a set of conventions for
how to choose a name, much like web sites
have a particular style and layout.
In Python most variable
names use only lowercase
letters with underscores to separate
words, we call this pothole case.