Hi, in this video, we will introduce
a problem about a web service, and
IP addresses of it's clients.
We will use this problem,
to illustrate different approaches
throughout the whole lesson.
Suppose you have a web service with many,
many clients,
who access your service through
the Internet from different computers.
In the Internet,
there is a system which assigns a unique
address to each computer in the network.
Just like every house in
the city has its own address.
Those addresses of computers
are called IP addresses or just IPs.
Every IP address looks like this,
four integers, separated by dots.
Every of the four integers
is from 0 to 255.
So that it can be stored
in eight bits of memory.
And the whole IP address,
can be stored in 32 bits of memory
as the standard integer type in C++ or
Java.
So there are 2 to the power
of 32 different IP addresses,
which is roughly 4 billion.
Recently, the Internet became so
big that 4 billion is no longer enough for
all of the commuters in the network.
That's why people designed the new
address system called IPv6.
And the number of addresses
there is 2 to the power of 128,
which is a number with 39 digits.
And it will be sufficient for a long time.
In this problem,
we will start talking about old system
called IPv4, which is still in use.
And which contains only 2 to the power
of 32 different IP addresses.
When somebody accesses your web service,
you know from which IP address did he or
she access it.
And you store this information in
a special file called access log.
You want to analyze all the activity, for
example, to defend yourself from attacks.
An adversary can try to kill your service
by sending lots and lots of requests from
his computer to your service, so
that it doesn't survive the lot and fails.
This is called Denial of Service attack.
And you want to be able to
quickly notice the pattern.
That there is a unusual high
number of requests from the same
IP address during some period of time for
example, the last hour.
And to do that,
you want to analyze your Access Log.
You can think of your access log as of
a simple text file with many, many lines.
And in each line, you have date and
time of the access, and
the IP address from which
the client accessed your servers.
And you want to be able to quickly
answer the queries like, did anybody
access my service from this particular
IP address during the last hour?
And how many times did
he access my service?
And how many different IPs were used to
access the service during the last hour?
To answer those questions,
we'll need to do some Log Processing.
But of course, we don't want to
process whole one hour of logs
each time we want to answer such a simple
question because one hour of logs can
easily contain dozens of thousands or
hundred of thousands or
even millions of lines depending
on the load of your web service.
Want to do that much faster.
So to do that we'll keep count.
For each IP address, we'll keep a counter
that says how many times exactly
that IP address appears in the last one
hour of the access log, or how many times
during the last hour clients accessed your
service from that particular IP address.
And we'll store it in some data
structure C, which is basically
some data structure to store the mapping
from IP addresses to counters.
We don't know yet
how to implement that data structure C.
We will discuss that further.
We will update the counter corresponding
to IP addresses every second.
For example, if now is 1 hour 45 minutes
and 13 seconds from the start of the date
and we'll ignore the date field in
the access log for the sake of simplicity.
Then we need to increment the counters
corresponding to the IP addresses in
the last two lines of the log,
because those are new lines.
We also need to remember to
decrement the counters corresponding
to the IP addresses in
the old lines of the log.
For that we'll look at the lines
exactly 1 hour ago in the log.
Because the lines which
are older than that, for
them we've already decremented
the counters in the previous seconds.
And the lines which
are more recent than that,
we still don't need to decrement the
counters because the IPs in those lines
are still in the 1 hour window
ending in the current second.
So we'll decrement the counters
corresponding to the lines which are 1
hour ago from the current moment.
Now let's look at the to pseudo code.
In the main loop we have
the following variables.
log represents the access log.
We will think of it as
an array of log lines.
Each log line has two fields.
Time and IP address.
C is some mapping from IPs to counters.
We still don't know how
to implement that but
we suppose that we have some
data structure for that.
i is an index in the log which points
to the first unprocessed log line.
So when a new second starts,
we'll need to start
incrementing counters corresponding to
lines starting from i and further in log.
j is the first or the oldest line
in the current 1 hour window.
So that when the next second starts
we'll need to decrement counters for
some of the lines starting
from line number j.
We initialize i and j with 0 and
C with an empty mapping,
because there is nothing
to store in the start.
And then each second,
we call procedure UpdateAccessList, and
we pass there the access
log to read data from.
We also pass i and j,
which we will use inside and also update.
And we pass data structure C,
which is our goal to updated.
So now let's look at the pseudo code for
update access list.
it consists of two parts.
The first part deals
with the new lines and
the second part deals with the old lines.
New lines start from line number i
which is the first unprocessed line.
Look at this line and we increase
the counter corresponding to the IP
in this line using our data structure C.
And then we go on to the next line.
We'll proceed with this while
the time written in the log line i
is still less than or equal to the time
when UpdateAccessList was launched and
then we stop processing new lines.
And we want to all blinds.
How do we determine that the line is
old enough, to decrement the counter?
We compute the time now,
which we assume is computed in seconds.
So then we need to subtract, exactly one
hour from that and that is 3600 seconds.
And if the time written
in line j is less than or
equal to that, we need to decrement
the corresponding counter.
So we'll start with line number j, which
is the first line in our 1 hour window.
We check that it is old enough
to decrement the calendar.
We decrement the calendar if that's the
case and then we move on to the next line.
In the and when we stop in this while
loop, j will point again to the first or
oldest line in the current 1 hour window.
So we've implemented the updating
procedure correctly.
Now how to answer the question
whether this particular IP was or
was not used to access our
service during the last hour.
That is really easy.
If the counter corresponding
to that IP is more than 0,
then this IP was used
during the last hour.
Otherwise the counter will be 0.
So,we've implemented all the procedures
necessary to answer the questions,
but for one small detail.
We don't know how to
implement data structure C.
And we will discuss that
in the next lectures.