Hi.
In this video we will talk
about direct addressing,
which is the first step
on the way to hashing.
Remember this computer
code from the last video.
We implemented procedure UpdateAccessList
using a data structure C,
which stores a counter for any IP address.
Now the question is, how to implement
the data structure C itself.
The idea here, is that there are 2 to
the power of 32 different IP addresses.
According to IP(v4) format.
And we can actually convert
each IP to a 32-bit integer.
And it will be a one to one
correspondence between old possible IPs.
And all numbers between zero and
two to the power 32 minus one.
Thus, we can create an array A,
of size exactly two to the power of 32,
with indexes zero to two to
the power of 32 minus one.
And then for each IP,
there will be exactly one position in
this array, correspondent to this IP.
And then, we will be able to use
the corresponding answer in array A.
Instead of the counter for this IP.
Now, how do we actually convert
IP addresses to integers?
If you look at this picture,
you will see that any IP address
actually consists of 4 integer numbers.
Which are all, at most, 255.
And each of them corresponds to 8 bits,
or 1 byte
in the total 4-byte or
32-bit integer number.
Basically, if you just coordinate
all the 8 bytes corresponding
to first number with 8 bytes.
Corresponding to the second number and to
the third number and to the fourth number.
You will get 32 bytes.
And if you then convert this string
of 32 bytes into the decimal form.
You will get an integer number in
the form which we are used to.
For example, if you take a very
simple IP address, 0.0.0.1.
It will convert to integer 1,
because all the higher bits are zeroes and
in the lowest byte.
The only bit set is the lowest bit and
that corresponds to number 1.
If we convert the number in the picture,
to the decimal form,
we will get 2886794753.
Now, what do you think will be the integer
number corresponding to this IP?
And the correct answer is 1168893508.
Now, here is the formula and
the code to convert an IP
address to an integer number.
Why is that?
Well, the lowest eight bits are in
the fourth number of the IP address.
So we use them without changing.
The next Eight bits,
are in the third number of IP.
But to use them,
we need to move them to the left by
eight positions in the binary form.
And to do that, we need to multiply
the corresponding integer number by two to
the power of eight.
The next eight bits are in
the second number of the IP.
And to use them we need to move
them to the left by 16 positions
in the binary form.
To do that, we multiply the corresponding
integer number by two to the power of 16,
and so on.
This gives us a one to one correspondence
between IP address and integer number.
Now, we can rewrite the code for
UpdateAccessList using array A,
instead of mysterious data structure C.
And the only thing that changes
is the incrementing and
decrementing the counters.
So when we need to increment a counter
corresponding to the IP in the ith line.
We first convert this IP to integer number
from 0 to 2 to the power of 32 minus 1.
And then we increase the entry of
the integer RA A, add this index.
Note, that each IP is converted
to its own integer number.
So, there will be no collisions
between different IP numbers.
When we try to increment a counter for
one IP number and
by chance increment the current
correspondent to another IP address.
All IP addresses are uniquely mapped
into integers from zero to two
to the power of 32 minus one.
We do the same thing when we
need to decrement the counter.
So basically, in the position in array
A corresponding to any IP address,
we will store the counter.
Which measures how many times
this particular IP was accessed
during the last hour.
Now, how to answer the question,
whether this IP was or
was not used during the last hour,
to access your services.
This is very easy.
We first convert the IP to
the corresponding position in the area A,
and then we look at
the counter this position.
If the IP was used,
then the counter will be more than zero.
Otherwise it will be exactly zero.
So, now lets look at the asyptotics
of this implementation.
UpdateAccessList is as fast as we can do.
It is constant time per log line.
Because for each log line,
we only look at some position
in the array and increment it.
And also increment some counter,
or decrement some counter.
AccessedLastHour is also constant time.
Because the only thing we do is,
we look at some position in their rate.
Which is a constant time impression and
compare it with a zero, but
there is a drawback.
Even if during the last hour,
for example, in the night,
there are only five, or 10, or 100 IPs.
From which your clients use the service.
You will still need 2 to the power of 32
memory cells, to store that information.
And in general, if you have for
example, new IP protocol.
IPv6, it already contains 2 to the power
of 128 different IP addresses.
And if you create an array of that size,
it won't fit in memory in your computer.
In the general case, we need O(N) memory,
where N is the size of our universe.
Universe is the set of all objects,
that we might possibly want to
store in our data structure.
It doesn't mean that every one of them
will be stored in our data structure.
But if we at least at some point might
want to store it, we have to count it.
So for example, if some of the IP
addresses never access your service.
You will still have to have
a cell in your array for
this particular IP,
in the direct addressing method.
So, this method only works when
the universe is somewhat small.
And we need to invent something else
to work with the universes which
are bigger than that or even infinite.
Such as, for example,
the universe of all possible words,
all possible strings, or
all possible files on your computer.
And we will talk in
the next videos about that.