Hi, in this video we will study another
approach to the IP addresses problem.
In the last video we understood that
the direct addressing scheme sometimes
requires too much memory.
And why is that?
Because it tries to store something for
each possible IP address while we're only
interested in the active IP addresses.
Those from which at least some user has
accessed our service during the last hour.
So the first idea for
improvement of the memory consumption
is let's just store the active IP's and
nothing else.
Another idea is that if our error based
approach from the last video has failed,
then lets try to use
list instead of an error.
So let's store all the IP addresses
which are active in a list.
Sorted by the time of access.
So that the first element in the list
corresponds to the oldest access time
during the last hour, and the last element
in the list corresponds to the latest,
newest access from some IP
address to our service.
Let's jump from here right into the pseudo
code, because it's pretty simple.
We're going to have our procedure
update access list which takes in
the log file log.
It also takes in i which
is the index of the first
log line which hasn't been processed yet.
And also it has input L
which is the list and
instead of some abstract data structure
see from the first videos and
instead of the area a from
the direct addressing scheme.
We put parameter L which is
a list into this procedure and
this is the list with active IP addresses.
So our code have to pass first deals with
new lines and second deals with old lines.
We just go searching from
the first unprocessed line.
And if we need to added to our
list because it was processed
during the last hour,
we just append it to the end of the list.
And now again, the last element of
the list corresponds to the latest,
newest access from some IP address.
And note that in our list we will
start not just the IP address but,
both IP address and the time of the axis.
And then we will go to the next element
in the log file and go and go while we
still have some log lines which we
need to add to the end of our list.
And then the second part we just look at
the oldest event during the last hour,
which is corresponding to
the first element of the list.
And if that is actually before
the start of the last hour,
then we need to remove it from the list.
And so we just do L.Pop.
And we do that while the head
of the list is still too old.
And when we stop, it means that all
the elements in the list are actually
with time during the last hour.
Why is that?
Because the list is always kept in
the order by increasing time of access.
When we add new log lines to the list.
We add only those which have time even
more than last element of the list
currently, and
we remove something from the list.
We remove the oldest entries.
So, all the entries are always sorted,
and as soon as we removed everything from
the start which is too old, all
the entries in the list are not too old.
They are made during the last hour.
So this is pretty simple and now we need
to answer questions like, whether my IP
address was used during the last hour to
access the service and how many times.
To answer the first one we just need to
find out whether there is an element
in our list with the given IP address.
And that is done by find by ID,
which is different from the standards
find procedure of the least by the fact
that we search not by the whole object,
which is a log line,
which contains both IP address and time.
But we search just by the first field,
by the IP address.
So our list contains
tuples of IP addresses and
times of access, and
we only look by IP address.
But the implementation will be the same.
We'll just go from the head of
the list to the end of the list, and
compare the IP field of the log lines
with the IP address given as the input.
And if it coincides we
will return this element,
otherwise we'll return that there is
nothing with this IP address in the list.
And the reason we return
some special [INAUDIBLE].
So then, in the AccessedLastHour,
just compare the results with null.
If it's not null then this IP address
is in the list, otherwise it's not.
And to count the number of times
our service was accessed from
a particular IP address, we just need to
count the number of log lines in
the list which have the same IP address.
And that can be done by procedure
CountIP of the list which
again differs from the standard count
procedure in the list by the fact that it
counts by the first field, not by
the whole object which is a log line.
But it just goes from
to the end of the list.
Compares the IP field with
the given IP and if they coincide,
it increases the counter by 1.
And returns the counter in the end.
So this is all the implementation.
Now let's analyze it.
Let N be the number of
currently active IPs,
then the memory consumption
is bigger of N.
Because we only store the active IP
addresses and the corresponding times
of X's, but the times of X's on the add
constant memory per active IPs.
So it's all null linear in the number
of active IPs which is much better than
the direct addressing scheme because
it require an amount of memory
proportionally to the number
of all possible IP addresses.
And here will only require amount
memory proportional to the number of
currently active IP addresses.
What about running time?
We know the standards list
procedures such as Append, Top and
Pop all working constant time and
that's why the UpdateAccessList
works in constant time per log line.
Of course, any particular call to
UpdateAccessList could take more than
constant number of operations if we
need to add more new lines to the end of
the list or remove many many old
lines from the start of the list.
But for each log line we will
only append it at most once and
we will only removed from
the beginning at most once.
So it's constant time per log line
plus constant time per each call of
UpdateAccessList just to check whether
we need to append something and
whether we need to remove
something from the beginning.
But this amount of operations
can be controlled by how
often do we actually
call Update Access List.
What about answering the questions?
We know that Find By IP and
Count IP have to go through the whole list
in the worst case and actually count.
IP has to go through the whole list
all the time to find out how many
log lines have the same IP as the given
one and so AccessLastHour and
AccessCountLastHour are both linear
in the number of active IPs.
And that is actually now good
because even without introducing
any additional data structures,
we could just take the log file,
take the last line in it before
the current time, and go back from it.
And just look through each log line and
compare its IP address with
the IP address in the question.
And count how many times it
occurs during the last hour and
just stop as soon as we go through
the border of the last hour.
And that will take the same time
without any additional data structure.
So this solution is not more
clever than the trio approach.
So, we failed somewhat with
direct addressing scheme and
we failed with this list based approach.
It is overall a failure?
Well no, in the next videos we'll
combine the ideas from direct
addressing scheme with
the list based approach.
And we'll come up with solution which is
both good in terms of memory consumption
and is much faster than the trivial
approach in terms of the running time.