Hi, in this video, we will finally
start talking about hash tables.
We will define what a hash table is and
what we can do with it.
In the last video,
we've introduced the notion of map, and
now we'll introduce a very similar and
natural notion of a set.
By definition, a set is a data structure
which has at least three methods,
to add an object to the set,
to remove an object from the set, and
to find out whether a given object
is already in the set or not.
One of the examples we already know very
well, set of all IPs through which clients
access to your service
during the last hour.
This is an example with which we've
worked for the last few videos.
Another example would be to store the set
of all students currently on campus.
And another one is to store all the key
words of a given programming language so
that we can quickly highlight them in
the text editor, which you used to code.
There are two ways to implement a set.
One of them is when you already
have an implementation of a map,
you can base your implementation
of set on the map.
Basically, you can set a map from all
the objects S that you need to store
in the set to the set of values, V, which
only contains two values, true and false.
If the object is in the set,
then the corresponding value
to this object will be true.
If the object is not in the set,
it is either not in the map or
the corresponding value to
it in the map is false.
But that is not a very efficient
way because we will have to
store twice as much objects and
values as we need.
And also,
when we remove objects from the set,
it will be hard to remove
them from the map.
We will probably have to store them with
value false, so there's a better way.
We can again use chaining.
But instead of storing
pairs of objects and
corresponding values in the chains,
we'll just store objects themselves.
Let's see how can we
implement that into the code.
Again, we'll have a hash
function from all the objects S
to the set of integer
numbers from 0 to m-1.
We denote it by O and
O' objects from the set S, and
we initialize array A with an array of
size m which consists of lists or chains.
And each chain consists of object O.
Initially all the chains are empty.
When we need to find an object inside
a set, we first compute the hash value
of our object, we look at
the corresponding cell in the array A.
We take the list of objects from there,
and then we go through the whole list and
try to find object O there.
If we find it, return true.
Otherwise, return false because our
object O can be only in the list
corresponding to the cell in the array A,
number h(O).
To implement add, we again compute
value of hash function on object O,
we take the list
corresponding to this cell.
And we go through this list,
if we find our object O on this list,
then we don't need to do anything because
our object O is already in the set.
Otherwise, we append our object to the
list corresponding to cell number h(O).
To remove object from the set,
we first try to find it in the set.
If it's not in the set,
initially we don't need to do anything.
Otherwise, we again compute
the hash value of our object,
take the corresponding list, and
erase our object from that list.
So, now we are ready to
say what is a hash table?
A hash table is any
implementation of a set or
a map which is using hashing,
hash functions.
It can even not use chaining.
There are different ways to use
hash functions to store a set or
a map in memory.
But chaining is one of the most frequently
used methods to implement a hash table.
We have a few examples of hash
tables already implemented and
built in our standard library types and
programming languages, for example.
Set is implemented as unordered_set in
C++, as HashSet in Java, as set in Python.
And map is implemented as unordered_map
in C++, as HashMap in Java,
and as dict, or dictionary in Python.
Why those types are called
unordered in C++?
You will learn in one of the next
modules about data structures.
For now, you just know that hash
tables were already implemented in
the main languages we used for
the specialization.
In conclusion,
we've learned what is chaining.
We've learned what is a hash table.
And now we know that chaining is
a technique that can be used to implement
a hash table.
We know that the memory consumptions for
the chaining technique is big O(n + m)
where n is the number of objects
currently stored in the hash table.
And m is the cardinality
of the hash function.
We also know that the operations with such
a hash table implemented using chaining
work in time c+1, where c is
the length of the longest chain.
Now the question is,
how to make both m and c small?
Why do we need that?
Because we want both small memory
consumption and fast operations.
For example, if m is very big,
then we can use direct addressing,
or something like that.
But for some universes,
some sets of objects,
we will use too much memory, or
we will have just too much overhead
on top of our O of n memory which is
needed to store n objects, anyway.
If n is small, but c is big,
well that's one different match
from the list based approach where
we used only O of n memory to store
the list, to store only the active IPs.
But then we have to spend O of
n time to actually look through
all the list every time
we want to make a query.
So we want both m being
relatively small and c.
How can we do that?
Well, we can do that based on a clever
selection of a hash function, and
we will discuss this topic
in the next lessons.