In this video, we'll look at a proof
of how the Master Theorem works.
So a reminder, the Master Theorem
states that if T(n) equals a T of
ceiling of n over b plus a polynomial,
then we have these three cases.
So let's do as we normally do
with a recurrence relation and
let's create a recurrence tree.
So we'll have our recurrence at the top
to just remind ourselves what that is.
Let's assume for the sake of
argument that n is a power of b.
That's a reasonable assumption since we
can always just pad n to be larger, right,
if we increase it by no more than b we can
get to the next closest power of b and
then this will be a simpler analysis.
So we have our problem n.
At the next level,
we break the problem down into
a copies of a problem n over b large.
So level zero.
We have a problem of size n.
Level 1 we have problems of size n/b.
At the general level i we have
problems of size n over b to the i.
At the bottom level, which is level log
base b of n, we have problems of size 1.
How many problems are there?
At level 0 there's of course one problem.
At level 1, a problems.
And in general at the ith level,
a to the i problems.
At the log base b of n level,
it's a to the log base b of n.
How much work do we have to do?
Well work is just a function of
how many problems we have and
the amount of work for each problem.
So at level zero we have just
O(n to the d) work.
There's one problem and
it takes O(n to the d) time.
And level one we have a problems.
And each of them takes
O(n over b to the d) work.
Okay, we can pull out the a and
the b and the d to be all together, and
that's just O(n to the d)
times a over b to the d.
At the ith level we have
a to the i problems and
each one is
O(n over b to the i to the d).
Again, we can pull out the a to the i,
the b to the i, and
we're left with O(n to the d)
times a over b to the d to the i.
And finally, at the bottom level it's
just a to the log base b of n because
the problems are all size 1.
It's just
O(n to the log base b of a).
So the total amount of work is the
summation from 0 to the log base b of n.
O(n to the d) times the quantity
a over b to the d, all that to the i.
So let's look at what seems like a slight
digression, and that is geometric series.
So a Geometric Series is
a series of numbers that
progresses by some multiplicative factor.
I'll give you an example.
If we take 1 + 2 + 4 + 8 + 16 + 32 + 64,
that's a geometric series
where our factor is
a factor of 2 at each time.
Just as well, we could have
a geometric series that goes down.
So we could have, for
instance, let's say 10,000,
1,000, 100, 10, 1.
Where we're going down by a constant
factor of ten at each increment.
Now it turns out, our multiplicative
factor, let's call that r,
as long as r is not equal to one we
have a simple closed form for this.
This is just a times
(1-r) to the n over 1 minus r.
And it turns out that big O notation,
what happens is
we care about the largest term.
So our sum is going to be bounded by
a constant times our largest term.
So, if r is less than 1 then our
largest term is the first element a and
therefore our solution is O(a).
Okay, because it's our largest term,
it gets smaller,
smaller, smaller, smaller, smaller.
And as long as it's by this
multiplicative factor,
then all that really
matters is this first term,
because the rest of it sums to no more
than a constant times that first term.
If on the other hand, r is greater than 1,
then what matters is the very last term,
because that's the biggest term and all
the previous ones are smaller and smaller.
So it's smallest, larger,
larger, larger, largest.
And so
that largest term is a r to the (n-1).
So in a geometric series we care
about either the first term or
the last term, whichever one is bigger.
Now if we take that back to
the case of our recurrence tree,
we notice our summation here.
This is the same summation we had from our
recurrence tree and we see that we have
a geometric series.
a is taking the place of
big O then to the d and
r is taking the place
of a over b to the d.
So our multiplicative factor
is a over b to the d.
And there are three cases.
You remember as we stated
the solution to the Master Theorem.
Case one is d is greater
than log base b of a.
Well it's equivalent to saying
a over b to the d is less than 1.
So now we have our multiplicative
term is less than 1.
So it's getting smaller and
smaller and smaller.
That means that the largest
term is the first term.
And that's the one that
we have an order of.
So this is big O of,
officially big O of big O of n to the d,
which is just the same
as big O of n to the d.
Case 2, where d equals log base b of a and
equivalently,
a over b to the d is equal 1.
Well, if a over b to the d is equal
to one, remember our geometric
series formula didn't hold, so we're
going to just have to calculate this.
But if a over b to the d is 1, then
a over b to the d to any power is still 1.
So that means, that our summation
is just a summation from i equals 0 to
log base b of n of O(n to the d).
And that's just 1 plus log base b of n,
because that's the number of terms in
our summation times O(n to the d).
Well the 1 is a low order term we don't
care about, and log base b of n can
just be treated as log n, because a base
change is just some multiplicative factor,
and that disappears in our big O notation.
So we end up with, as we see in the
theorem, O(n to the d times log n).
And then our final case,
is d is less than log base b of a,
which is equivalent to saying
a over b to the d is greater than 1.
So here, our multiplicative
factor is greater than 1.
So our smallest term is the first term and
our largest term is the last term.
So in this case, this is big O of our
last term is O(n to the d) times
a over b to the d to the log b of n.
So, i is log base b of n.
This is a bit of a mess.
Let's see whether we can
fix this a little bit.
So let's go ahead and apply the log base b
of n power separately to a and b to the d.
So we have, in the numerator,
a to the log base b of n.
And then the denominator,
b to the d times log base b of n.
Well, b to the log base b of n is just n.
So, that's going to disappear down
to n to the d in the denominator.
In the numerator,
a to the log base b of n,
by logarithmic identity is equal
to n to the log base b of a.
So we can swap those other two.
And now, if we compare big O
of n to the d and n to the d,
we know big O of n to the d is bounded
by some constant, k times n to the d.
So we have k n to the d divided by
n to the d, which is just some k.
And that constant can go away because
we're still talking about big O notation.
So we're left just with big O
of n to the log base b of a,
which is what we have for the final case.
So the Master theorem is a shortcut.
Our master theorem again
as a restatement is here.
I have a secret to tell you, however.
I do not remember the master theorem and
I don't actually even look
up the master theorem.
Here's what I do.
When I have a recurrence of this rough
form, I look at the amount of work
done at the first level and at the second
level (which is a very easy calculation) and
then I just say to myself Is
that the same amount of work?
If it's the same amount of work it's
going to be the same amount of work
all the way down and so
we're going to be in case two.
So it's going to be the amount
of work at the first level,
which we known is O(n to the d),
times log n because there are that many levels.
On the other hand, if the first
term is larger than the second term
I know the first term is going
to dwarf all the other terms.
And so, we're left with just
O(n to the d).
And finally, if the first term
is less than the second term,
I know they're going to keep increasing
and it's the bottom term that I need.
And that is just going to be the number of
leaves which is n to the log base b of a.
The master theorem is really handy to use
whether you memorize it or you have it
written down and use it or in my case you sort
of recreate it every time you need it.
Thanks.