Hi.
In this lesson you will learn how to
implement the Greedy Algorithm for
the Fractional Knapsack.
How to estimate its running time and
how to improve its asymptotics.
Here is the description of the greedy
algorithm from the previous lesson.
While knapsack is still not full,
we select the best item left.
The one with the highest
value per unit of weight.
And either fit all of this
item in the knapsack or
if there is only few space left in
the knapsack, cut this item and
fit as much as you can in what's
left in the knapsack, and
then repeat this process
until the knapsack is full.
In the end return the total value of
the items taken and the amounts taken.
We've proven that the selection
of best item is a safe move.
Then after we've selected the best item
what we've got left is a knapsack with
a capacity which is less, but the problem
is the same: you have some items and
you have a knapsack of some capacity and
you should fill it optimally so
as to maximize the total
value of the items that fit.
So this greedy algorithm really works.
Now let's implement it.
Here we have a procedure called Knapsack.
It starts with filling the array A with
amounts of items taken with 0 and
the total value we also
initialize to 0 and then,
as we said on the slide, we repeat for
n times the following iterations.
If the knapsack is already
full than in the variable W,
we will have 0 because in the start
we have in the variable W the total
capacity of the knapsack, but each time we
will put something in the knapsack, we will
update W will decrease it by the amount
of weight that we put already in.
And so in the end,
when the knapsack is full, W will be 0.
If W became 0, it means that we should
just return the total value and
the amounts of the items that we took.
Otherwise we should select the best item.
The best item is the item which is
still left so, wi is more than 0 and
out of such items, it's the item
with the maximum value per weight,
so the one which maximizes vi over wi.
When we've selected the i, we determine
the amount which will it take,
it is either the whole wi, the whole of
this item if it fits in the knapsack.
Otherwise, if the capacity of
the knapsack is already less,
then we just fill it up to the end.
So A is minimum of wi and big W.
After we select the amount,
we just update all the variables.
So we update wi by decreasing it by a,
because we took already a of this item.
We're also increased the amount
A of i corresponding to the item
number i by the value A.
And we'll also decrease the capacity left,
because we just decrease it by A.
By putting it A of item i.
Also we increase value V by this formula:
a multiplied by vi and divided by wi.
Why is that?
Because we took A of item number i,
we took A units and
one unit brings us amount of
value equal to vi over wi.
So if you take A units,
the total value by these items,
a multiplied by vi and divided by wi.
After we do n iterations, or maybe less,
if the knapsack is full before
we do all n iterations, we'll return the
total value and the amounts in the array.
Now the running time of this
algorithm is Big-O of n squared.
Why is that?
Well, first we have the inner selection
of best item, which works in linear time.
Because basically, we have to go through
all the items to select the best one.
And we have the main loop, for loop, which
is executed n times at most, maybe less.
So in each iteration we do some
linear time computation and
we do this at most n times.
That means that the total running
time is Big-O of n squared.
Now we can't improve on that because if
we sort the items by decreasing value of
vi over wi, then it will be easier to
select the best item which is still left.
Let's look at this pseudo code.
Let's assume that we've already
sorted the input items,
size that v1 over w1 is, more than or
equal to v2 over w2 and that is greater,
or equal to the fraction for
the next item and up to vn over wn.
And we can start with
the same array of amounts and
the same total value filled with zeroes.
But then we make a for loop for
i going from 1 to n.
And on each iteration i will be
the best unit which is still left.
So on the start of the iteration we check
whether we still have some capacity
in the knapsack.
If it is already filled we
just return the answer.
Otherwise we know that i is the best item
because we didn't consider it previously
and it is the item with the maximum
value per unit out of those
which we didn't consider before.
So we determine the amount of this
item with the same formula and
we update the weights,
the amounts, the capacity, and
the total value in the same way as
we did in the previous pseudocode.
The only change is that we change
the order in which we consider the items.
And this allows us to make each iteration
in constant time instead of linear time.
So, this new algorithm now works in linear
time, because it has at most n iterations,
and each iteration works at
most in constant time.
So, if we apply first
some sorting algorithm
to sort items by decreasing
value of vi over wi.
And then apply this new
knapsack procedure.
Total run time will be n log n,
because sorting will work in n log n.
And the knapsack itself
will work in linear time.