The programs that we've written so far
execute the same sequence of instructions
each time that they're run.
In this lecture, we're going to use
bullion expressions to control which
instructions get executed.
Let's consider this problem.
A flight was scheduled to arrive at a
particular time, and it is now estimated
to arrive at another time.
Write a function, given the two times,
returns a flight status, either on time,
early, or delayed.
For this function, a time will be
represented using a float.
For example, the time three AM will be
represented by 3.0 and the time two:3030
PM fourteen:30, will be represented by
14.5.
Therefore, each of the times we're working
with is going to be between 0.0 and 24.
0.0 inclusive and 24 exclusive.
This is called a precondition.
When writing our function we expect that
the times provided will be within this
range.
Let's begin to define the function, we'll
start with some example function calls.
I'm going to name this function report
status.
And it will have two arguments, take two
arguments.
The first will be the scheduled time of
arrival, and the second will be the new
estimated time of arrival.
When those two values are the same, it
will return the message on time.
When the scheduled time is 12.5 and the
new estimated time of arrival is 11.5 or
earlier, this function will return early.
.
And, finally for the last possible
situation, is that when the time is 9.0,
the scheduled time and then you estimated
time comes later, this function should
return a message saying that the flight is
delayed.
Now let's write the type header.
The function has two parameters both
numbers and in all the cases here, I've
passed in floats.
But we could have easily passed in integer
values.
So we can use number for those two
parameters and it is going to return
something of type string.
Time for the header.
We know that we've named the function
Report Status and now we need to decide on
two good names for the parameters.
The first parameter, I can call scheduled
time.
The second, I will call estimated time.
The last part is a doc string that needs
to be added is the functions description.
This function will return a flight status,
and that will be one of three strings. On
time, early or delayed.
It's returning that status for a flight
that was scheduled to arrive, at scheduled
time, the first parameter.
But is now estimated to arrive at
estimated time, which is the second
parameter.
One additional piece of information that
needs to be added to this doc string is
that the precondition that the schedule
time be between 0.0 and 24.
The same is true of the estimated time.
It also needs to fall within that range.
.
It's now time to write the body of the
function.
We're going to write this function body in
a couple of different steps.
And by the end, we'll have the entire
thing working.
To start with, we need to figure out how
to execute some statements sometimes, but
not on others.
For example, we want to return a string on
time.
But we don't want to return that string
every time this, this function executes.
Only at the times when scheduled time is
equal to estimated time.
We are going to use an if statement to
express this.
This if statement will have a boolean
condition which is that the scheduled time
be equal to the estimated time.
And we are going to place this return
statement within the body of the if.
So notice that it is indented, indicating
that, that falls within the if statement.
The way that we read this code is that if
this scheduled time is equal to the
estimated time, if that boolean expression
is true, then the return on time statement
is executed.
Otherwise, it is not executed, and we
would continue down on, with any code that
follows this if.
Let's save this and run it.
So when I call this function, in the
shell, with equal times it reports the
status on time.
If I were to call this function at the
moment with one of the time, pairs of
times that are not equal, then nothing is
returned.
To be more precise, I should actually say
that it looks like nothing is returned.
Because something is returned by this
function, even though no return statement
was executed.
Let's print this function call.
So the function is called, whatever value
is returned is returned.
And that value is about to be printed.
And we can see that none is printed.
When a function call executes and no
return statement is executed, the value
none is returned by the function.
The type of none is none-type, not string.
So that breaks the type contract that we
specified for our report status function
We need to complete the rest of the
function ensuring that, that type contract
is abided by.
Let's go back to defining the function.
Right now, we have a single if statement
and when this boolean condition is true,
on time is returned.
When it's false we want to do something
else.
So we check to see if this is true, and
then we're going to use L, standing for
else, L if, to check for a second
condition.
This time we're going to check to see
whether the scheduled time is bigger or
greater than estimated time.
And when it is, we will return early.
.
And it's to be spelled as scheduled.
So at this stage let's run it.
And when we call this function with equal
times it says on time.
When we, when we call it with earlier
times, it reports early.
But still, at this point when we call this
with later time.
None is returned.
So we're not quite done yet.
We're going to add a third part to the if
statement, which is an else clause.
Else says, if none of the preceding
conditions or expressions are true, then
do this.
So we've checked whether they're equal,
greater than, and the only thing left is
that scheduled time is less than estimated
time.
In that situation, this function will
return delayed.
So we can run it again, checking all of
our conditions, when they're equal.
When it's earlier, and when the estimated
time is later.
We now have the appropriate reports.
I want to mention a few general features
of if statements.
We can have zero or more L if clauses
associated with an if And we can have zero
or one else clauses, and the else has to
be the last clause for the if statement.
When we have an if statement with these
various expressions, we evaluate each
expression in order.
And for the first one that evaluates to
true, the body of that, that part in the
if statement is executed.
After that body is executed, the if
statement is terminated.
So it exits and continues on to the code
that comes below it, without checking any
further conditions.