Hi.
In this video, we will implement
the Breadth-first Search algorithm from
the previous video and
analyze it's running time.
Let's look at this pseudocode.
The procedure of BFS is called
after Breadth-first Search and
it takes graph G and
origin node S as input parameters.
It also uses array dist to
store the distances from
the original node S to
all nodes in the graph.
It can be not an array,
it can be a map from nodes to distances,
depending on what are your nodes.
If your nodes are numbered from 0 to
n minus 1, then it will probably be
convenient to use an array of size n
to store distances for those nodes.
But if your nodes are labeled with
some strings or some other objects,
then it maybe wise to use a map
from nodes to distances and
call this data structure dist.
Anyway, we'll use this dist data
structure to store our estimations
of distances from origin to
all the nodes in the graph.
And we initialize all these distances with
infinity, with the exception of the node
as itself, which gets an estimation
of 0 from the beginning.
And we will also use another data
structure Q, which is a queue,
the data structure which works in
the principle of first in, first out.
So the first element that
goes into the queue is the first
element that goes out of the queue.
And we initialize this Q with just
one element, the origin node S.
And this symbolizes that we already
discovered node S and put it in the queue.
So all the discovered nodes
are those which are in the queue.
All of the nodes which
haven't been in the queue yet
are white nodes which
are not discovered yet.
And the black nodes, in the terms
of the example I showed you before,
are those nodes which are already
out from the queue and
are being processed or
have been processed before.
And we will take nodes from Q one by one,
process them,
discover new nodes and put new
discovered nodes back into the queue.
So we'll start with Q initialized
with only starting node S.
And while this Q is not empty,
we take the first element
from it using method dequeue.
So we get it to variable u.
So, this is the first node in the queue,
and we start processing it.
And to start processing it,
we triggers all the edges outgoing
from this node u in the graph.
So we have a for loop for all edges (u,v)
in the set of edges of the graph and
this means that we traverse all the edges
which have starting nodes u and
some other node as it's end.
And we'll look at node v and
now we need to determine whether
this node is already discovered and
maybe already processed or not.
And to determine that,
we'll use our dist values.
So if dist value of the node is infinity,
then it means that this node
hasn't been discovered yet,
because as soon as it will be discovered,
we will change the estimation of the
distance to it and it will becomes finite.
While it is still infinite, it means
that the node hasn't been discovered.
And vice versa, if dist Is finite,
then we have discovered this node already.
So if this node was discovered previously,
then we don't need to do anything with it.
This is a red edge.
And we don't do anything
with a red edge from
our currently processing node to
the node which was discovered earlier.
But if the edge is to a white node
which was not discussed previously,
we need to process this edge.
And by processing it we first
discover the end of this edge v and
we do that by calling enqueue, so
adding these v to the end of the queue.
And we'll also change the estimate
of the distance to this node v and
we set it to distance to
the current node plus one.
Because we know that when we process
a node from somewhere, some of the edges
are red because they go to the same
layer of or one of the previous layers.
But the edges that go to the undiscovered
nodes go to the next layer.
So the distance to v is equal
to distance to u plus 1.
And we repeat and repeat this process
while our queue is not empty.
And we need to make a few notes.
First, this infinity thing.
Of course, in a real programming language,
there won't be any infinity,
so you will have to use
something special for that.
One variant is to estimate what
is the maximum possible distance
from origin node to any nodes
in the graph, and just use
a constant value or some computable value
which is definitely bigger than that.
For example, distance from origin
cannot be bigger than the number of
nodes in the graph,
because every path without
cycles inside it will have, at most,
a number of nodes minus 1 edges.
Or you can just say that it is not bigger
than the number of edges in the graph.
Because you won't use the same edge twice
in the shortest path from origin node
to your node.
So anyway,
[COUGH] you can assign infinity to
number of nodes plus 1 or number of
edges plus 1 or some other big value.
And another thing you can do is you just,
instead of using integer numbers for
storing distances, you create a special
structure which has two fields.
One of them is distance if is determined.
And another field is just a boolean field,
which tells you whether the distance
is defined or it is still not defined,
and then this means infinity.
And another note is that why
this algorithm even stops.
And the key observation is that we
only put a node into the queue once,
because as soon as we put this
node in the queue, we enqueue it,
we also change the estimation of distance
to this node and it becomes finite.
And so one, we will try to pull it in
the queue next time, we will compare
the distance to it with infinity and
it won't be equal to infinity.
So we won't put node into the queue again.
And it means that we put at most number of
nodes in the graph, elements in the queue.
And on each step of the while loop,
we take some node out of this queue,
so its size decreases.
So it can increase at most number
of nodes in the graph times and
it decreases in each steps.
So, this means that these others
definitely stops and it definitely stops
after at most number of nodes in the graph
steps of the external while loop.
Now let's estimate the running time
of this algorithm more precisely.
I state that the running time of
breadth-first search is proportional to
the number of edges plus
number of nodes in the graph.
Why is that?
First we've already discovered that
each vertex, each node of the graph,
is enqueued at most once.
So the number of iterations
of the external while loop
is at most number of nodes of the graph.
Another observation is that each
edge is examined either once for
directed graphs, or
twice for undirected graphs.
Why is that?
Well, the edge is examined when
one of its ends is processed.
The node, which is one of its ends,
is processed.
And if the graph is directed,
then the edge is actually examined
only if it's start is processed.
And if the graph is undirected,
then for each of its nodes,
the edge is examined when
this end is processed.
Of course, this edge will work and
discover a new node at most once out
of those two times it is examined.
But still it will be examined
twice from both ends.
And of course, if the edge is not
connected to the original node,
it won't be examined at all.
But we say that each edge in any case
will be processed at most twice.
And what it means is that the total
number of iterations of the internal for
loop is, at most,
number of edges of the graph.
And so adding those up and
adding the constant number of
operations in the start and adding the
initialization of the dist values which
goes in time proportional to the number
of nodes of the graph, in total,
we got number of edges plus
number of nodes in the graph.
And in the next video we will prove that
breadth-first search actually returns
correct distances to all
the nodes from the origin node.