Now the main result is that one node u is
discovered during breadth-first search.
The dist value, the estimate of
distance to this node from origin,
is assigned exactly the correct
distance from node S to node u.
Let's prove this.
To prove it, we'll use mathematical
induction, and as a base case,
we see that one node S is discovered.
This is the first node to be discovered.
The dist value is assigned to 0, and
this is actually the correct
distance from S to itself.
So we'll use induction on
the distance to the node.
So, the inductive step is that
suppose we proved our statement about
correct distances for all nodes, which
are distance at most k from the origin.
And now we'll prove it for
nodes at distance exactly k + 1.
If we do that,
we'll prove the lemma itself.
So now, taken out v at distance
k + 1 from the origin,
we know that for
all nodes which are closer,
the correct distances are found
during breadth-first search.
Now let's prove it for
this particular node v.
So we know that v was discovered,
because it is reachable.
And we proved that all reachable
nodes were discovered during
breadth-first research.
So it was discovered while
processing some other node u.
Now let's estimate the distance to u.
From one point of view, we know that the
distance from S to v is at most distance
from S to u plus 1, plus this edge from
u to v through which v was discovered.
And we know the distance from
S to v is exactly k + 1,
and that means the distance
from S to u is at least k.
From the other hand, we know that v is
discovered only after u is dequeued.
And using the order lemma, we can state
that the distance to u is strictly less
than distance to v, because otherwise v
would be discovered before u is dequeued.
And so distance from S to u
is strictly less than k + 1.
And we already know this at least k.
And we also know this
distance is integer number.
And so the only option is that
distance from S to u is exactly k.
And then see what happens when
we assign this value for v.
We assign it to this value of u + 1,
which is k + 1.
Which is the same as
the distance from original to v.
So we proved our lemma by induction that
when the node is discovered at that point,
it is assigned correct distance
estimate and it is saved in this value.
And the last property we want to prove,
just to understand better how
breadth-first search works and
to apply it to some nonstandard situation,
is that the queue which we use in
the breath-first search looks like this.
It first has some nodes of distance d for
some d, and
maybe in the end it has some
nodes of distance d + 1.
But it doesn't contain
any other distances.
If the first node in
the queue has distance d,
then there are no nodes in the queue
with distance less than d,
there are no nodes with
distance more than d + 1.
And maybe there are some nodes
at distance exactly d + 1, but
they all go after all the nodes
at distance d in the queue.
Let's prove that.
So first, we know that by order lemma,
all nodes at distance d were enqueued
before first such node is dequeued.
And nodes at distance d + 1 are only found
when a node at distance d
is dequeued in process.
So, this means that nodes at distance
d were enqueued before nodes at
distance d + 1 were dequeued.
Also, we know the same thing for
nodes at distance d- 1,
so they were all enqueued
before nodes at distance d.
So by the time node at
distance d is dequeued,
all the nodes at distance d- 1
are already dequeued from the queue.
So there are no more nodes in
the queue at distance d- 1 or less.
And regarding the nodes at distance
more than d + 1, they will be
discovered only when we start dequeuing
nodes at distance d + 1 and more.
But those nodes are all going
after nodes at distance d.
So at the point when the first
node in the queue has distance d,
no nodes at distance more than
d + 1 can be in the queue,
because no nodes at distance
d + 1 were dequeued and so
we couldn't put anything at distance
more than d + 1 in the queue.
So we proved this property.
Also, and now we have to prove that
our algorithm finds correct distances
to all the reachable nodes in the graph,
that it finds infinite distances to
the unreachable nodes in the graph,
and we also know the structure of
the queue at any given moment in time.
And in the next lecture,
we will also learn how to actually,
not only find distance, but
also reconstruct the shortest path
from the origin to the node we need.
Because we don't want to just know that
the distance in terms of number of
flight segments from Moscow to
San Diego is two, we also want to find
are those two flight segments to
actually get from Moscow to San Diego.
So, see that in the next video.