Hi, in this video you will learn
what is a shortest path tree, how to
use it to reconstruct the shortest
path from original to the node
you needed shortest path to after finding
distances with breadth-first search.
And we'll need to slightly modify
breadth-first search procedure for that.
What is the shortest-path tree?
On the left we some undirected
graph with a nine nodes, and
suppose we selected nodes as the origin.
Then on the right we see the layered
structure of this graph,
where as in the layer zero.
Four nodes in the layer one,
two nodes in the layer two and
two nodes in the layer three.
So, we know the distances to those
nodes but we also can remember is
how did we come to this or that particular
node during the breath's first search.
So, for example, we example,
we came to the node a during breath's
first search, directly from s.
We draw a directed edge from A to S.
Saying that S is the note from which
we came to A when we discovered it.
We also draw an edge
from B to A saying that
in our breakfast search algorithm
we discovered B from A.
So we can draw such an edge for
all the nodes but
for S itself, and we will get some graph.
And we'll prove later that it is a tree,
but to make a tree,
we also need to make it undirected, so we
just remove all the arrows from the edges.
And this already will be a tree.
So the lemma states that
shortest-path tree,
as we define it now, is indeed a tree.
So that it doesn't contain any cycles.
Because the fact that this is a connected
component is by construction.
We only add those nodes in the tree,
which we reached during breath for search.
And always connect a new note
we just discovered to some note,
which was already in the tree, so
the graph is obviously connected.
We're going to need to prove that
there are no cycles in this graph,
let's prove that as
usual by contradiction.
So, suppose there is a cycle
in the shortest path three.
And suppose this is a cycle off length 5,
A-B-C-D-E.
Now this is an undirected cycle but
the edges of the cycle have to
be ordered somehow initially.
So, for example, the edge between A and
B can be either from A to B or
B to A but it doesn't really matter.
Let's assume that.
Go from a to b without loss of generality.
Now what we know is in the shortest
path tree, at most one
outgoing edge from each node because for
each node other than s,
we just saved from which
node did we discovered it.
There is only one such node
from which this is discovered.
There at most one outgoing edge from each
node, and if we look at the edge between
A and E, we know that there is
an outgoing edge from A already.
The edge between A and E cannot be
an outgoing edge from A, because.
A would have two outgoing edges.
So the only way this can work is that
there is an outgoing edge from E to A.
And similarly, the edge between D and
E can only be attached from D to E,
and the same with edge CD and
the same with edge BC.
So now we see the directitude So
looks like it can work but
unfortunately it can not.
So lets look at the distance from S to A.
We know that when we go by the direct
edge of a shortest path graph we go from
node which was discovered from some node
To the nodes from which it was discovered.
And we know that the distance to
the newly discovered node is assigned
to distance of the nodes from
which it was discovered plus one.
So if we go by this edge to
the parent in the shortest path tree,
we decrease our distance
from S by exactly one.
We begin We stay in the node which
is closer to S, exactly by 1.
So if we go from A to B,
the distance to S decreases by 1.
If we go from B to C, decrease by 1.
So we start with some
distance D from S to A,
and then when we go by edge A B,
we stay at node B.
And we know that the distance
from S to B is at most D minus 1.
And then the distance to
C is at most d minus two,
and the distance to D is at most d minus
three, and d minus four for E, and now,
we make the conclusion that the distance
to A is at most d minus five.
So, d is at most d minus 5
which is a contradiction,
which cannot happen so, By contradiction
we'll prove that they're cannot be
any cycles in the shortest
path tree indeed.
Now how to construct
the shortest path tree?
We've defined it in such a way
that it is very easy to do.
We only need to add two statements
to the code of the BFS procedure.
We need another array or map, which is
called prev so in prev we will store for
each node the previous node
from which it was discovered.
And initialize it with
a pointer to no work with
a special pointer needle, which basically
means we don't have any previous node.
And when we discover a node
in the end of the procedure.
We not only have data
distance to those node, but
we also save the node from
which it was discovered.
Now this is the only moment when berev
changes because the next time we won't
discover this node again and
we won't change its berev.
So that's the whole code for
constructing shortest-path tree.
Now for every node we know what is
its parent in the shortest-path tree.