In this video, I'm gonna talk about
perceptrons.
These were investigated in the early
1960's, and initially they looked very
promising as learning devices.
But then they fell into disfavor because
Minsky and Papert showed they were rather
restricted in what they could learn to do.
In statistical pattern recognition,
there's a statistical way to recognize
patterns.
We first take the raw input, and we
convert it into a set or vector feature
activations.
We do this using hand written programs
which are based on common sense.
So that part of the system does not learn.
We look at the problem we decide what the
good features should be.
We try some features to see if they work
or don't work we try some more features
and eventually set of features that allow
us to solve the problem by using a
subsequent learning stage.
What we learn is how to weight each of the
feature activations, in order to get a
single scalar quantity.
So the weights on the features represent
how much evidence the feature gives you,
in favor or against the hypothesis that
the current input is an example of the
kind of pattern you want to recognize.
And when we add up all the weighted
features, we get a sort of total evidence
in favor of the hypothesis that this is
the kind of pattern we want to recognize.
And if that evidence is above some
threshold, we decide that the input vector
is a positive example of the class of
patterns we're trying to recognize.
A perceptron is a particular example of a
statistical pattern recognition system.
So there are actually many different kinds
of perceptrons, but the standard kind,
which Rosenblatt called an alpha
perceptron, consists of some inputs which
are then converted into future activities.
They might be converted by things that
look a bit like neurons, but that stage of
the system does not learn.
Once you've got the activities of the
features, you then learn some weights, so
that you can take the feature activities
times the weights and you decide whether
or not it's an example of the class you're
interested in by seeing whether that sum
of feature activities times learned
weights is greater than a threshold.
Perceptrons have an interesting history.
They were popularized in the early 1960s
by Frank Rosenblatt.
He wrote a great big book called
Principles of Neurodynamics, in which he
described many different kinds of
perceptrons, and that book was full of
ideas.
The most important thing in the book was a
very powerful learning algorithm, or
something that appeared to be a very
powerful learning algorithm.
A lot of grand claims were made for what
perceptrons could do using this learning
algorithm.
For example, people claimed they could
tell the difference between pictures of
tanks and pictures of trucks, even if the
tanks and trucks were sort of partially
obscured in a forest.
Now some of those claims turned out to be
false.
In the case of the tanks and the trucks,
it turned out the pictures of the tanks
were taken on a sunny day, and the
pictures of the trucks were taken on a
cloudy day.
All the perceptron was doing was measuring
the total intensity of all the pixels.
That's something we humans are fairly
insensitive to.
We notice the things in the picture.
But a perceptron can easily learn to add
up the total intensity.
That's the kind of thing that gives an
algorithm a bad name.
In 1969, Minsky and Papert published a
book called Perceptrons that analyzed what
perceptrons could do and showed their
limitations.
Many people thought those limitations
applied to all neural network models.
And the general feeling within artificial
intelligence was that Minsky and Papert
had shown that neural network models were
nonsense or that they couldn't learn
difficult things.
Minsky and Papert themselves knew that
they hadn't shown that.
They'd just shown that perceptrons of the
kind for which the powerful learning
algorithm applied could not do a lot of
things, or rather they couldn't do them by
learning.
They could do them if you sort of
hand-wired the answer in the inputs, but
not by learning.
But that result got wildly
overgeneralized, and when I started
working on neural network models in the
1970s, people in artificial intelligence
kept telling me that Minsky and Papert
have proved that these models were no
good.
Actually, the perceptron convergence
procedure, which we'll see in a minute, is
still widely used today for tasks that
have very big feature vectors.
So, Google, for example, uses it to
predict things from very big vectors of
features.
So, the decision unit in a perceptron is a
binary threshold neuron.
We've seen this before and just to re-,
refresh you on those.
They compute a weighted sum of inputs they
get from other neurons.
They add on a bias to get their total
input.
And then they give an output of one if
that sum exceeds zero, and they give an
output of zero otherwise.
We don't want to have to have a separate
learning rule for learning biases, and it
turns out we can treat biases just like
weights.
If we take every input vector and we stick
a one on the front of it, and we treat the
bias as like the weight on that first
feature that always has a value of one.
So the bias is just the negative of the
threshold.
And using this trick, we don't need a
separate learning rule for the bias.
It's exactly equivalent to learning a
weight on this extra input line.
So here's the very powerful learning
procedure for perceptrons, and it's a
learning procedure that's guaranteed to
work, which is a nice property to have.
Of course you have to look at the small
print later, about why that guarantee
isn't quite as good as you think it is.
So we first had this extra component with
a value of one to every input vector.
Now we can forget about the biases.
And then we keep picking training cases,
using any policy we like, as long as we
ensure that every training case gets
picked without waiting too long.
I'm not gonna define precisely what I mean
by that.
If you're a mathematician, you could think
about what might be a good definition.
Now, having picked a training case, you
look to see if the output's correct.
If it is correct, you don't change the
weights.
If the output unit outputs a zero when it
should've output a one, in other words, it
said it's not an instance of the pattern
we're trying to recognize, when it really
is, then all we do is we add the input
vector to the weight vector of the
perceptron.
Conversely, if the output unit, outputs a
one, when is should have output a zero, we
subract the input vector, from the weight
vector of the [inaudible].
And what's surprising is that, that simple
learning procedure is guaranteed to find
you a set of weights that will get a right
answer for every training case.
The proviso is that it can only do it if
it is such a set of weights and for many
interesting problems there is no such set
of weights.
Whether or not a set of weights exist
depends very much on what features you
use.
So it turns out for many problems the
difficult bit is deciding what features to
use.
If you're using the appropriate features
learning then may become easy.
If you're not using the right features
learning becomes impossible and all the
work is deciding the features.