Once a function is defined,
we can call it over and over again.
In this lecture,
we're going to focus on reusing functions
by calling them in other
places when appropriate.
For example, we'll call our functions from
within other function definitions and
also within other function calls.
In the lecture on defining functions,
we wrote triangle.pie which
contained two functions.
This code is a revised version that
I produced following the steps of
the design recipe.
To recap the design recipe,
we begin with an example or two, followed
by the type contract, the function header,
a description of the function.
We then code the body and
test the function.
We'll now add another
function to triangle.pie.
This function will calculate
the semiperimeter of a triangle.
The semiperimeter is simply
half of the perimeter.
Following the exact design recipe, the
first step is coming up with an example.
We will call the function semiperimeter.
The function will need the lengths of
the three sides in order to perform
the calculation.
So in the function call we'll
imagine passing in three lengths.
And then the result we get back
will be half of the perimeter.
Let's do one more function call,
this time passing floats
instead of ints as arguments.
And the result that we expect
to get back would be 12.9.
The next step of the design
recipe is the type contract.
For the semiperimeter function,
the types will be numbers cuz
we may have ints or floats.
And this function will return a float.
Next we provide the function header.
We begin with the keyword def
followed by the function name that we
already decided on in our example calls.
And we pass in three
parameters in this case.
I will call them side1, side2 and side3.
Next is the function description.
We need to say what
the function will return, and
explain how the parameters are used.
So we're going to return
the semiperimeter of a triangle
that has sides of the length
given in the parameters.
We're now ready to write
the body of the function.
This function is going to return the
semiperimeter, which means that we will
calculate the perimeter by summing the
three sides and divide that result by two.
Notice the part of the body
of the semiperimeter function
is exactly the same as part
of the body of perimeter.
Rather than duplicating the code
to calculate the perimeter,
we can call the perimeter function from
within the semiperimeter function.
By reusing the perimeter function,
we reduce the risk of making an error when
calculating the perimeter, since that
function has already been tested.
Now it's time to test
the semiperimeter function.
We will begin by running the module.
And then we will execute that function
by calling it within the shell.
I'm going to use the same example that
I used in the function's doc string.
And we get back 6.
And then if I call it with
the floats from the doc string,
well, a mix of floats and
ints, we get back 12.9.
So the function performs
as we expect it to.
Here's another problem for us to consider.
For this problem we're going to
make use of the area function
that we wrote earlier.
Recall that area has two parameters,
the base and the height.
And then it returns
the area of the triangle.
This problem involves two slices of pizza.
At a party there are these
two slices of pizza left.
A hungry person is trying to figure
out which slice is the largest.
Since the slices
are the shape of triangles,
this person measures the base and
the height of each slice.
Now that we know the base and
the height of each slice of pizza,
we can use our program to help
determine which is biggest.
We'll also use one of
Python's built-in functions,
the max function, to help us out.
So we start by calling max.
And the first argument that we'll pass to
max will be the area of the first slice
of pizza, the slice that has base 3.8 and
height 7.0.
And then the second argument to
the function max will be area
of the second slice of pizza,
a triangle with base 3.5 and height 6.8.
When we execute this function, we find
out which of those two areas is bigger.
And now we can check to see which
slice of pizza that that value,
13.29 repeating, corresponds with.
So we can see from that function
call the area of the first slice
matches the maximum area.
And that means that the winning
pizza slice is this one.
So what this example shows is that
not only can we call functions
from within function definitions,
as we did in the semiperimeter example.
But we can also pass
function calls as arguments
to functions since function calls
are themselves expressions.