In this video we're going to use the
Python Visualizer to explore how function
calls are managed in computer memory.
We have written a function
called convert to minutes,
which takes in a number of hours, and
returns the equivalent number of minutes.
For example, if we call convert to
minutes with argument 2 then expect
to get back 120,
because there are 120 minutes in 2 hours.
Notice the indentation all code
belonging to a function must be indented
typically four spaces.
Let's visualize what happens
when we run this program.
When we read the function definition,
of author one Python does,
we see that a variable called
convert to minutes is created.
It contains a memory address
of a function object.
That function object contains all
information about the function including
any code that needs to be executed,
the parameter, and the doc string.
We are now now paused on line ten which
contains an assignment statement.
Notice the variable minutes
too has not been created yet,
that will happen after we finish
executing the assignment statement.
So first we have to evaluate
the expression on the right hand side of
the equals symbol, and
that expression is a function call.
Once that function call has returned it
will give us back a value and minutes
too will be created and it will store
the memory address of that returned value.
In order to execute this function
call the argument is evaluated.
That will create a box for value 2 in
addition a new region of memory will be
created to keep track of what happens
while convert_to_minutes is executed.
Here is value 2 and
here is variable num_hours,
the area of computer memory to
the right is called the heap.
And contains all the values that
are created during execution of a program.
The area of memory to the left
is called the call stack,
it's called a stack because
it's like a stack of plates.
When a function is called,
a stack frame is created and
when that function returns,
its frame is removed from the stack.
And control passes back to
the caller of that function,
each frame contains variables that are
specific to that section of the program.
The main frame contains variables that
are created outside of a new function and
frames for functions contain
parameters and local variables.
A local variable is any
variable that is created inside
of a function such as variable result.
Line seven contains
an assignment statement,
we evaluate the right hand side.
We look up what num_hours is and
it's 2, 2 times 60 is 120.
So we're going to see
a value 120 get created.
And we're going to see a variable
result get created inside function
convert_to_minutes.
Result refers to 120,
num_hours refers to 2.
We're about to execute a return statement
that's going to evaluate result,
which is 120 and
it's going to yield that memory address.
Notice that we get to see
what the return value is.
As soon as we click forward one more time
we're going to exit function
convert_to_minutes.
Control is going to pass back to where we
were in the program, that was right here.
We're going to finish this call to
convert_to_minutes with argument 2 and
it's going to give us back
the memory address of value 120.
That should create a variable minutes 2,
In deed, that's what happens.
The stack frame for
the call to convert_to_minutes is gone,
gone from computer memory.
That's what happens when a function exits,
we're going to step through
another column convert_to_minutes, this
time we're going to pass an argument 3.
And we're going to save the results
to result the minutes_3 here.
Let's watch that happen, we evaluate
3 which creates it in the heap,
Num_hours refers to that value now.
It used to refer,
on the first call, to value two.
Now it refers to value 3 because we've
called it with a different argument.
Now, when I calculate num_hours times 60,
I look at the stack here and
I see that I'm taking 3 times 60,
and that's 180.
And so we're going to get
a variable result referring to 180.
We still have value 120 up here
because outside of this function,
minutes 2 still refers to it.
Now we're going to return 180,
that will yield memory
address id5 which is going be
stored inside a new variable
minutes_3 which will be
created in this main module.