Last week, we were introduced to
the pandas data manipulation and
analysis library.
We saw that there is really two-core
data structures which are very similar,
the one-dimensional series object and
the two-dimensional DataFrame object.
Querying these two data structures
is done in a few different ways,
such as using the iloc or
loc attributes for row-based querying, or
using the square brackets on the object
itself for column-based querying.
Most importantly, we saw that
one can query the DataFrame and
Series objects through Boolean masking.
And Boolean masking is a powerful
filtering method which
allows us to use broadcasting to determine
what data should be kept in our analysis.
In this week's lecture,
we're going to go into more detail on how
to manipulate DataFrame, in particular.
We're going to explore how to reduce and
process data using GroupBy and Apply,
and how to join data sets from
multiple files together into one.
We'll also talk about some features
that pandas has which are useful for
both traditional statistical analyses and
machine learning.
Let's start with how to merge data sets.
We've already seen how we add new
data to an existing DataFrame.
We simply use the square bracket
operator with the new column name,
and the data is added as
long as an index is shared.
If there is no shared index and
a scalar value is passed in,
which remember a scalar value is just a
single value like an integer or a string.
The new value column is added with
the scalar value as the default value.
What if we wanted to assign
a different value for every row?
Well, it gets trickier.
If we could hardcode the values into
a list, then pandas will unpack them and
assign them to the rows.
But if the list we have isn't long enough,
then we can't do this,
since Pandas doesn't know where
the missing values should go.
Here's an example.
We used the DataFrame of store purchases
from one of our previous lectures,
where the index is a list of stores and
the columns store purchase data.
If we want to add some new column called
Date to the DataFrame, that's fine.
We just use the square bracket
operator directly on the DataFrame,
as long as the column is as long
as the rest of the records.
If we want to add some new field,
may be a delivery flag,
that's easy too since it's a scalar value.
The problem comes in when we
have only a few items to add.
In order for this to work,
we have to supply pandas the list
which is long enough for the DataFrame,
so that each row could be populated.
This means that we have to
input none values ourselves.
If each of our rows has a unique index,
then we could just assign the new
column identifier to the series.
For instance, if we reset the index in
this example so the DataFrame is labeled
from 1 through 2, then we create a new
series with these labels, we can apply it.
And the results we get are as we expected.
The nice aspect of this approach is that
we could just ignore the items that we
don't know about, and
pandas will put missing values in for us.
So this is a really nice way to do it.
More commonly, we want to join two
larger DataFrames together, and
this is a bit more complex.
Before we jump into the code, we need to
address a little relational theory, and
to get some language conventions down.
This is a Venn Diagram.
A Venn Diagram is traditionally
used to show set membership.
For example, the circle on the left is the
population of students at a university.
The circle on the right is
the population of staff at a university.
And the overlapping region in the middle
are all of those students who
are also staff.
Maybe these students run tutorials for
a course, or grade assignments,
or engage in running research experiments.
We could think of these two populations
as indices in separate DataFrames,
maybe with the label of Person Name.
When we want to join the DataFrames
together, we have some choices to make.
First what if we want a list of
all the people regardless of
whether they're staff or student, and
all of the information we can get on them?
In database terminology,
this is called a full outer join.
And in set theory, it's called a union.
In the Venn diagram,
it represents everyone in any circle.
It's quite possible though that we only
want those people who we have maximum
information for, those people
who are both staff and students.
In database terminology,
this is called an inner join.
Or in set theory, the intersection.
And this is represented in the Venn
diagram as the overlapping parts
of each circle.
Okay, so let's see an example of
how we would do this in pandas,
where we would use the merge function.
First we create two DataFrames,
staff and students.
There's some overlap in these DataFrames,
in that James and
Sally are both students and staff,
but Mike and Kelly are not.
Importantly, both DataFrames are indexed
along the value we want to merge them on,
which is called Name.
If we want the union of these,
we would call merge passing in the
DataFrame on the left and the DataFrame on
the right, and telling merge that
we want it to use an outer join.
We tell merge that we want to use the left
and right indices as the joining columns.
We see in the resulting DataFrame
that everyone is listed.
And since Mike does not have a role, and
John does not have a school,
those cells are listed as missing values.
If we wanted to get the intersection,
that is,
just those students who are also staff,
we could set the how attribute to inner.
And we set the resulting DataFrame
has only James and Sally in it.
Now there are two other common use
cases when merging DataFrames.
Both are examples of what
we would call set addition.
The first is when we would want to get
a list of all staff regardless of whether
they were students or not.
But if they were students, we would want
to get their student details as well.
To do this we would use a left join.
You could probably guess what comes next.
We want a list of all of the students and
their roles if they were also staff.
To do this we would do a right join.
The merge method has a couple
of other interesting parameters.
First, you don't need to use indices to
join on, you can use columns as well.
Here's an example.
So what happens when we have
conflicts between the DataFrames?
Let's take a look by
creating new staff and
student DataFrames that have
a location information added to them.
In the staff DataFrame,
this is an office location where
we can find the staff person.
And we can see the Director
of HR is on State Street,
while the two students
are on Washington Avenue.
But for the student DataFrame,
the location information is
actually their home address.
The merge function preserves this
information, but appends an _x or
_y to help differentiate between which
index went with which column of data.
The _x is always the left
DataFrame information, and
the _ y is always the right
DataFrame information.
And you could control the names of _x and
_y with additional
parameters if you want to.
Now you try it.
Here's a DataFrame of products and
invoices.
The product has an identifier and
a sticker price.
The invoice lists the people,
products, identifiers, and quantity.
Assuming that we want to generate totals,
how do we join these two DataFrames
together so that we have one which
lists all of the information we need?
Before we leave merging of DataFrames,
let's talk about multi-indexing and
multiple columns.
It's quite possible that the first name
for students and staff might overlap, but
the last name might not.
In this case, we use a list of the
multiple columns that should be used to
join keys on the left_on and
right_on parameters.
As you see here, James Wilde and
James Hammond don't match on both keys.
So the inner join doesn't include
these individuals in the output, and
only Sally Brooks is retained.
That's it for merging of DataFrames.
pandas has a lot more options in the area,
but I think the merge function is perhaps
the most easiest to understand and
the most flexible.
In the next section, we're going to talk
about how to write idiomatic pandas and
delve a bit deeper into more advanced
functions for manipulating DataFrames.