Hello, and
welcome to the sorting problem lesson.
As usual,
we start with a problem I'll review.
So sorting is a fundamental
computational problem.
Your input in this problem consists
of a sequence of elements, and
your goal is to output this element in,
for example, non-decreasing order.
The formal statement of
this problem is as follows.
You are given a sequence
of finite elements.
We will usually denote the sequence
by A throughout this lesson.
And your goal is to output these same
elements in non-decreasing order.
Once again,
sorting is an important computational
task used in many efficient algorithms.
For some algorithms,
it is just as important to process
given elements in non-decreasing order,
going from smaller ones to larger ones.
In some other algorithms,
just by sorting your input data,
you gain a possibility to perform
your queries much more efficiently.
A canonical example of such
situation is a search problem.
In this problem, we are given
a sequence of finite elements.
And your goal is to check whether
a particular element is present
in your sequence.
A simple way to solve this problem, is of
course, just to scan your input sequence
from left to right and to check, whether
your element is present in this sequence.
This gives you a linear kind algorithm.
And you know already
that if you input data,
if you input sequences you sorted,
then you can do this much more faster.
Basically, in time, in logarithmic time,
in the size of your input sequence.
So ou first compare your
element to the middle element.
If it is just few element, then you
are done, if it is not, you continue
with the left half of your sequence or
the right half of your sequence.
So in logarithmic number of comparison,
and the worst case, you
will be able to say whether your element
is present in this sequence or not.
So, if you are given a sequence and
you are expecting many such queries.
You're expecting to be asked to check
whether a given object is present or not.
For me such objects, then it just makes
sense to first sort your input data and
only then perform all these queries.
This will give you a much more
efficient algorithm in general.
All right.
And this is only a small example.
We will see many other situations,
where sorting your data first helps to
perform queries much more efficiently.
So in the subsequent
videos of this lesson,
we will study many efficient
sorting algorithms.