In the previous video, we proved that
the running time of the Warshall
algorithm on a sequence consisting
of n elements is big log of n.
In this video we will show that
this bond is essentially optimal.
We will do this by showing that
any correct sorting algorithm
that sorts an object by
comparing pairs of them.
Must make a clear stand log in operation
such as particularly in the worst case.
Once again we say that the sorting
algorithm is comparison based
if it sorts the given objects
just by comparing pairs of them.
We can imagine the following situation, we
have add objects, that look the same, for
example in walls, but
have different weights.
And we also have pen balance.
And this pen balance is, our only
way to compare pairs of these balls.
And our goal is to rearrange these balls,
in order of increasing weights.
So, for example, the two source and
algorithms that we'll already consider it,
namely the selection sort algorithm and
the merge sort algorithm are both
comparison based algorithms.
So for example, the selection
sort algorithm at each region
finds the minimum value in
the remaining part of the array.
And it does so exactly by
comparing pairs of objects, right?
Also, the merge sort algorithm is
also comparison based algorithm.
So it first splits an array into halves.
And then it needs to merge
the two results in arrays.
And when merging the results in arrays,
it also uses comparisons, right?
So we take the first two
elements of two sorted arrays.
We compare them, and based on this
comparison we take one of these elements
out of one of those two arrays and
put it to the result in the array.
So this as a formal statement
that we're going to prove.
It says that any
comparison based algorithm
that sorts an object has running time.
At least big and
n log n in the worst case.
So but
in otherwise we can say the following.
Assume that you have an algorithm
that sorts an object
by comparing pairs of them.
It can be the case that for
some given both sequences of an object,
your algorithm performs less
than analog operations.
Say, linear number of operations.
However, it cannot be the case that
your algorithm always sorts in time,
asymptotically less than n log n.
Meaning that, there must exist, sequence
of objects, on which your algorithm
will perform at least performing a login
comparison to sort such sequences.
Any comparison based algorithm can be
shown as a huge tree that contains all
possible sequences of comparisons
that can be made by this algorithm.
For example, here on the slide.
We show a simple algorithm
that sort three object.
Three objects.
So it starts by comparing a1 and a2.
If a1 happens to be smaller than a2,
then we proceed to comparing a2 and a3.
If a2 is smaller than a3,
then we already know the permutation
of the input three objects
in non-decreasing order.
Namely, we know that
a1 is smaller than a2,
and we know that a2 is smaller than a3.
So we can just output
the following permutation.
Right.
If on the other hand,
a2 happened to be at least a3,
then at this point we already
know that a2 is greater than a1.
And a2 Is no smaller than a3.
So at this point, we know that a2 is the
maximum element among our three elements.
However, we still need to compare a1 and
a3, so we do this comparison,
and based on its result, we output either
this permutation or this permutation.
Well this was the case when a1
happened to be small as an a2.
However we need also to consider the case
when a1 happened to be at least a2.
So we proceed similarly in this case.
So this is just a toy example for
an algorithm for
a comparison based algorithm comparing
three objects, sorting three objects.
However, such a huge tree can be drawn for
any comparison based health algorithm.
So at the root of this tree
we have the first comparison.
And its children will label just the next
comparison that is made based on the
result of the first comparison and so on.
So each internal node is
labeled with some comparison.
And each leaf is labeled with
a permutation of m input objects.
A simple but crucial for this argument
observation is that in this tree,
we must have at least n factorial leaves.
And this is because we have n factorial
different permutations of n input objects.
Where n factorial is defined to be
the product of n and minus one and
minus two and so on.
So why is that?
Why we must have any possible
permutation as a leaf in our tree?
Well, this is just because it is possible
that this permutation is a lead output,
is the right output of our algorithm.
So for example on our previous slide, on
our toy example, we have three objects and
there are six possible permutations
of these three objects, and
there are six leaves in our tree.
For example one of them is 213 and
it says that the second element
is the smallest one, then goes the first
element, and then goes the third element.
And indeed there are cases
when this is the right answer.
Right?
So when the input data
consists of three objects,
such that the second element
is the smallest one,
the first one is the next one, and
the third element is the largest one.
Right?
So once again, you have a huge tree which
carries a comparison based algorithm.
There must be at least n factorial leaves,
because each possible permutation must
be present as a leaf in our tree.
So on the other hand the maximal number of
comparisons made by our algorithm
corresponds to the depths of our tree.
So the depths is defined as
the maximal number of edges run away
from the root to the leaf,
to some leaf of our tree.
So and this is exactly the maximal
possible number of comparisons
which our algorithm makes.
So now we would like to show that
d must be large in our case,
must be at least be big
O omega of analog n.
And we know already that our
tree contains many, many leaves.
Mean n factorial is a function
that grows extremely fast.
Okay so, intuitively we would like
to show that if a tree has many,
many leaves, then it has a large depth.
And at least intuitively this clear.
If you have a tree of very small depths
then it must just a few leaves, right?
But, we know that it has many, many,
many leaves,
in fact at least ten factorial leaves.
To formally show this we need the
following, we need the following estimate.
The depths of a binary tree is at
least a binary algorithm of its number
of leaves or equivalently 2 to the depths
is at least its number of leaves.
Well this can be proved formally, but
let me just show you this informally.
Let's concede a tree for
example of depth 1.
So in this case, d is equal to 1.
And it is clear that the maximal
possible number of leaves
in a tree of depth 1 is equal to 2.
So now, let's try to understand
what is the maximal possible
number of leaves in a depth
of In a tree of depth 2.
For example, this is a tree of depth 2.
This is another tree of depth 2,
it has has three leaves.
And this is a tree of depth 2 that has
maximal possible number of leaves,
in this case it is 4.
It is 2 to the d indeed.
And intuitively it is clear that
to have a tree of depth d that has
maximal possible number of leaves.
We need to take a tree which has
a full binary tree of depth d, right?
And this tree has exactly
2 to the d leaves.
So the maximal number of leaves in
a tree of depth d is 2 to the d.
Which proves that 2 to
the d is at least l.
Okay, so the last step that we need to
show is that if we have n factorial
leaves, then the depths of our
tree is at least big log n again.
And we will show this on the next slide.
It remains to estimate log of n factorial.
We're going to show here that log of n
factorial is at least c times n log n.
Which means as it works that log of
n factorial is big log of n log n.
To do this, we express n
factorial as a product of 1, 2, 3.
And so on n minus 1, and
then right algorithm of product of these
numbers as a sum of their algorithm.
So, log of n factorial is equal to log
of 1 plus log of 2 plus log of 3 and
so on plus log of n.
So, this is a sum of an object.
Let's just throw away the first
half of this and elements,
and leave only the second half.
So in this second half,
we have n over two elements and
each of them is at least
log of n over two, right?
So this has algorithms of numbers
which are at least n over two.
So we have n over two.
Elements, each of them is at
least algorithms of n over 2.
This allows us to conclude that log sum is
at least 10 over 2 times log of n over 2.
And this in turn be big log of n for
a simple reason.
So log n over 2 is equal to log n minus 1.
Well, this grows like log n, right?
Because log n is a growing function and
one is a constant so
again minus one goes as log n.
And over grows as n, right?
So, this is up to constant factors,
this is just n.
So, n over two times log n
over two grows like n log n.
Okay so this concludes our proof, and
this concludes the proof of
the fact that any comparison based
algorithm must make at least n log
n adorations in the worst case.
Once again, another conclusion is that
when merged sort algorithms that we
considered in the previous lecture
e is asymmetrically optimal.
In the next video we will see
an algorithm that actually sorts
n given objects in time less than n log n.
Actually in time just in linear time.
In time big log of n however,
it will sort the n given objects,
knowing something about these objects.
It will only sort the given objects
if the subject has small integers.
And we will sort them without actually
comparing them to each other.