Hello everybody!
Welcome back.
Today we're going to start talk
about Fibonacci Numbers and
algorithms to compute them.
In particular, in this lecture we're
just going to introduce the sequence of
the Fibonacci numbers and
talk a little bit about their properties.
So to begin with the Fibonacci numbers
is a fairly classically studied
sequence of natural numbers.
The 0th element of the sequence is 0.
The first element is 1.
And from thereon, each element
is the sum of the previous two.
So 0 and 1 is 1.
1 + 1 is 2.
1 + 2 is 3.
2 + 3 is 5.
And the sequence continues,
8, 13, 21, 34, and so on.
So it's a nice sequence of numbers
defined by some pretty simple recursive
rule and it's interesting for
a number of reasons.
It has some interesting number theoretic
properties, but originally this sequence
was developed by an Italian
mathematician as a mathematical model.
And it's a little bit weird.
You might try and wonder what sorts
of things this could be a model for.
Well, it turns out that, originally,
this was used as sort of a mathematical
model for rabbit populations.
There was some idea that if
you had a pair of rabbits,
it would take them one generation to
mature and every generation thereafter,
they'd produce a pair of offspring.
And if you work out what this means,
then you find out the Fibonacci numbers,
tell you how many pairs of rabbits
you have after n generations.
Now, because rabbits are known for
reproducing rather quickly, you might
assume that the sequence therefore
grows quickly, and in fact it does.
It's not hard to show that
the nth Fibonacci number is at
least 2 to the n over 2 for
all n at least 6.
And the proof can be made by induction.
You prove this directly for n 6 or
7 just by computing the numbers and
showing that they're big enough.
And after that point,
Fn is the sum of Fn-1 and Fn-2.
By the inductive hypothesis,
you bound that below and
do a little bit of arithmetic.
And it's bounded below by 2 to the n/2.
So that completes the proof.
In fact, with a little bit more work
you can actually get a formula for
the nth Fibonacci number as roughly
1 point square root of 5 over 2 to the n.
These things grow exponentially quickly.
And to sort of drive that home a little
bit more, we can look at some examples.
The 20th Fibonacci number is 6765.
The 50th Fibonacci number is
approximately 12 billion.
The 100th Fibonacci number is much,
much bigger than that.
And the 500th Fibonacci number is this
monster with something like a 100
digits to it.
So these numbers do get
rather large quite quickly.
So the problem that we're
going to be looking into for
the next couple of lectures is,
how do you compute Fibonacci?
So, if you want to use them to
model rabbit populations or
because of some number theoretic interest.
We'd like an algorithm that as input
takes a non negative integer n and
returns the nth Fibonacci number.
And we're going to talk about
how you go about doing this.
So, come back next lecture and
we'll talk about that.