Hello everybody.
Welcome back.
Today we'll talk a little bit more
about how to compute Fibonacci numbers.
And, in particular, today what we're going
to do is we're going to show you how to
produce a very simple algorithm that
computes these things correctly.
On the other hand, we're going to show
that this algorithm is actually very slow,
and talk a little bit
about how to analyze that.
So let's take a look at
the definition again.
The zero'th Fibonacci number is 0.
The first Fibonacci number is 1.
And from there after each Fibonacci
number is the sum of the previous two.
Now these grow pretty rapidly,
and what we would like to do is
have an algorithm to compute them.
So let's take a look at
how we might do this.
Well, there's a pretty easy way to
go about it, given the definition.
So if n is 0, we're supposed to return 0.
And if n is 1, we're supposed to return 1.
So we could just start with a case
that says if n is at most 1,
we're going to return n.
Otherwise what are we supposed to do?
Otherwise, we're supposed to
return the sum of the n- 1, and
n- 2 Fibonacci numbers.
So we can just compute those two
recursively, add them together, and
return them.
So, this gives us a very simple
algorithm four lines long that
basically took the definition of our
problem and turned it into an algorithm
that correctly computes
the thing it's supposed to.
Good for us.
We have an algorithm and it works.
However, in this course, we care a lot
more than just, does our algorithm work?
We also want to know if it's efficient, so
we'd like to know how long this algorithm
takes to run, and there's sort of
a rough approximation to this.
We're going to let T(n) denote
the number of lines of code
that are executed by this
algorithm on input n.
So to count this is
actually not very hard.
So if n is at most one,
the algorithm checks the if case,
goes to the return statement,
and that's two lines of code.
Not so bad.
If n is at least two,
we go to the if case.
We go to the else condition, and
then run a return statement.
That's three lines of code.
However ,in this case we also need
to recursively compute the n-1, and
n-2 Fibonacci numbers.
So we need to add to that however many
lines of code those recursive calls take.
So all in all though,
we have a nice recursive formula for T(n).
It's two as long as n is at most one.
And otherwise, it's equal to T(n) minus
one plus T(n) minus two plus three.
So a nice recursive formula.
Now, if you look at this formula for
a little bit, you'll notice that it looks
very similar to the original formula that
we used to define the Fibonacci numbers.
Each guy was more or
less the sum of the previous two.
And in fact,
from this you can show pretty easily
that T( n) is at least the n'th
Fibonacci number for all n.
And this should be ringing some warning
bells because we know that the Fibonacci
numbers get very, very,
very large, so T(n) must as well.
In fact,
T(100) is already 1.77 times 10 to the 21.
1.77 sextillion.
This is a huge number.
Now, suppose we were running
this program on a computer that
executed a billion lines of code a second.
It ran it at a gigahertz.
It would still take us about 56,000
years to complete this computation.
Now, I don't have 56,000 years to wait for
my computer to finish.
You probably don't either, so
this really is somehow not acceptable,
if we want to compute Fibonacci
numbers of any reasonable size.
So what we'd really like is
we'd like a better algorithm.
And we'll get to that next lecture.
But first we should talk a little bit
about why this algorithm is so slow.
And to see that, maybe the clearest
way to demonstrate it is to look at
all of the recursive calls this algorithm
needs in order to compute its answer.
So, if we want to compute
the n'th Fibonacci number,
we need to make recursive calls to compute
the n-1,and n-2 Fibonacci numbers.
To compute the n-1,
we need the n-2 to the n-3.
To compute the n-2, we need the n-3, and
n-4, and it just keeps going on and on.
From there we get this big
tree of recursive calls.
Now if you'll look at this
tree a little bit closer,
it looks like we're doing
something a little bit silly.
We're computing Fn-3,
three separate times in this tree.
And the way with our algorithm works,
every time we're asked to compute it,
since this is a new recursive call,
we compute the whole thing from scratch.
We recompute Fn-4, and Fn-5, and then,
add them together and get our answer.
And it's this computing
the same thing over and
over again that's really slowing us down.
And to make it even more extreme,
let's blow up the tree a little bit more.
Fn-4 actually gets computed these
five separate times by the algorithm.
And as you keep going down more and
more and more times,
are you just computing the same
thing over and over again?
And this is really the problem with
this particular algorithm, but
it's not clear immediately
that we can do better.
So, come back next lecture and we'll talk
about how to get around this difficulty,
and actually get a fairly
efficient algorithm.