Hello, everybody, welcome back.
We're still talking about algorithms
to compute Fibonacci numbers.
And in this lecture,
we're going to see how to actually
compute them reasonably efficiently.
So, as you'll recall, the Fibonacci
numbers was the sequence zero,
then one, then a bunch of elements, each
of which is the sum of the previous two.
We had a very nice algorithm for them last
time, which unfortunately was very, very
slow, even to compute the 100th Fibonacci
number say. So we'd like to do better.
And maybe you need some idea for
this new algorithm.
And one way to think about it is what do
you do when you compute them by hand.
And in particular,
suppose we want to write down a list
of all the Fibonacci numbers.
Well, there's sort of
an obvious way to do this.
You start off by writing zero and
one because those are the first two.
The next one going to be zero plus one,
which is one.
The next one is one plus one which is two,
and one plus two, which is three,
and two plus three, which is five.
And at each step, all I need to do is look
at the last two elements of the list and
add them together.
So, three and five are the last two,
I add them together, and I get eight.
And, this way, since I have all of
the previous numbers written down,
I don't need to do these recursive calls
that I was making in the last lecture,
that were really slowing us down.
So, let's see how this algorithm works.
What I need to do is I need to
create an array in order to store
all the numbers in this
list that I'm writing down.
The zeroth element of
the array gets set to zero,
the first element gets set to one,
that's to set our initial conditions.
Then as i runs from two to n, we need to
set the ith element to be the sum of the i
minus first and i minus second elements.
That correctly computes
the ith Fibonacci number.
Then, at the end of the day,
once I've filled out the entire list,
I'm going to return the last
element after that.
So, now we can say,
this is another algorithm,
it should work just as well,
but, how fast is it?
Well, how many lines of code did you use?
There are three lines of
code at the beginning, and
there's a return statement at the end,
so that's four lines of code.
Next up we have this for statement
that we run through n minus one times,
and each time we have to
execute two lines of code.
So adding everything together we find out
that t of n is something like 2n plus two.
So if we wanted to run this
program on input n equals 100,
it would take us about 202
lines of code to run it.
And 202 is actually a pretty small number
even on a very modest computer these days.
So essentially, this thing is going
to be trivial to compute the 100th or
the 1,000th or the 10,000th Fibonacci
number on any reasonable computer.
And this is much better than the results
that we were seeing in the last lecture.
So in summary,
what we've done in this last
few lectures, we've talked about the
Fibonacci numbers, we've introduced them.
We've come up with this naive algorithm,
this very simple algorithm that goes
directly from the definition, that
unfortunately takes thousands of years,
even on very small examples to finish.
On the other hand, the algorithm we just
saw is much better, it's incredibly fast
even on fairly large inputs and
it works quite well in practice.
And so, the moral of this story,
the thing to really keep in
mind is that in this case and
in many, many others the right algorithm
makes all the difference in the world.
It's the difference between
an algorithm that will
never finish in your entire lifetime and
one that finishes in the blink of an eye.
And so,
that's the story with Fibonacci numbers.
Next lecture we're going to talk about
a very similar story that comes with
computing greatest common divisors.
So I hope you come back for that.
Until then, farewell.