In this video, I am going to describe how
we might be able to combine recognition
of objects by using the relationships
between their parts and recognition of
objects using a deep neural network.
At present in computer vision, there's
broadly three approaches to recognizing
objects.
Either you use a deep convolutional
neural net and this currently works best.
Or you use a parts-based approach, which
I think in the long run is going to work
best,. Or you use the existing features
that computer vision people know how to
extract from images and make histograms
of them and then use lots of hand
engineering.
This is the approach that the
convolutional neural networks have
recently beaten.
The point of this video is to show how we
might combine a parts-based approach with
early stages that use convolutional
neraul networks.
Even though convolutional neural networks
have worked very well for recognizing
objects and images,
I think there's something missing.
When we pool the activities of a bunch of
replicator feature detectors, we lose the
precise position of the feature detector
that was most active.
This means we don't know exactly where
things are and that's fatal for high
level parts, such as the nose and the
mouth.
In order to recognize whose face it is,
you need to use the precise spatial
relationships between high level parts,
like noses and mouths.
If you overlap the pools so that each
feature occurs in several different
pools, you retain more information about
its position and that makes things work a
bit better, but I don't think that's the
answer.
A related problem is that convolutional
neural nets that use translations to
replicate feature detectors cannot
extrapolate their understanding of
geometrical relationships to radically
new viewpoints like different
orientations or different scales.
We could, of course, try replicating
across orientation and scale, but then,
we get huge numbers of replicated feature
detectors.
Now, people are very good at
extrapolating.
After seeing a new shape once, they can
recognize it from a very different
viewpoint.
Currently, the way we deal with that with
convolutional neural networks is to train
them on transformed data.
So this involves giving them huge
training sets, where we tried to
transform the data through different
orientations, and scales, and lightings,
and all sorts of other things so that the
network can cope with those variations.
But that's a very clumsy way of dealing
with the variations.
I think a much better way is to use a
hierarchy of coordinate frames and to use
a group of neurons to represent the
conjunction of the shape of a feature and
it's pose relative to the retina.
So when these neurons are active, it
tells you a feature of that kind is
there, like a nose.
And the precise activities or relative
activities of these neurons tell you the
pose of the nose.
If you think about representing the pose
of something, that's really a
relationship between two coordinate
frames.
So it's a relationship between a
coordinate frame embedded in the thing
and the coordinate frame of the camera or
retina.
So, in order to represent the pose of
something, we have to embed a coordinate
frame within it.
Once we've done this and we have a
representation of the pose of thoughts of
objects relative to the reckoner, it's
easy to use the relationships between
paths to recognize larger objects.
So we're going to use the consistency of
the poses of the parts as a cue for
recognizing a larger shape.
If you look at this picture, we have a
nose and we have a mouth and then the
right spacial relationship to one
another.
One way of thinking about that is that if
you ask the mouth to predict the pose of
the whole face, and if you ask the nose
to predict the pose of the whole face,
they'll make similar predictions.
If you look on the right share, we have
the same nose and the same mouth, but now
they're in the wrong spatial
relationship.
And that means that if they separately
make predictions about the pose of the
whole face, those predictions won't agree
at all.
So here's two layers in a hierarchy of
parts, where the larger parts can be
recognized by consistent predictions from
smaller parts.
Let's suppose we're looking for a face.
And so in the middle here the ellipse
with Tj in it is a collection of neurons
that are going to be used for recognizing
the pose of the face.
And the Pj next to it is a single
logistic neuron that's going to be used
for representing whether or not we think
there's a face there.
We have a similar representation in the
lab below, where we have a representation
of the pose for a mouth and a
representation of the pose for a nose,
and we can recognize the phase by
noticing that those two representations
make consistent predictions.
So we take a vector of activities that
represents the pose of the mouth.
We multiply by matrix Tij that represents
the spatial relationship between a mouth
and a face, and we get a prediction, Ti *
Tij for the pose of the face.
We do the same thing with the nose.
We take a vector of neural activities
that represents the pose of the nose, Th.
We multiply it by the relationship
between the nose and the face and we get
another prediction for the pose of the
face.
If those two predictions agree, there's a
face there, because the nose and the
mouth are in the right spacial
relationship and that's very unlikely
without there being a face there.
What we're doing here is inverse computer
graphics.
In computer graphics, if you knew the
pose of the face, you could now compute
by using the inverse of Tij, the pose of
the mouth and similarly for the nose.
So in computer graphics you're going from
poses of larger things to poses of their
parts.
In computer vision, you need to go from
the poses of the parts to the poses of
larger things and you need to check
consistency when you do that.
Now if we can get a neural net to
represent these pose vectors, as vectors
of neural activity, then we get a very
nice property.
Spatial relationships can then be
modelled as linear operations.
That makes it very easy to learn
hierarchy visual entities,
and it also makes it very easy to
generalize across viewpoints.
So, what's going to happen when we make
small changes in viewpoint is the pose
vectors, those vectors of neural
activities are all going to change.
What's going to be invariant is the
weights.
It was the weights that represented the
relationship between the part from the
hole, like Tij on the previous slide, and
those don't depend on viewpoint.
So we want to get the invariant
properties of a shape into the weights.
And we want to have the pose vectors in
the activities,
because when we change viewpoint, all
those pose vectors are going to change.
So, rather than trying to get neural
activities that are invariant to
viewpoint, which is what the pooling in
the convolutional net is trying to do.
We're going to aim to get neural
activities that are equivariant of
viewpoint.
As the pose of the object varies the
activities of the neurons vary.
That means the percept of an object, not
its label but what it looks like, is
going to change as the viewpoint changes.
I'm going to finish by giving you some
evidence that our visual systems really
do impose coordinate frames in order to
represent shapes.
This was pointed out a long time ago by a
great psychologist called Irvin Rock.
So if you look at this shape and I tell
you it's a country, most people don't
know which country it is.
They look at it, and they think it looks
a bit like Australia, but it's so sort,
sort of mirror image of Australia,
but it's not really a familiar country at
all.
If you tell them where the top is, that
it's that way up, they immediately
recognize that's it's Africa.
If they knew what coordinate frame to
impose on it, it immediately becomes a
familiar shape.
Similarly, if I give you a shape like
this one, you can perceive it as a square
or you can perceive it as a diamond.
Those are two completely different
percepts.
What you know about the shape is totally
different depending on which way you
perceive it.
So for example, if you perceive it as a
tilted square, you're acutely sensitive
to whether the angles are right angles.
If you perceive it as an upright diamond,
you're not sensitive to that at all.
The angles could be 5 degrees off and you
wouldn't notice it, but you are sensitive
to something else.
If you perceive it as an upright diamond,
you're acutely sensitive to whether the
corner on the left and the corner of the
right are at the same height.
And you'll probably notice now that, in
this figure, they're very slightly
different heights.
These kind of demonstrations are
evidence, that in order to represent
shapes we impose coordinate frames on
them.
Because when you're looking at that
square or diamond, it's the same thing
you're looking at, but the percept's
totally different depending on what
coordinate frame you impose.