In this video, I'm going to talk about
some exciting recent work, which I think
will go a long way towards answering the
question how do you settle those
hyper-parameters in a neural network?
This recent work uses a different kind of
machine learning to help us decide what
values to use for hyper-parameters.
In other words, it's using machine
learning to replace the graduate student
who fiddles around with all these
different settings of the
hyper-parameters to find out what works.
It relies on a way of modeling smooth
functions called Gaussian processes,
which I had always thought of as
inadequate for doing things like speech
and vision and I still think they are
inadequate for that.
But when you're in a domain where you
don't have much prior knowledge and the
only thing that you can really appeal to
is that you expect similar inputs to have
similar outputs, then Gaussian processes
are ideal.
And that's the domain we're in when we're
fiddling around with vectors of
hyper-parameters hoping to find a vector
of hyper-parameters that works well.
So, for example is the number of hidden
units, the number of layers, the weight
penalty,
whether it's used drop out or not. Those
are all hyper-parameters and different
combinations of them work well together.
So this is a very hard space to explore
by hand.
It's very easy when we're exploring by
hand to fail to notice things.
Gaussian processes are very good at
noticing trends in the data and they
provide a very good way of finding good
sets of hyper-parameters if you have
enough computers.
One of the commonest reasons that people
give for not using neural networks is
that it requires a lot of skill to set
the hyper-parameters.
This is actually a pretty good reason.
If you don't have much experience, it's
easy to get stuck using a completely
wrong value for one of the
hyper-parameters, and then nothing works.
You have to set things like the number of
layers,
the number of units per layer,
what types of units to use,
the weight penalty, the learning rate,
the momentum, and so on and so on.
If you use a learning rate that's 100
times too big or 100 times too small,
your network simply won't work.
One way to approach this is to do a naive
grid search.
That is, for each of these
hyper-parameters, you make a list of
alternative values and then you try all
possible combinations of values.
You can see that this is going to blow
up.
If you have more than a few
hyper-parameters,
you're going to end up with many more
combinations than you can possibly try.
It turns out that there's something
that's considerably better than doing a
naive grid search.
We can just sample random combinations.
That is for each hyper-parameter, we make
a list of alternatives and then we pick
one thing randomly from each list.
The reason that's better is because some
of the hyper-parameters won't have much
effect and others will have a lot of
effect.
And what we don't want to do is exactly
repeat the settings of the
hyper-parameters that have a lot of
effect for different settings of
hyper-parameters that don't have much
effect.
We don't learn much that way.
In a grid search, you'll have several
points along each axis that are identical
for all the other parameters.
And so, if moving along that axis of the
grid search makes no difference, you've
replicated the same experiment many times
and haven't learned anything about the
other parameters.
There's something you can do that's much
better than random combinations,
and basically it amounts to saying, let's
use machine learning to simulate the
graduate student who is trying to decide
what the hyper-parameter should be.
So, instead of using random combinations,
we look at the results we've got so far
and try and predict what combinations are
likely to work well.
That is, we have to predict regions of
the hyper-parameter space, in which we
expect to get good results.
It's not sufficient just to say how well
we expect to do.
We also have to have an idea of the
uncertainty.
We might, for example, have a region,
where we expect to do about the same as
we're currently doing,
but maybe we would do much better.
In that case, it would be worth going and
exploring that region.
It's even worth exploring regions where
we expect to do worse,
but we might just do a lot better.
Now we're going to assume that the amount
of computation involved in evaluating one
setting of the hyper-parameters is huge.
It involves training a big neura; network
on a huge data set and it might take
several days on a big computer.
Relative to that amount of work, building
a model to predict how well a setting of
the hyper-parameters will do, given all
the settings we've experimented with so
far is much less work.
And so it's going to require much less
computation to fit the predictive model
to the results of the experiments we've
seen so far than it is to run a single
experiment.
So what kind of model are we going to use
for predicting the results of future
experiments?
It turns out there's a kind of model I
haven't talked about in the course called
Gaussian process models.
Basically, all these models do is assume
that similar inputs give similar outputs.
They don't have any more sophisticated
prior than that,
but they're very good at using that prior
in an effective way.
So if you don't know much about what you
expect hyper-parameters could do, a weak
prior like that is probably the best you
can do.
Gaussian processes are able to learn for
each input dimension what the appropriate
scale is for measuring similarity.
So for example, if the number of hidden
units could be 200 or it could 300,
the question is are those similar number
or are those very different numbers?
Should we expect the results we get with
200 to be very similar to the results we
get with 300 or should we expect them to
be very different?
If we don't know anything about neural
nets, initially we have no idea, but we
could look at the results of experiments
so far.
And if experiments with 200 and
experiments with 300 tend to give very
similar answers when you take into
account the other differences between the
experiments,
then 200 is probably similar to 300.
And so, we set a scale for that dimension
such that you need differences of much
more than that to expect to get very
different results.
Now, it's important that Gaussian
processes models do more than just
predicting the expected outcome of a
particular experiment.
That is how well the neural net that we
train will do on a validation set.
In addition to predicting a mean value
for how well they expect the neural
network to do, they predict a
distribution,
they predict the variance.
They're called Gaussian processes because
their predictions are Gaussian.
When they're making a prediction for new
settings of hyper-parameters that are
close to several consistent settings that
we've already run, so we know the answer.
The predictions will tend to be fairly
sharp, that is well have low variance,
but when they are predictions for
experiments with hyper-parameters that
are very different from in setting the
hyper-parameters we'd experimented it
with so far,
the predictions made by Gaussian process
models will have very high variance.
So here's quite a good strategy for using
Gaussian processes to decide what to try
next.
So remember, we have one kind of learning
model, which is a big neural network that
takes a long time to route,
and we're trying to figure out a good
setting of the hyper-parameters to try
next.
We have a different kind of machine
learning algorith, called a Gaussian
process, that's looking at the results of
the experiments we've done so far and
trying to predict for some proposed new
setting of the hyper-parameters How well
the neural network would do and also how
unsure that prediction is?
So what we're going to do is we're going
to keep track of the hyper-parameters
that have worked best so far.
That is a single setting of all the
hyper-parameters that gave us the neural
net with the highest performance so far.
Now, when we run the next experiment, our
best setting so far might be replaced by
the new experiment because it gives
better performances in neural net or it
might stay the same.
So since we're going to substitute the
results of the new experiment it is
better than anything we've seen so far,
our best setting so far can only improve.
So here's a good strategy for what
setting of the hyper-parameters to try
next.
We pick a setting of the
hyper-parameters,
such that the expected improvement in our
best setting is big.
We don't worry about the fact that we
might do an experiment that leads to a
really bad result,
because if it gets a really bad result,
we won't replace our best so far with
this new experiment.
Also, when learn something.
This is a phenomenon that managers of
hedge funds know about.
I often tell the client if the fund goes
up, I'll take 3% of your profits.
If the fund goes down, you lose.
Now that's a crazy thing for a client to
agree to, because that gives the hedge
fund manager huge incentive for taking
huge risks, because he has no significant
answer.
But, for finding hyper-parameters that
work well, it's a sensible strategy.
So, consider these three predictions, A,
B, and C.
We're going to suppose that A, B, and C
are different settings of the
hyper-parameters that have not been tried
and those green Gaussians are the
prediction of our Gaussian process model
for how well each of those setting would
do.
For setting A, the mean is well below our
current best so far and there's only
moderate variance.
For setting B, the mean is closer to our
best so far,
but since there isn't much variance,
there really isn't that much upside.
For setting C, the mean is actually lower
than for setting B, but because it's high
variance there's a big upside.
We're going to take the area under
Gaussian C that's above the red line and
we're going to take the moment of that
area above the red line and that's the
thing we're looking for the matching
margin and you can see that C has a much
bigger moment than B or A.
It may only have the same area as B above
the line,
but some of that area is much further
above the line,
so we might get a very big win if we try
setting C.
So that's the one our policy would tell
us to pick here.
Here's the worst part,
B is intermediate and c is the best bet.
So how well does this work?
Well, if you got the resources to run a
lot of experiments, it's much better than
a person of finding good combinations of
the hyper-parameters.
The policy I gave you so far is a
strictly sequential policy that assumes
that it can see all of the experiments
run so far,
but there's no reason why you shouldn't
make it a bit more complicated and run a
whole bunch of experiments in parallel.
Using a Gaussian process model to predict
how well a particular setting of the
hyper-parameters will do is sensible,
because it's not the kind of task we're
good at.
It's not like visional speech, and it's
not clear that there's a lot of
complicated structure to be found in the
data.
It may be that the only real structure is
that things are smooth and they have some
scale.
Also, a person can't keep in mind the
results of 50 different experiments, to
see what they predict.
If you're doing all this by hand, you
might just fail to notice that all of
your good results had very small learning
rates, and all of your really bad results
had very big learning rates,
because you're attending to lots of other
things that you're varying.
A Gaussian process model would not miss a
trend like that.
One final reason why Gaussian process
models are a very good way of setting
hyper-parameters is they're much less
likely than a person to cheat.
Typically when we're doing research, we
want to compare a new method that we
thought of with some old or standard
method,
and there's a very strong tendency to
work harder to find good hyperparameters
for our new method than for the stupid
old method.
That's why when you compare methods, you
should really compare the results got by
different groups,
where for each method, the results are
produced by the group that believes in
that method.
If we use Gaussian process models to
search for good sets of hyper-parameters,
they're going to do just as hard a search
for the type of model we don't believe in
as they are for the type of model we do
believe in.