In this video we'll look in more detail
at what happens when a neural network is
discriminatorily fine tuned after it's
first been pre-trained as a stack of
Boltzmann machines.
What we'll see is that the weights in the
lower layers hardly change at all.
But that nevertheless these tiny changes
make a big difference in the
classification performance of the neural
net, because they put the decision
boundaries in the right places.
We also see that the effect of
pre-training is to make deeper networks
more effective than shallower ones.
Without pre-training it's often the other
way around.
Finally, I give a fairly general argument
about why it makes sense to start by
doing generative training.
And only after this is well under way to
consider discriminative training.
So now we're going to look at some work
done in Yoshua Bengio's lab, examining
what happens during fine tuning after a
net's been generatively pre-trained.
If you look on the left, there's the
receptive fields in the first hidden
layer of feature detectors, after the
generative pre-training but before the
fine tuning.
Then on the right, there's the same
receptive fields after the fine-tuning
then you'll see almost nothing has
changed.
Nevertheless, the changes helped with
discrimination.
Here's an example of how pre-training
reduces the test errors for networks with
one hidden left.
The task was discriminating between
digits in a very large set of distorted
digits.
And you can see that after the back
propagation fine tuning, the networks
with pre-training almost always did
better than the networks without
pre-training.
The effect gets even bigger, if you use
deeper networks.
So here you can see that there's
basically no overlap between the two
distributions.
And the deep networks with pre-training
have got better than the shallow
networks, and the deep networks without
pre-training have got worse than the
shallow networks.
This is showing you the classification
error and the variation classification
error as you change the number of layers
when you're not doing pre-training.
And you can see that two layers appears
to be best.
And by the time you've got four layers,
you're doing considerably worse.
By contrast, if you use pre-training,
four layers is better than two layers.
There's much less variation and DR is
lower.
This is a visualization made with Teeson
of what happens to the weights during
training for both pretrained and
non-pretrained networks and they are all
plotted in the same space but you can see
they form two distinct classes in
networks.
One's at the top and that works without
pretraining and the ones at the bottom
and that works with pretraining.
Each point shows a model in function
space.
It's no use comparing weight vectors
because two nets might differ by having
two of the hidden units swapped round.
So they behave exactly the same way, but
the weights would look very different.
In order to compare them, you have to
compare the functions of the
implementation.
And a way to do that is to have a suite
of test cases and look at the outputs the
networks produce on those test cases.
And then concatenate those outputs into
one great long vector.
And so if two networks produce very
similar outputs for all the test cases,
that concatenated vector will be very
similar for the two networks.
Now you take those concatenated output
vectors and you plot those in 2D using
t-SNE.
The colors show the stages of training so
if you look at the networks at the top,
there's an initial blob in dark blue.
And then you can see that it's all moving
roughly the same direction.
In other words, the networks after one
epoch of learning are all more similar to
one another then they are to the initial
networks.
That's even more pronounced with the
pre-trained networks at the bottom.
So the color tells you which epoch you're
in.
The trajectories at the top without
pre-training show that different networks
end up in different places in function
space.
And they're quite widely spread.
The trajectories of the bottom show that
with pre-training, you end up in a quite
different region of function space.
And the networks tend to be more similar
to one another.
But the main point is there's no overlap.
The kinds of solutions you find, if you
pre-train the networks generatively, are
just qualitatively different from the
kinds of solutions you find if you start
with small random words.
The last thing I want to say in this
video is to explain why pre-training
makes sense.
So let's imagine that the way we
generated pairs of an image and a label
was by taking the stuff in the real
world, using that to generate an image,
for example by taking a photograph of
something.
And then having generated the image we
attached a label to it that didn't depend
on the stuff in the world.
So contingent on the image itself, the
stuff in the world is relevant the label
thus depends on the pixels in the image
That would be the case for example if the
label told us whether the top left pixel
was similar to the bottom right pixel.
Now if we generated images that way, then
it would make sense to try and learn a
mapping from images to labels.
Because the labels depend directly on the
images but actually, it's more plausible
that the way we generate image label
pairs are by there being stuff in the
world that gives rise to the image.
And the reason the image has the name it
has is because of the stuff in the world,
not because of the pixels in the image.
So you see a cow.
You take a photograph.
And you call that a photograph of a cow,
because you were looking at a cow when
you took it.
Now the point is, there's a high
bandwidth from the stuff in the world to
the image.
And there's a low bandwidth from the
stuff in the world to the label.
For example if I just say cow, you don't
know whether the cow is upside down,
whether it was brown or black and white,
whether it was alive or dead, how big it
was, what else was in the image, whether
it was facing you or facing away from
you.
One of those things aren't conveyed by
the label.
If you see an image with thousands and
thousands of pixels, you typically know
all of those things.
You get much, much more information about
the causes of an image by looking at the
image then you do by looking at the label
of the image.
So in that situation, where there's a
high bandwidth pathway from the world to
the image, and a low bandwidth image from
the world to the label, because the label
typically contains very few bits.
It makes much more sense to try and
recover the label by first inverting the
high boundary pathway to get back to the
stuff in the world that caused the image.
And then having recovered the stuff in
the world that caused the image, to
decide what label it would be given.
So that's a much more plausible model of
how we assign names to things in images.
And that justifies having a pre-training
phase where you try and go from the image
to its underlying causes, followed by a
discriminative phase where you try and go
from those underlying causes to the
label.
And perhaps you slightly fine tune the
mapping from the image to the underlying
causes.