In this video I'm going to describe how
to use an RBM to model real value data.
The idea is that we make the visible
units.
Instead of being binary stochastic units,
the linear units with Gaussian noise.
When we do this, we get problems with
learning.
And it turns out a good solution to those
problems is to then make the hidden units
be rectified linear units.
With linear Gaussian units for the
visible, and rectified linear units for
the hiddens, it's quite easy to learn a
restricted Boltzmann machine that makes a
good model of real value data.
We first used restricted Boltzmann
machines with the images of handwritten
digits.
For those images.
Intermediate intensities caused by a
pixel being only partially inked can be
modelled quite well by probabilities,
that is numbers between one and zero that
are actually the probability of a
logistical unit being on.
So we treat partially inked pixels.
As having a probability of being inked.
This is incorrect but it works quite
well.
However it won't work for real images.
In a real image the intensity of a pixel
is almost always, almost exactly the
average of its neighbors.
So its got a very high probability of
being very close to that average and a
very small probability of being a little
further away.
And you can't achieve that with a
logistic unit.
Mean field logistic units are unable to
represent things like the intensity is
69. but very unlikely to be 71. or 67. So
we need some other kind of unit.
The obvious thing to use is a linear unit
with Gaussian norms.
So we model pixels as Gaussian variables.
We can still use alternating, get
sampling, to run the Markoff chain
required for the cross-divergence
learning.
But we need to use a much smaller
learning range, otherwise it will tend to
blow up.
The equation looks like this.
The first term on the right hand side, is
a kind of parabolic containing function.
It stops things blowing out.
So determining that sum contributed by
the Ith visible unit is parabolic in
shape.
It looks like this.
It's parabola with its minimum at the
bias of the Ith unit.
And as the Ith unit departs from that
value, we add energy quadratically.
So that tries to keep the Ith visible
unit close to VI.
The interactive term between the visible
and the hidden units looks like this.
And if you differentiate that with
respect to the I, you can see that you
get a constant.
It's the sum over all J, of H J W I J
divided by sigma I.
So that term with its constant gradient
looks like this.
And when you add together, that top down
contribution to the energy is linear, and
the parabolic containment function.
You'll get a parabolic function, but with
the mean shifted away from BI.
And how much it shifted depends on the
slope of that blue line.
So the effect of the hidden units is just
to push the mean to one side.
It's easy to write down an energy
function like this.
And it's easy to take derivatives off it.
But when we try learning with it, we
often get problems.
There were a lot of reports in the
literature that people could not get
these Gaussian binary RBM's to work.
And it is indeed extremely hard to learn
tight variances for the visible units.
It took us a long time to figure out why
it's so hard to learn those visible
variances.
This picture helps.
If you consider the effect that visible
unit I has on hidden unit J.
When visible unit I has a strong standard
deviation sigma I, that has the effect of
exaggerating the bottom up weights.
That's because we need to measure the
activity of I in units of its standard
deviation.
So when the standard deviation is small,
we need to multiply the weight by a lot.
If you look at the top down effect of J
on I, that's multiplied by sigma I.
So when the standard deviation of a
visible unit I is very small, the bottom
up effects get exaggerated, on the top
down effects get attenuated.
The result is that we have a conflict
where either we have bottom up effects
that are much too big or top down effects
that are much too small.
And the result is that the hidden units
tend to saturate and be firmly on or off
all the time, and this will mess up
learning.
So the solution is to have many more
hidden units than visible units.
That allows small weights between the
visible and hidden units to have big top
down effects, because of so many hidden
units.
But of course, we really need the number
of hidden units to change as that
standard deviation sigma I gets smaller.
And on the next slide, we'll see how we
can achieve that.
I'm going to introduce stepped sigmoid
units.
The idea is we make many copies of each
stacastic binary hidden unit.
All the copies have the same weights, and
the same bias that's learned B But in
addition to that adapted bias B they have
a fixed offset to the bias.
The first unit has an offset of -1.5. The
second unit has an offset of -1.5. The
third one has an offset of minus -2.5,
and so on.
If you have a whole family of sigmoid
units like that, with the bias changed by
one between neighbouring members of the
family, the response code looks like
this.
If the total in product is very low, none
of them are turned on.
As it increases, the number that get
turned on increases linearly.
This means that as the standard deviation
on the previous slide gets smaller, the
number of copies of each hidden unit that
get turned on gets bigger and we achieved
just the effect we wanted, which we get
more top-down effect to drive these
visible units that have small standard
deviations.
Now it's quite expensive to use a big
population of binary stochastic units
with offset biases, because for each one
of them, we need to put the total input
through the logistic function, but we can
make some fast approximations which work
just as well.
So the sum of the activities of a whole
bunch of sigmoid units with offset
ballasts, which is shown in that
summation.
Is approximately equal to log of one plus
E to the X and that in turn is
approximately equal to the maximum of
nought and X.
And we can add some noise to the X if we
want.
So the first term in the equation looks
like this.
The second term looks like that.
And you can see that the sum of all those
sigmoids in the first term will be a
curve like that.
And we can approximate that by a linear
threshold unit that has a value of zero
unless it's above threshold.
In which case its value increases
linearly with its input.
Contrastive Divergence Learning works
well for the sum of a bunch of stochastic
logistic units with offset biases.
And in that case.
You get a noise variance that's equal to
the logistic function.
But the output of that sum.
Alternatively we can use that green curve
and use rectified linear units.
They're much faster to compute because
you don't need to go through the logistic
many times.
And can trust divergence works just fine
with those.
One nice property of rectified linear
units is that if they have a bias of
zero, they exhibit scale equivariance.
This is a very nice property to have for
images.
What scale equivariance means is that if
you take an image x and you multiply all
the pixel intensities by a scalar a.,
then the representation of ax in the
rectified linear units would be just a
times the representation of x.
In other words, when we scale up all the
intensities in the image, we scale up the
activities of all the hidden units but
all the ratios stay the same.
Rectified linear units aren't fully
linear because if you add together two
images, the representation you get is not
the sum of the representations of each
unit separately.
This property of scale equivariance is
quite similar to the property of
translational equivariance, convolutional
nets off.
So if we ignore the pooling for now, in a
convolution on that, if we shift an image
and look at the representation,
the representation of a shifted image is
just a shifted version of the
representation of the unshifted image.
So in a convolutional net without
pooling, translations of the input just
flow through the layers of the net
without really affecting anything.
The representation of every layer is just
translated.