So in this lecture,
we're going to talk about dynamic
arrays and amortized analysis.
In this video we're going to
talk about dynamic arrays.
So the problem with static arrays is,
well, they're static.
Once you declare them,
they don't change size,
and you have to determine
that size at compile time.
So one solution is what are called
dynamically-allocated arrays.
There you can actually allocate the array,
determining the size of
that array at runtime.
So that gets allocated
from dynamic memory.
So that's an advantage.
The problem is,
what if you don't know the maximum size
at the time you're allocating the array?
A simple example,
you're reading a bunch of numbers.
You need to put them in an array.
But you don't know how
many numbers there'll be.
You just know there'll be some mark at the
end that says we're done with the numbers.
So, how big do you make it?
Do you make it 1,000 big?
But then what if there are 2,000 elements?
Make it 10,000 big?
But what if there are 20,000 elements?
So, a solution to this.
There's a saying that says all
problems in computer science can
be solved by another level of indirection.
And that's the idea here.
We use a level of indirection.
Rather than directly storing
a reference to the either static or
dynamically allocated array,
we're going to store a pointer to
our dynamically allocated array.
And that allows us then
to update that pointer.
So if we start adding more and
more elements, when we add too many,
we can go ahead and allocate a new array,
copy over the old elements,
get rid of the old array, and
then update our pointer to that new array.
So these are called dynamic arrays or
sometimes they're called resizable arrays.
And this is distinct from
dynamically allocated arrays.
Where we allocate an array, but once it's
allocated it doesn't change size.
So a dynamic array is
an abstract data type, and
basically you want it to
look kind of like an array.
So it has the following operations,
at a minimum.
It has a Get operation,
that takes an index and
returns you the element at that index, and
a Set operation, that sets an element at
a particular index to a particular value.
Both of those operations
have to be constant time.
Because that kind of what
it means to be an array,
is that we have random access with
constant time to the elements.
We can PushBack so that adds a new element
to the array at the end of the array.
We can remove an element
at a particular index.
And that'll shuffle down
all the succeeding ones.
And finally, we can find out how
many elements are in the array.
How do we implement this?
Well, we're going to store arr,
which is our dynamically-allocated array.
We're going to store capacity,
which is the size of that
dynamically-allocated array,
how large it is.
And then size is the number of elements
that we're currently using in the array.
Let's look at an example.
So let's say our dynamically
allocated array has a capacity of 2.
But we're not using any elements
in it yet, so it's of size 0.
And arr then points to that
dynamically allocated array.
If we do a PushBack of a,
that's going to go ahead and
put a into the array and update the size.
We now push b, it's going to put b
into the array and update the size.
Notice now the size is equal to
the capacity which means this
dynamically allocated array is full.
So if we get asked to do another PushBack,
we've got to go allocate a new
dynamically-allocated array.
We're going to make that larger,
in this case it's of size 4.
And then we copy over each of the elements
from the old array to the new array.
Once we've copied them over, we can go
ahead and update our array pointer to
point to this new dynamically allocated
array, and then dispose of the old array.
At this point now we finally have
our new dynamically allocated array,
that has room to push another element,
so we push in c.
We push in d, if there is room
we put it in, update the size.
And now if we try and
push another element,
again we have a problem, we're too big.
We can allocate a new array.
In this case,
we're going to make it of size 8.
We'll talk about how you determine
that size somewhat later.
And then copy over a, b, c, and
d, update the array pointer,
de-allocate the old array, and
now we have room we can push in e.
So that's how dynamic arrays work.
Let's look at some of the implementations
of the particular API methods.
Get is fairly simple.
So we just check and see, we're going to
assume for the sake of argument,
that we are doing 0-based indexing here.
So if we want to Get(i), we first
check and make sure, is i in a range?
That is, is it non-negative, and
is it within the range
from 0 to size i minus 1?
Because if it's less than 0 or
it's greater or equal to size,
it's out of range, that will be an error.
If we're in range then
we just return index
i from the dynamically allocated array.
Set is very similar.
Check to make sure out index is in bounds,
and then if it is,
update index i of the array to val.
PushBack is a little more complicated.
So, let's actually skip the if
statement for now and just say,
let's say that there is empty
space in our dynamic array.
In that case, we just set array at
size to val and then increment size.
If, however, we're full,
we're not going to do that yet,
if size is equal to capacity,
then we go ahead and allocate a new array.
We're going to make it twice the capacity,
and then we go through a for loop,
copying over every one of the elements
from the existing array to the new array.
We free up the old array and
then set array to the new one.
At that point then,
we've got space and we go ahead and
set the size element and
then increment size.
Remove's fairly simple.
Check that our index is in bounds and
then go ahead through a loop,
basically copying over successive
elements and then decrementing the size.
Size is simple, will just return size.
There are common implementations for
these dynamic arrays and
C++'s vector class is
an example of a dynamic array.
And there, notice it uses
C++ operator overloading, so
you can use the standard array
syntax of left brackets,
to either read from or
write to an element.
Java has an ArrayList.
Python has the list.
And there is no static arrays in Python.
All of them are dynamic.
What's the runtime?
We saw Get and Set are O(1),
as they should be.
PushBack is O(n).
Although we're going to see
that's only the worst case.
And most of the time actually,
when you call PushBack, it's not
having to do the expensive operation, that
is, the size is not equal to capacity.
For now, though,
we're just going to say that it's O(n).
We'll look at a more detailed
analysis when we get into aggregate
analysis in our next video.
Removing is O(n), because we've
gotta move all those elements.
Size is O(1).
So in summary, unlike static arrays,
dynamic arrays are dynamic.
That is, they can be resized.
Appending a new element to a dynamic
array is often constant time, but
it can take O(n).
We're going to look at a more
nuanced analysis in the next video.
And some space is wasted.
In our case, if we're resizing by a factor
of two, at most half the space is wasted.
If we were making our new
array three times as big,
then we can waste two-thirds of our space.
If we're only making it 1.5 as big,
then we would waste less space.
It's worth noting dynamic array can also
be resized smaller, that's possible too.
It's worth thinking about what if
we resized our array to a smaller
dynamic array as soon as we got
under one-half utilization?
And it turns out we can come up
with a sequence of operations that
gets to be quite expensive.
In the next video, we're going to
talk about amortized analysis.
And in particular, we're going to look at
one method called the aggregate method.