Let's go back to the dynamic array.
So are there alternatives
to doubling the array size?
Right, we doubled each time.
What happens if we didn't double?
Well we could use some
different growth factor.
So for instance, we could use 2.5.
So grow the array by more than two,
or grow the array by less than two.
As long as we used some constant
multiplicative factor, we'd be fine.
The question is can we
use a constant amount?
Can we add by a particular amount,
like, let's say, 10 each time?
And the answer is really, no.
And the reason is, as the array got
bigger and bigger, and we have to resize
every ten times,
we just don't have enough time
to accumulate work in order
to actually do the movement.
Let's look at another way.
Let's look at an aggregate method.
Let's say c sub i is the cost
of the i'th insertion.
We're going to define that as one, for
putting in the i'th element,
plus either i-1 if the i-1'th
insertion makes the
dynamic array full.
So that is if i-1 is a multiple
of 10 and it's 0 otherwise.
By the definition of aggregate method which is
just the sum of the total costs divided
by n and that's n plus again that's
the one summed n times is just n plus
the summation from one to (n-1)/10 of 10j.
That is just the multiples of 10.
All the way up to but not including n.
So 10, 20, 30, 40 and so on.
All that divided by n.
Well, we can pull the 10
out of that summation so
it's just 10 x the summation
j = 1 to (n- 1)/10 of j.
So that's just numbers 1, 2, 3, 4,
and so on, all the way up to (n- 1)/10.
That is O(n squared).
That summation.
So we've got n+10 times O(N^2)/n=O(n^2)/n=O(n).
So this shows that if we use a constant
amount to grow the dynamic
array each time that we end up with
an amortized cost for push back of O(n)
rather than O(1).
So it's extremely important
to use a constant factor.
So in summary we can
calculate the amortized cost
in the context of
a sequence of operations.
Rather than looking at a single operation
in its worst case we look at a totality
of a sequence of operations.
We have three ways to do the analysis.
The aggregate method,
where we just do the brute-force sum based
on the definition of the amortized cost.
We can use the banker's method
where we actually use tokens and
we're saving them conceptually
in the data structure.
Or the physicist's method where
we define a potential function,
and look at the change in that potential.
Nothing changes in the code.
We're only doing runtime analysis, so
the code doesn't actually
store any tokens at all.
That's an important thing to remember.
That is dynamic arrays and
amortized analysis.