Hi, in this last lesson of
the Advanced Shortest Paths module,
we will study the contraction
hierarchies algorithm.
In the previous lessons, we've learned
the idea of bidirectional search.
And we've studied the bidirectional
Dijkstra's algorithm,
which can be thousands of times faster
when applied to social network drafts.
However, for road networks, it typically
gives just roughly 2x speedup.
And in this lecture, we'll start an
algorithm that gives much better speedup,
thousands of times and more.
And the idea for
such speedup is the following.
Long-distance trips go
mostly through highways.
For example, if you consider this
long trip by car from San Francisco
to New York, and if you look at
the navigational directions,
then you'll see that basically,
you need to first merge into the highway.
Then you need to merge from that highway
into a bigger interstate highway,
go through it, then exit to a smaller
highway, and then exit to a street, and
then get to your address.
And this is the general case.
When you need to get from some point A to
point B, you need to first merge from
streets to a highway, then merge from
there into an even bigger highway,
and repeat that maybe several times,
and then start exiting.
You exit to a smaller highway,
then to an even smaller highway,
and then exit to your street,
and then go to your address.
And so less important roads
merge into more important roads.
And there is some kind of hierarchy of
those roads, which is obvious to humans.
But we don't know that hierarchy
when we're given the graph.
So the idea is to use the structure of the
shortest paths in the real road networks.
And this will allow us to actually
avoid scanning many small roads,
many not important vertices in the graph.
because if you go from San Francisco to
New York, then most probably you don't
need to go through small streets
somewhere in Las Vegas or Chicago.
Most of the way,
you'll be going through a big highway.
And you won't go into small streets
in the middle of your trip.
And there are algorithms which are based
on this idea, Highway Hierarchies and
Transit Node Routing by Sanders and
Schultes.
And transit node routing is one of
the fastest known algorithms for
shorter paths in real road networks.
They can be millions of times faster
than the classical Dijkstra algorithm.
But those algorithms are pretty complex.
And in this lecture, we'll study
the contraction hierarchies algorithm,
which is at least thousands of times and
more faster than Dijkstra.
But it is pretty simple, and
you will be able to implement it as
part of the project of this module.
And you will be even
able to play with it and
implement different, your own ideas and
heuristics to improve it even further.
So the idea of the contraction
hierarchies algorithm
is to order the nodes by importance.
Instead of ordering the highways by
their importance, we order the nodes.
And the idea is that the importance
of the nodes on your
shortest path should first increase and
then decrease back.
And for example,
these could be points where a highway
merges into another highway.
And it can't really get away
without passing through this node.
And then if this is true that
the importance first increases and
then decreases back, we can use
bidirectional search from source to
the most important node
on our shortest path.
This is a forward search.
And then from the target to the most
important node on our shortest path,
this is a backward search.
And then when they meet in the common
middle point which has the biggest
importance on the path, then we have
the path between source and the target.
So the idea is about which nodes
are important, which are not.
First, many shortest paths
involve important nodes.
If you look at this map of the US,
you will see that there are many,
many big routes coming
out from big cities.
And that's no coincidence.
And as most of the shortest paths,
which are long-distance
go through these big roads,
they also go through these big cities.
So big cities are important nodes.
And many shortest paths go
through those important nodes.
Another idea is that the important
nodes are somewhat spread around.
Because in each region of the map,
we have some big cities and
capital of the state or
some bigger city in the state,
which is important node, such that many
shortest paths again go through it.
It can't just have one single important
node, and everything else is unimportant.
You always have them spread
out through all the map.
And another thing is that important nodes
are sometimes completely unavoidable.
For example, for many, many different
source points in San Francisco
on the left shore and for many target
points in Oakland on the right shore,
there is no other way to get from
the source to this target via some
shortest path and
bypass this Treasure Island in between.
And so this Treasure Island
node is very important
because you cannot just avoid
it with the shortest path.
And the contraction hierarchies algorithm
uses this scheme of shortest paths with
preprocessing.
When you don't just get a graph, and
then instantly start to answer queries,
how long does it take to get from A to B?
Now instead you first get the graph and
you get some time to preprocess it.
It can be a long process.
It can take a few hours or even days.
But then when you're ready, and you've
saved the results of your preprocessing,
you can answer the queries for
distance and shortest paths much faster.
And you work with this
preprocessed graph to do that.
And this is a very practical case.
For example in Google Maps or
in Yanix Maps, that's what people do.
They first preprocess the graph.
And then they push the preprocessed
graph and the algorithm into production.
And then they can answer your
queries millions of times faster
without you noticing it.
And it doesn't matter that we have to
spend a few hours or a few days before
pushing the graph into production
because it happens behind the scenes.
And so the general schema is that you
prerpocess the graph then implement
a special algorithm to find distance and
shortest path in this preprocessed graph.
And then you reconstruct the shortest
path in the initial graph and
show it to the user somehow.
In the next videos, we will first
study how the preprocessing works for
the contraction hierarchies.
Then we'll study how to implement
the distance and shortest path queries.
We'll prove the correctness
of the overall algorithm.
And we'll point out some very important
optimizations of this algorithm.
And in the end, we will understand
how we can actually measure
the importance of the nodes
that this algorithm uses and
how to implement this
importance in your algorithm.