Hi, in this video we'll study how
to actually find the distance
between nodes in the augmented
graph after pre-processing it
using contraction of the nodes.
So the main idea is that we will
use Bidirectional Dijkstra.
And this Bidirectional Dijkstra
will only use some of the edges
of the augmented graph.
So you remember that when
we contracted the nodes,
we placed them from bottom to top in
the order of increasing importance.
And also in the order of contraction,
so the later the node was contracted,
the more important is this node.
And so we drew this arrow with
node order from bottom to top.
And we will consider
only the upward edges.
So for example if we need to find
the shortest path between node two and
node three in this graph,
the path will look like this.
It will go first, by edges,
which go up to some node
with the biggest importance.
For example, in this case,
it will be node 6.
And then we'll go by edges down
from that node 6, into node 3.
And to find such a path, we will use
Bidirectional Dijkstra, which we'll start
both from 2 and from 3 and from 2
it'll go by forward edges which go up.
And from 3 it'll go by backward
edges which also go up.
And then they will meet at some node and
we'll find some path which goes
first up and then goes down.
This is the general idea but
it is someone difference still
from the classical
Bidirectional Dijkstra variant.
So in the Bidirectional Dijkstra as soon
as we find some node that is process both
by the forward search and
the backward search, we stop and
compute the shortest distance.
In this case, we don't stop when some
node was processed by both searches.
We stop only when the extracted
node is already farther
than our current estimate of
the distance to the target.
This is the pseudo code code for the
function ComputeDistance which takes as
inputs service node s and target node t
and returns the distance between them.
Of course it also takes as input for
example the graph and
the reverse graph for the bidirectional
search but I just omitted those details.
Note however that you only need to store
in the graph the edges which go upwards.
So we have a node A and
a node B and an edge from A to B.
If A was contracted earlier than B,
then you need to store this edge.
But if B was contracted earlier than A,
then this edge goes downwards and so
you don't need to store this edge.
You can just delete it because it
won't be used at all in the queries.
And so, you don't need to
store it in the pre-process,
in the augmented graph at all.
We start with initializing
variable estimate which will
store our current estimate of the distance
between the source and the target.
And we initialize it with plus
infinity because currently,
we don't know of any path
between source and target.
Then we do the standard initialization
of the bidirectional Dijkstra data.
We fill the arrays with distance
estimates for the forward search and
the backward search with plus infinities.
And we'll also set the distance in the
forward search from the source to zero.
And the distance in the backwards
search from the target also to zero.
And also have the lists of
the processed nodes for
the forward and the backward search.
Then we'll have the main loop and
this loop goes while we still have some
nodes to process, either in the forward
Dijkstra or in the backward Dijkstra.
Which means that basically in our
priority queue that we use for
the Djikstra algorithm,
there still are some nodes.
Either in the queue for the forward
Djikstra search or in the queue for
the backward Djikstra search.
While there are still such nodes,
we try to extract node in the forward
search if there is still something
in the queue for the forward search.
And this node will all ready have
the distance estimate which is
equal to the distance from
source s to this node v.
So if the distance from s to v is
already bigger than the estimate
of the distance from s to t,
we don't need to process node v.
And we don't need to put it into queue and
to process the nodes which
are the successors of v.
So we only do that if the distance
estimate of v is smaller or
equal to the current estimate.
Then we process, basically we do the same,
we do in the regular Dijkstra step.
And then,
we need to also update our estimate.
So if v is processed in the reverse
search which act that by if v in proc R,
then it is processed in both searches.
Because v has just been processed
in the forward search and
it is also in the list of processed
nodes in the backward search.
So it is processed by both forward and
backward searches.
This means that its distance
estimates both in the forward and
the backward search are already equal to
the corresponding distances from s to v
and from v to t.
And so we know the length of the shortest
path going from s to t through v.
This path has length equal to
dist of v plus dist R of v.
If this length is smaller than our current
estimate of the distance between s and
t we need to update it.
And that's what we do
in this if statement.
And then we try to do
the backward Dijkstra search.
And it is completely symmetric
to what we have here for
the forward Dijkstra search, so
I don't write the code for that.
And this while loop goes and goes until
all the nodes and all the queues for
forward and backward search are processed.
And then in the end we just
return our current estimate
of the distance between source and
the target.
Now it seems that we
already know everything.
We know how to pre-process the graph
using the contraction of the node.
We also know how to implement queries
using bidirectional Dijkstra, so
are we done?
Can we actually go and
implement this algorithm?
Well of course we're not done because for
example we don't know yet
whether this algorithm works correctly or
not.
So commute distance procedure returns some
estimate of the distance between source
and the target but
is it always correct estimate?
Is it always equal to the distance between
s and t in the initial graph or not?
We don't know that.
Also, this can be distance procedure
only returns us the estimate of
the distance between source and the target
but it doesn't return the actual shortest
path between source and
the target in the initial graph.
But that's more of a technical moment.
Using the standard bidirectional Dijkstra
algorithm we can reconstruct the path
in the augmented graph between source and
target using the special RA with
the previous node in the shortest
path from source to this node.
And the same for the backward search.
And then some of the edges
could be shortcuts,
instead of the edges of the initial graph.
But then while we do the pre-processing
we should also store in the shortcut
not just the edge but also which two edges
were there before we ended the shortcut.
Now we can recursively
take the shortcut and
replace it with the two edges
that were before the shortcut.
And then if some of those two edges
are also shortcuts, we recursively
get the edges that were there before
these shortcuts were added, and so on.
And then, we will eventually reconstruct
the path in the initial graph,
which only contains the edges
of the initial graph.
And in the next video we will actually
prove that this algorithm works correctly,
that the estimate from the compute
distance procedure will always return
the correct distance between source and
the target.