Hello everybody.
Welcome back.
Today we're going to be talking
about using Big-O notation.
So the basic idea here, we're going
to be talking about how to manipulate
expressions involving Big-O and
other asymptotic notations.
And, in particular, we're going to
talk about how to use Big-O to compute
algorithm runtimes in
terms of this notation.
So recall,
we said that f(n) was Big-O of g(n).
If for
all sufficiently large inputs f(n) was
bounded above by some fixed
constant times g(n).
Which really says that f is bounded
above by some constant times g.
Now, we'd like to manipulate expressions,
we'd like to, given expressions write them in
terms of Big O in
the simplest possible manner.
So there's some common
rules you need to know.
The first rule is that multiplicative
constants can be omitted.
7n cubed is O of n cubed.
n squared over 3 is O of n squared.
The basic premise that we had when
building this idea was that we wanted to
have something that ignores
multiplicative constants.
The second thing to note is
that you have two powers of n.
The one with the larger
exponent grows faster,
so n grows asymptotically slower
than Big-O of n squared.
Root n grows slower than n,
so it's O of n.
Hopefully this isn't too bad.
What's more surprising is that
if you have any polynomial and
any exponential,
the exponential always grows faster.
So n to the fifth is O
of root two to the n.
n to the 100 is O of 1.1 to the n.
And this latter thing is something
that should surprise you a little bit.
Because n to the 100 is
a terrible runtime.
Two to the 100 is already so big that
you really can't expect to do it ever.
On the other hand,
1.1 to the n grows pretty modestly.
1.1 to the 100 is a pretty
reasonable-sized number.
On the other hand, what this really says,
is that once n gets large, maybe
100 thousand or so, 1.1 eventually takes
over, and starts beating n to the 100.
And it does so by, in fact, quite a bit.
But it doesn't really happen
until n gets pretty huge.
In a similar vein, any power of log n
grows slower than any power of n.
So log n cubed is O of root n.
n log n is O of n squared.
Finally, if you have some sum of terms
smaller terms in the sum can be omitted.
So n squared plus n.
n has a smaller rate of growth.
So this is O of n squared.
2 to the n + n to the 9th.
n to the 9th has a smaller rate of growth,
so this is O(2 to the n).
So, these are common rules for
manipulating these expressions.
Basically these are the only ones that
you'll need most of the time to write
anything in terms of Big-O
that you need.
Okay, so
let's see how this works in practice.
If we actually want to compute
runtimes using Big-O notation.
So let's look at this one algorithm again.
So we created an array.
We set the 0th element to 0 and
the first element to 1.
We then went through this loop,
where we set each element to
the sum of the previous two.
And then returned the last
element of the array.
Let's try computing this runtime
in terms of Big-O notation.
So, we're just going to run through
it operation by operation and
ask how long it takes.
First operation is we created an array,
and let's for the moment ignore
the memory management issues, assume that
it's not too hard to allocate the memory.
But let;s suppose that what your compiler
does is we actually want to zero out
all of these cells in memory and that's
going to take us a little bit of work.
Because for every cell,
basically what we have to do,
is we need to zero out that cell, we then
need to increment some counter to tell us
which cell we're working on next and
then maybe we need to do a check to
make sure that we're not at the end.
If we are at the end,
to go to the next line.
Now for every cell we have
to do some amount of work.
We have to do something like do a write,
and the comparison, and an increment.
And it's not entirely clear how
many machine operations this is.
But it's a constant amount of
work per cell in the array.
If there are n plus 1 cells.
This is O of n time,
some constant times n.
Next we set the zeroth
elements of the array of zero.
And this might just be
a simple assignment.
We might have to load a few things into
registers or do some pointer arithmetic,
but no matter whether this is one
machine operation or five or seven,
that's still going to be a constant number
of machine operations, O(1).
Similar is setting the first element
to one again, O(1) time.
Next we run through this loop, for
i running from two to n, we run through it
n minus one times, that's O(n) times.
The main thing we do in the loop is we set
the ith element of the array to the sum
of the i minus first and i minus second.
Now the lookups and the store,
those are all of the sorts of things we
had looked at, those should be O of 1.
But the addition is a bit worse.
And normally additions are constant time.
But these are large numbers.
Remember, the nth Fibonacci number
has about n over 5 digits to it,
they're very big, and
they often won't fit in the machine word.
Now if you think about what happens if
you add two very big numbers together,
how long does that take?
Well, you sort of add the tens digit and
you carry, and
you add the hundreds digit and you carry,
and add the thousands digit,
you carry and so on and so forth.
And you sort of have to do work for
each digits place.
And so the amount of work that you do should
be proportional to the number of digits.
And in this case, the number
of digits is proportional to n, so
this should take O(n) time
to run that line of code.
Finally, we have a return step, which is
a pointer arithmetic and array lookup and
maybe popping up the program stack.
And it's not quite clear how much work
that is, but it's pretty clear that
it's a constant amount of work,
it doesn't become worse as n gets larger.
So, that's O of one time.
So, now we just have to
add this all together.
O of N plus O of 1 plus O of 1 plus
O of N times through the loop times
O of N times work per time through
the loop plus O of 1, add it all together,
the dominant term here, which is the only
one we need, is the O of n times O of n.
That's O of n squared.
So this algorithm runs
in time O of n squared.
Now, we don't know exactly
what the constants are,
but O of n squared means that if we
want to finish this in a second,
you can probably handle
inputs of size maybe 30,000.
Now, depending on the computer that you
had and the compiler and all of these
messy details, maybe you can only handle
inputs of size 1,000 in a second.
Maybe you can handle inputs
the size of million in a second.
It's probably not going to be as low as
ten or as high as a billion but, I mean,
30,000's a good guess and well, it takes
work to get anything better than that.
And so, this doesn't give us an exact
answer but it's pretty good.
Okay, so
that's how you use Big-O notation.
It turns out that occasionally you
want to say a few other things.
Big O really just says that my
runtime is sort of bounded above
by some multiple of this thing.
Sometimes you want to say the reverse.
Sometimes you want to say
that I'm bounded below.
And so
there's different notation for that.
If you want to say that f is bounded below
by g, that it grows no slower than g,
you say that f(n) is Omega of g(n).
And that says that for some constant c,
f(n) is at least c times g(n),
for all large n.
Now instead of saying bounded above or
bounded below,
sometimes that you actually want to
say that they grow at the same rate.
And for
that you'd see f is Big-Theta of g(n).
Which means, that F is both Big-O of g,
and, Big-Omega of G.
Which says, up to constants, that f and
g grow at the same rate.
Finally, sometimes instead of saying that
f grows no faster than g,
you actually have to say that it
grows strictly slower than g, and for
that you say f(n) is Little-o of g(n).
And that says that, not only is
the ratio between f(n) and g(n) bounded
above by some constant, but actually this
constant can be made as small as you like.
In particular this means that
the ratio f(n) over g(n) goes to zero
as n goes to infinity.
So, these are some other notations
that you'll see now and then.
You should keep them in mind.
They're useful.
Big-O is the one that usually shows up,
because we actually want to
bound our runtimes above.
It's sort of the big, important thing,
but these guys are also useful.
So, to summarize the stuff
on asymptotic notation.
What it lets us do is ignore these
messy details in the runtime
analysis that we saw before.
It produces very clean answers that tell
us a lot about the asymptotic runtime
of things.
And these together make it very useful.
It means we're going to be using it
extensively throughout the course.
So you really ought to get used to it.
But, it does throw away a lot
of practical useful information.
So if you really want to
make your program fast,
you need to look at more than
just the Big-O runtime.
But, beyond that, we're going to use it.
With this lecture,
we basically finished the sort of
introductory material that we need.
Next lecture I'll talk to you a little bit
about sort of an overview of the rest of
the course and some our philosophy for it.
But after that, we'll really get
into the meat of the subject.
We'll start talking about key
important ways to design algorithms.
So, I hope you enjoy it.