Hello and welcome to the next lesson
of the data structures class.
It is devoted to disjoint sets.
As a first motivating example, consider
the following maze shown on the slide.
It is basically just a grid
of cells with walls between
some pairs of adjacent cells.
A natural question for
such a maze is given two points,
given two cells in this maze whether
there is a path between them.
For example for these two points for
these two cells shown on these slides
there is a path and
it is not too difficult to construct it.
Let's do this together.
So this is, we can go as follows.
And there is actually another path here,
we can also go this way.
Great.
On the other hand,
there is no path between these two points
shown on the slide and to show this
we might want to construct just a set of
all points that are reachable from B.
Let's again do this, so
let's just mark all the points
that are reachable from B.
So it is not difficult
to see that we marked
just every single point
which is reachable from B.
And we now see that A does
not belong to this set.
Which actually justifies that A is
not reachable from B in this case.
The maze problem can be easily solved
with the help of the disjoint set
data structure which supports
the following three operations.
The first operation is called MakeSet.
It takes one argument x and
it creates just a set of size
one containing this element x.
The second operation is called Find.
It takes an argument x and returns an ID
of the set that contains this element x.
Well, we expect this ID to satisfy
the following two natural properties.
If x and y, if two elements,
x and y lie in the same set,
then we expect the operation Find to
return the same ID was for x and y.
Well just because x and
y lie in the same set, and
Find returns some identifier of this set,
right?
If, on the other hand, x and
y lie in different sets,
then Find(x) should not be
equal to Find(y), right?
The last operation is called Union and
it takes two arguments, x and y.
And then it considers two sets
containing x and y, and it merges them.
In particular,
if we just called Union(x,y) and
right after this we called Find(x) and
Find(y).
Then these two call to Find operation
should return exactly the same identifier.
Just because x and y after the call
to union, lie in the same merged set.
Recall that our maze example
shows a particular point B
is not reachable from a particular
point A, we did the following.
We first constructed
the region of all cells,
reachable from this point B in our maze.
We then just checked that a, that point
a does not belong to this region.
So this was a justification of the fact
that a is not reachable from b
in our maze.
And in fact, any maze can be
partitioned into disjoint regions,
where in each region, between any
two cells there is a path, right?
And using the disjoint sets data
structure it is easy to partition any
maze into such disjoint regions.
We can do this by preprocess
the maze as follows.
We first call MakeSet for
all cells c in our maze.
This creates a separate region for
each cell.
So initially we have as many regions
as there are cells in our maze.
Then we do the following.
We go through all possible
cells in our maze.
So when a cell C is fixed,
we also go through all possible
neighbors of this cell in our maze.
We say that n is a neighbor of c
if n is an adjacent cell of c and
there is no wall between them.
So at this point c belongs to some
region and n belongs to some region and
we just discovered the fact that
there is a path between c and n.
Which means that, actually,
any cell from this region
is reachable from any cell
from this region, right?
To reflect this fact,
we just call Union(c,n).
This creates a separate set for
these two regions.
This merges these two regions, right?
So after the call to this preprocess and
procedure each region in this maze,
receives a unique ID, right?
So then to check whether a particular
cell is reachable from other cell we just
need to check whether the Find operation
returns the same for them or not.
To give another example of using
the disjoint sets data structure,
assume that we're building a network.
In each area we have four machines we
call MakeSet(1) for the first machine.
MakeSet(2) for the second machine,
and so on, so,
to reflect the fact that initially,
each machine lies in a separate set.
In particular, if we now check
whether Find(1) is equal to Find(2),
then it is false just because 1 and
2 lie in different sets.
Now, let's add a wire between the third
machine and the fourth machine.
To notify our data structures that
now 3 and 4 belong to the same set,
we call Union(3,4), okay?
Now let's introduce the fifth machine so
we do this by calling MakeSet(5)
then let's add another wire between
the second machine and the third machine.
To notify our data structure about
this event we call Union(3,2).
If we now call Find(1) and
Find(2), they should return,
these two calls should return
different values because 2 and
1, machines 2 and
1 still belong to different sets.
Okay, now we have the wire
between the machines 1 and 4.
And now yes, to notify our data structure
about this event we call Union(1,4),
and now if we check whether Find(1) is
equal to Find(2) it should return true.
Just because now 1 and 2 lie in the same
set that contains machine 1, 2, 3, and 4.
Later in this specialization,
we will learn the Kruskal algorithm,
which builds a network of a given
set of machines in an optimal way,
and uses the disjoint set
data structure essentially.