Now when we've seen a few examples of
using the disjointed set data structure
and when we formally defined it,
let's start to think about
possible ways of implementing it.
As usual we will start with a few
naive implementations that will turn
out to be slow on one hand, but
on the other hand they will help us to
come up with an efficient implementation.
First of all, let us simplify
our life by assuming that our n
objects are just integers from 1 to n.
This in particular will allow us to
use the subjects as indices in a race.
Okay, so
our sets are just sets of integers.
And we need to come up with a notion
of an ID, of a unique ID for each set.
So, let's use the smallest
element in each set as its ID.
In particular,
since our objects are integers, for
each element we can
store the ID of the set,
this element belongs to in
the array called smallest.
For example,
if we have the following three sets,
then in the first set the ID,
namely the smallest element is two.
In the second set the smallest element and
the only element is five.
In the third set
the smallest element is one.
Then this information is stored in
the array called smallest of size nine.
Separations MakeSet and
Find can be implemented in just
one line of code in this case.
Namely to create a singleton set
consisting of just element i,
we set smallest of i to be equal to i,
right.
To find the ID of the set
containing the element i,
we just return the value of smallest[i].
The running time of both of
these operation is constant.
Everything is not so easy with
the union operation unfortunately.
So to merge two sets containing
elements i and j, we do the following.
First we find out the ID of
the set containing the element i.
We do this by calling Find(i) and
restores the result in the variable i_id.
Then we do the same for the element j.
We call Find(j) and we store
the resulting id in the variable j_id.
Then we check whether
i_id is equal to j_id.
And if they are equal, this means that
i and j already lie in the same set.
Which means that nothing needs to be done.
Which means, in turn,
that we can just return.
If i_id and j_id are different,
we do the following.
Well, we need to merge two sets.
The smallest element in this set is i_id.
The smallest element in this set is j_id.
Which means that the smallest
element in the merged set
should be just the minimum among i_id and
j_id.
Restores as minimum in the variable m.
Then we need to scan all the objects,
all our n objects and
update the id of each.
And update the value of
the smallest array for
reach objects for
which their id is i_id or j_id.
So this is done in the loop here
where k ranges from 1 to n.
So we check where
the smallest of k is i_id or
j_id and if it is equal then
we update it to be equal to m.
The running time of this operation is
linear of course, just because essentially
what we have here is a single loop
that goes over all n objects.
The bottleneck of our current
implementation is the union operation,
whose running time is linear as opposed
to the finite make-set operations.
Whose running time is just constant.
So we definitely need
another data structure for
storing sets, which allows for
more efficient merging.
And one such data
structure is a linked list.
So let's try to use the following idea.
Let's represent each set
just as a linked list and
let's use the tail of a list as
the ID of the corresponding set.
Let me illustrate this with two examples.
In this case we have two sets,
each one of them is represented,
is organized as a linked list, and
we treat the tail of a list as
the ID of the corresponding set.
For example in this case,
7 is the ID of the first set and
8 is the ID of the second set.
Now to find the ID of the set that
contains the element three for example,
we just follow the pointers until we
reach the tail of the corresponding list.
So in this case ID is well defined.
What is also nice, is that in this case.
We can merge two sets very efficiently.
Actually since they are organized
as lists, we just need
to append to the other list and
this requires changing just one pointer.
What is very nice in this case is
just the id of the merge itself
is updated automatically.
So after the merging,
the hat of the resulting list is 8, so
the ID is updated for all the elements
of two sets automatically.
As we've just discussed, there are at
least two advantages of the current
implementation where we store
each set as a linked list.
First of all the running time of the union
operation is, in this case, just constant.
This is because to merge, to linked lists,
we'd just append one of
them to the other one.
And for
this we need just to change one pointer.
Another advantage here is that we
have a well-defined ID in this case.
Namely if two elements lie in
the same set then find will return
the same tale element from
the corresponding list, right?
And also if two elements lie in
different sets then the tales
of the corresponding two
lists are different.
And this is exactly what we want.
There are however also two disadvantages.
The first disadvantage is that now
the running time of the find operation
is linear in the worst case.
This is because to find the tail
of the corresponding list, I mean,
given an element, we would like to
find the corresponding tail of a list.
For this, we need to follow the pointers
til we reach the tail of this list.
For this, we might need potentially to
traverse a linear number of elements.
Because the list might contain
a linear number of elements.
So in the worst case,
the running time of Find declaration
is linear, which is not so good.
The second disadvantage is that actually
implementing Union operation is not so,
in constant time, is not so easy as it
was shown on our previous two examples.
Namely, we assumed
implicitly in this example,
then when given two elements x and
y, we can find the beginning
of the list containing x, and the end of
the list containing y in constant time.
So to be able to do this, we might need
to store some additional information.
And this in turn will require us to
update this information when we merge
two elements.
So once again, this means that
to implement union procedure
in constant time we need to store
some additional information,
but not just pointers from a particular
element to the next element.
In search of an inspiration for
improving our current implementation,
let's review our previous two examples.
So we've discussed that merging
these two sets shown on this slide
is follows as good because it
requires just constant time and
it updates the ID of
the resulting set automatically.
On the other hand it is bad
because it creates a long list.
This in particular requires Find(9)
to traverse the whole list,
and this makes the find operation
a linear time operation.
Right, so let's try to think about a
different way of merging these two lists.
For example, what about the following one?
In this case, first of all we,
the resulting in structures is not least,
it's just strange right?
However, it is still constant time, right?
And also 7 can still be considered
as a ID of the resulting set.
Because 7 is reachable from
any other element, right?
However, so what about this structure?
It is not a list, but it is a tree.
Right, so it is a tree whose root is
seven, and that has two branches, right.
In the next video we will
develop this idea to get a very
efficient implementation of
the disjoint sets data structure.
Namely, we will represent
each set as a tree.
And we will show that in
this case the running time,
the amortized running time of each
operation is nearly constant.