So let's look at a naive divide and
conquer algorithm, to solve
polynomial multiplication problem.
The idea is, we're going to
take our long polynomial and
we're going to break it in two parts.
The upper half and the lower half.
So A(x) is going to be D sub
one of X ,times x sub n over 2,
plus d sub 0 of x, the bottom half.
D sub 1 of x, since we've pulled
out x sub n over 2 terms,
it's lowest term is actually,
just a sub n over 2.
So we have two parallel sub polynomials,
the high and the low.
We do the same thing for B.
So we break that into E sub 1 of x,
and E sub 0 of x.
Again, where E sub 1 of x is the high
terms, E sub 0 of x is the low terms.
When we do our multiplication, then,
we just multiply together D 1,
x sub n over 2 plus D 0 and
E 1 times x sub n over 2 plus E 0.
And that then yields for terms,
D sub 1 E sub 1 times x sub n,
D sub 1 E sub 0 + D sub 0 E sub 1
times x sub n/2 + D sub 0 E sub 0.
The key here is that, we now just need to
calculate D1 E1, D1 E0, D0 E1, and D0 E0.
Those are all polynomials of degree
n over 2.
And so, now we can go ahead and use a
recursive solution to solve this problem.
So it gives us a divide and
conquer problem.
Its run time is T of n,
equals 4 T of n over 2.
Why 4?
4, because we're breaking
into 4 subproblems.
Each of them takes time T of n over 2
ecause the problem is broken in half.
Plus, then,
in order to take the results and
do our addition that's going
to take order n time.
So some constant k, times that.
Let's look at an example.
So we have, n is 4, so
we have degree three polynomials.
And we're going to break up A of
x into the top half, 4x plus 3,
and the bottom half, 2x plus 1.
Similarly, we're going to break
up the top half of B of x.
X cubed plus 2 x squared
just becomes x plus 2.
And 3x plus 4, stays at 3x plus 4.
Now, we compute D1 E1.
So multiplying together, 4x + 3, times x
plus 2, gives us 4 x squared + 11x + 6.
Similarly, we calculate D1 E0,
D0 E1, and D0 E0.
Now we've done all four of those
computations, AB is just D1 E1,
4 x squared + 11x + 6 times x to the 4th,
plus the sum of D1 E0 and
D0 E1, times x squared,
plus finally D0 E0.
If we sum this all together,
we get 4 x to the 6th, plus 11 x to the 5th,
plus 20 x to the 4th, plus 30 x cubed,
plus 20 x squared, plus 11x plus 4.
Which is our solution.
Now, how long's this take to run?
We're going to look at that in a moment.
Let's look at the actual code for it.
So we're going to compute a resulting
array, from 0 to 2n-2, so
is all the results coefficients.
And our base case is that if n of size 1,
we're going to multiply together
A at a sub l, plus B at b sub l.
Let's look at those parameters again.
So A and B are our arrays of coefficients,
n is the size of the problem,
a sub l is the first coefficient
that we're interested in.
And b sub l is the coefficient in B,
So we're going to be going from b sub l,
b sub l plus one, b sub l plus two, etc.
And for n times.
First thing we'll do, is multiply
together the D sub one and E sub one.
So basically what we're doing, I'm sorry,
the D sub zero and E sub zero.
So, what we're doing is taking A and B,
we're reducing the problem size by 2 and
we're starting with
those same coefficients.
And we're going to assign those to
the lower half of the elements in R.
Then we're going to do something similar,
where we take the upper
halves of each of A and B.
So again, the problem size becomes n/2,
but now we're moving the lower coefficient
we're interested in from a sub l to a sub
l + n/2 and b sub l to b sub l + n/2.
And we're going to assign those to
the high coefficients in our result.
Then, what we have to do is
calculate D sub 0 E1, and D1 E0.
And then, sum those together.
When we sum those together,
we're going to assign those to the middle
elements of the resulting array.
And we'll then return that result.
Now the question comes up,
how long does it take?
So we have an original problem of size n,
we break it into four
problems of size n over 2.
So, level 0 we have size n,
level 1 we have size of n over 2,
at level i, our problems
are of size n over 2 to the i.
And all the way down to the bottom
of the tree is at log base 2 of n,
and each of the problems are of size 1.
How many problems do we have?
At level 0, we have 1 problem.
We have then 4 problems.
If we go to the i'th level,
we have 4 to the i problems.
And at the very bottom, then we have
4 to the log base 2 of n problems.
How much work is there?
Well, we just need to multiply
together the number of problems
times the amount of work,
so we have kn here, and
4 times, 4 because there are 4 problems,
kn over 2, because the problem
size is n over 2 and
the amount of work we're doing at each
level is k times n over 2 per problem.
So 4 kn over 2 just equals k times 2n,
At the ith level for
the i problems, each problem
takes k times n over 2 to the i
to deal with, we multiply together,
k 2 to the i times n.
And at the very bottom,
we have k amount of work,
we have a problem size of 1,
times 4 to the log base 2 of n.
Well four the log base two of n,
is just n squared.
So we have k n squared.
Our total
as we sum up all the work is going
to be summation from i equals zero
to log base two of n of four to
the i k times n over two to the i.
And that just gets dominated by
the very bottom term which is
big theta of n squared.
So that's what our runtime takes.
This is kind of weird.
We went through all this work to
create a divide and conquer algorithm.
And yet,
the run time is the same run time as it
was with our naive original algorithm.
We're going to see in the next video,
a way to redo our divide and
conquer algorithm, so we have less
work to do at each level, and so
we actually get a better final run time.