We've seen that even though PANDAS allows
us to iterate over every row in a data
frame this is generally a slow way
to accomplish a given task and
it's not very pandorable.
For instance, if we wanted to write
some code to iterate over all the of
the states and generate a list of
the average census population numbers.
We could do so
using a loop in the unique function.
Another option is to use
the dataframe group by function.
This function takes some column name or
names and splits the dataframe up into
chunks based on those names,
it returns a dataframe group by object.
Which can be iterated upon, and
then returns a tuple where the first
item is the group condition,
and the second item is the data
frame reduced by that grouping.
Since it's made up of two values,
you can unpack this, and
project just the column that you're
interested in, to calculate the average.
Here's some examples of
both methods in action.
Let's first load the census data, then
exclude the state level summarizations,
which had a sum level value of 40.
Here's some examples of
both methods in action.
Let's first load the census data,
then exclude the state level
summarizations which
had a sum level of 40.
In the first we used the census date.
We get a list of the unique states.
Then for each state we reduce the data
frame and calculate the average.
If we time this we see it takes a while.
I've set the number of loops here
the time it should take to ten
because I'm live loading.
Here's the same approach
with a group by object.
We tell pandas we're interested in
group and with a state name and then we
calculate the average using just one
column and all of the data in that column.
When we time it we see a huge
difference in the speed
Now, 99% of the time, you'll use
group by on one or more columns.
But you can actually provide
a function to group by as well and
use that to segment your data.
This is a bit of a fabricated example but
lets say that you have a big batch
job with lots of processing and
you want to work on only a third or
so of the states at a given time.
We could create some function which
returns a number between zero and
two based on the first
character of the state name.
Then we can tell group by to use this
function to split up our data frame.
It's important to note that in order
to do this you need to set the index of
the data frame to be the column
that you want to group by first.
Here's an example.
We'll create some new
function called fun and
if the first letter of the parameter
is a capital M we'll return a 0.
If it's a capital Q we'll return a 1 and
otherwise we'll return a 2.
Then we'll pass this function
to the data frame reply, and
see that the data frame is segmented
by the calculated group number.
This kind of technique,
which is sort of a light weight hashing,
is commonly used to distribute
tasks across multiple workers.
Whether they are cores in a processor,
nodes in a supercomputer, or
disks in a database.
A common work flow with group
bias that you split your data,
you apply some function,
then you combine the results.
This is called split
apply combine pattern.
And we've seen the splitting method,
but what about apply?
Certainly iterative methods as
we've seen can do this, but
the groupby object also has a method
called agg which is short for aggregate.
This method applies
a function to the column or
columns of data in the group,
and returns the results.
With agg, you simply pass in a dictionary
of the column names that you're interested
in, and
the function that you want to apply.
For instance to build a summary data frame
for the average populations per state,
we could just give agg a dictionary
with the Census 2010 pop key and
the numb/pie average function.
Now, I want to flag a potential issue and
using the aggregate method
of group by objects.
You see, when you pass in a dictionary
it can be used to either to identify
the columns to apply a function on or
to name an output column if there's
multiple functions to be run.
The difference depends on the keys that
you pass in from the dictionary and
how they're named.
In short, while much of the documentation
and examples will talk about a single
groupby object,
there's really two different objects.
The data frame groupby and
the series groupby.
And these objects behave a little
bit differently with aggregate.
For instance, we take our census data and
convert it into a series with the state
names as the index and only columns
as the census 2010 population.
And then we can group this by
index using the level parameter.
Then we call the agg method where
the dictionary that has both the numpie
average and the numpie sum functions.
PANDAS applies those functions to the
series object and, since there's only one
column of data It apples both functions
to that column and prints out the output.
We can do the same thing with
a data frame instead of a series.
We set the index to be the state name,
we group by the index, and
we project two columns.
The population estimate in 2010,
the population estimate in 2011.
When we call aggregate
with two parameters,
it builds a nice hierarchical column space
and all of our functions are applied.
Where the confusion can come in is when
we change the labels of the dictionary we
passed to aggregate, to correspond to
the labels in our group data frame.
In this case, pandas recognizes that
they're the same and maps the functions
directly to columns instead of creating
a hierarchically labeled column.
From my perspective this
is very odd behavior,
not what I would expect
given the labeling change.
So just be aware of this when
using the aggregate function.
So that's the group by function.
I use the group by function regularly
in my work, and it's very handy for
segmenting a data frame,
working on small pieces of the data frame,
and then creating bigger
data frames later.