Hi, in the previous lesson you've
learned what is a hash function,
what is a hash table, and how to use
those to implement data structures for
storing sets of objects and mappings
from one type of object to another one.
However, the speed of this data structure
depends a lot on the choice of hash
function and in this lesson you will
learn how to choose a good hash function.
You will learn how to implement
an efficient context book.
And you will also learn how is hashing
of strength objects in Java implemented.
We will start with the phone book problem.
When you use your phone you
want to be able to quickly
look up a phone number of a person
by name to be able to call him.
And to determine who is calling you and
to see not their phone number but
their name if it's in your contact book.
So, you need a data structure that
is able to efficiently add and
delete contacts from your phone book.
To look up phone number by name and
to do the reverse,
look up the name given the phone number.
To do that we will need two mappings,
one from phone numbers to names, and
another one from names to phone numbers.
We will implement both of
those maps as hash tables and
we will start from the mapping
from phone numbers to names.
One approach that we know from
the previous lesson is direct addressing.
First, we'll need to convert phone numbers
to integers and that is very easy to do.
We'll implement simple function
called int, as in integer that
just deletes all characters of
the phone number other then digits.
And then you are left with an integer
number like in this example.
Then we'll create an array called Name,
which will contain 10 to the power
L cells, where L is the maximum
allowed length of the phone number.
That way it will be able
to store a cell for
each integer number from 0 to 999,999 and
that 9 is going L times,
where L is the maximum
length of a phone number.
So it will be basically enough to store
each phone number of allowed length.
And in this array, we'll store the names
corresponding to the phone number.
So to store a name corresponding to some
phone number P, we will first convert P
to an integer, and the store the name
in the cell with this number.
And if there is no contact with
some particular phone number P,
we'll just store a default value
N/A in the corresponding cell.
This is how it will look like.
On the right is our array Name, and
on the left, we have two contacts.
Natalie with number
123-45-67 which is converted
to 1,234,567 and is stored in the cell
with this number in the array.
It is somewhere in
the middle of the array,
there are a lot of cells before that.
A few cells next to it are probably
filled with default value N/A.
Because of course we have much less
phone numbers in your phone book than 10
to the power of 7, which is 10 million.
And then there is another contact of Steve
which is stored at position 2232323.
And of course,
there are more N/As in this array.
So as we know operations in the direct
addressing scheme work in constant time.
However the memory consumption
is exponential in this case.
Is big O of 10 to the power of L,
where L is the maximum
allowed phone number length.
And that is problematic,
because with international phone numbers,
which can contain 12 digits or more for
European countries, for example,
we will need one terabyte, just to
store one phone book, of one person.
No smart phone is able to store
a phone book of size one terabyte.
And in the next video,
we will suggest a scheme that avoids
this problem with memory consumption.