Hi, in the previous video you learned
that for any deterministic hash function,
there is a bad input on which it
will have a lot of collisions.
And in this video,
you will learn to solve that problem.
And the idea starts from, remember
when you started QuickSort algorithm?
At first, you learned that it can
work as slow as m squared time.
But then you learned that adding a random
pivot to the partition procedure helps,
because now you know that QuickSort
works on average in n log n time.
And in practice, it works usually faster
than the other sorting algorithms.
So we want to use the same randomization
idea here for hash functions.
But we already know that we cannot just
use a random hash function because
it must be deterministic.
So instead, we will first create
a whole set of hash functions
called a family of hash functions.
And we'll choose a random function from
this family to use in our algorithm.
Not all families of hash functions
are good, however, and so
we will need a concept of universal
family of hash functions.
So let U be the universe, the set of
all possible keys that we want to hash.
And then a set of hash functions
denoted by calligraphic letter H,
set of functions from U to
numbers between 0 and m- 1.
So hash functions with
the same cardinality.
Such set is called
a universal family if for
any two keys in the universe
the probability of collision is small.
So, what does that mean?
Our hash function is
a deterministic function, so for
any two keys it either has a collision for
those two keys or not.
So, what does it mean that
the probability of collision for
two different keys is small?
It means that if we look at
our family calligraphic H,
then at most 1/m part of all
hash functions in this family,
at most 1/m of them have a collision for
these two different keys.
And if we select a random hash
function from the family with
probability at least one minus one over m,
which is very close to one,
there will be no collision for
this hash function and these two keys.
And of course it is essential
that the keys are different.
Because if keys are equal then any
deterministic hash function will have
the same value on these two keys.
So, this collision property with
small probability is only for
two different keys in the universe,
but for
any two different keys in the universe
this property should be satisfied.
It might seem that it is impossible but
later you will learn how to build
a universal family of hash functions and
practice.
So how are randomization
idea works in practice.
One approach would be to just make one
hash function which returns a random
value between 0 and m-1,
each value with the same probability.
Then the probability of collision for
any two keys is exactly 1/m.
But that is not a universal family.
Actually we cannot use this family
at all because the hash function is
not deterministic and we can only
use deterministic hash functions.
So instead,
we need to have some set of hash functions
such that all the hash functions
in the set are deterministic.
And then, we will select a random function
h from this set of hash functions,
and we will use the same fixed function
h throughout the whole algorithm.
So that we can correctly find all the
objects that we store in the hash table,
for example.
So, there is a Lemma about
running time of operations
with hash table if we
use universal family.
If hash function h is chosen at
random from a universal family
then on average the length of
the longest chain in our hash table
will be bounded by O(1 + alpha),
where alpha is the load factor.
Load factor is the ratio of number of
keys that we store in our hash table
to the size of the hash table allocated.
Which is the same as the chronology
of the hash functions
in the universal family that we use.
So, it makes sense.
If the load factor is small it means
that we only store a few keys in a large
hash table, and so
longest chain will be short.
But as our table gets filled up,
the chains grow.
This Lemma says, however,
that if we chose a random function from a
universal family they won't grow to much.
On average, the longest chain will
still be of length just (1 + alpha).
And probably that is just
a small number because alpha
is usually below one,
you don't want to store more keys in
the hash table than the size
of the hash table allocated.
So alpha will be below
1 most of the time and
then (1+ alpha) is just two, so
this is a constant actually.
So, the corollary is that if h is chosen
at random from the universal family,
then operations with hash table will
run on average in a constant time.
Now the question is,
how to choose the size of your hash table?
Of course, it control the amount of
memory used with m which is your
chronology of the hash functions and which
is equal to the size of the hash table.
But you also control
the speed of the operations.
So ideally, in practice, you want your
load factor alpha to be between 0.5 and 1.
You want it to be below 1 because
otherwise you store too much keys in
the same hash table and
then everything could becomes slow.
But also you don't want alpha to be
too small because that way you will
waste a lot of memory.
If alpha is at least one-half,
then you basically use linear memory
to store your n keys and
your memory overhead is small.
And operations still run in time,
O(1 + alpha) which is a constant time,
on average if alpha is between 0.5 and 1.
The question is what to do if
you don't know in advance how
many keys you want to
store in your hash table.
Of course, there is a solution to
start with a very big hash table, so
that definitely all the keys will fit.
But this way you will
waste a lot of memory.
So, what we can do is copy the idea
you learned in the lesson about
dynamic arrays.
You start with a small hash table and
then you grow it organically as
you put in more and more keys.
Basically, you resize the hash table and
make it twice bigger as soon
as alpha becomes too large.
And then,
you need to do what is called a rehash.
You need to copy all the keys from the
current hash table to the new bigger hash
table.
And of course,
you will need a new hash function
with twice the chronology to do that.
So here is the code which tries
to keep loadfFactor below 0.9.
And 0.9 is just a number I selected,
you could put 1 here or
0.8, that doesn't really matter.
So first we compute the current
loadFactor, which is the ratio
of the number of keys stored in
the table to the size of the hash table.
And if that loadFactor just
became bigger than 0.9,
we create a new hash table of twice
the size of our current hash table.
We also choose a new random hash
function from the universal family
with twice the cardinality coresponding
to the new hash table size.
And then we take each object
from our current hash table, and
we insert it in the new hash table
using the new hash function.
So we basically copy all
the keys to the new hash table.
And then we substitute our current hash
table with the bigger one and the current
hash function with the hash function
corresponding to the new hash table.
That way,
the loadFactor decreases roughly twice.
Because we added,
probably just added one new element,
the loadFactor became just
a little more than 0.9.
And then we increase the size of the hash
table twice while the number of keys
stayed the same, so
the loadFactor became roughly 0.45,
which is below 0.9,
which is what we wanted.
So to achieve that, you need to
call this procedure rehash after
each operation which inserts
something in your hash table.
And it could work slowly when
this happens because the rehash
procedure needs to copy all
the keys from your current hash
table to the new big hash table,
and that works in linear time.
But similarly to dynamic arrays,
the amortized running time will still be
constant on average because their
hash will happen only rarely.
So you reach a certain
level of load factor and
you increase the size of our table twice.
And then it will take twice longer to
again reach too high value of load factor.
And then you'll again increase
your hash table twice.
So the more keys you put in,
the longer it takes until the next rehash.
So their hashes will be really rare, and
that's why it won't influence your running
time with operations, significantly.