Hi, in the previous video,
you've learned the concept of universal
family of hash functions and you learned
how to use it to make operations
with your hash table really fast.
However, now we need to actually
build a universal family and you will
start with a universal family for the most
important object which is integer number.
Because any object on your computer
is represented as a series of bits or
bytes, and so you can think of it
as a sequence of integer numbers.
And so first, we need to learn
to hash integers efficiently.
So we will build a universal family for
hashing integers.
But we will look at our example
with phone numbers because
we need to store contacts in our phone.
So first, we will consider only phone
numbers up to length seven and for
example we will consider
phone number 148-2567.
And again,
we'll convert all of those phone numbers,
we want to start from integers from zero
to the number consisting of seven nines.
And for example, our selected phone number
will convert to 1,482,567.
And then we will hash those integers
to which we convert our phone numbers.
So to hash them, we will need to
also choose a big prime number,
bigger than 10 to the power of 7, for
example, 10,000,019 is
a suitable prime number.
And we will also need to choose the hash
table size which is the same as
the chronology of the hash
function that we need.
So now that we selected p and m, we
are ready to define universal family for
integers between 0 and
10 to the power of 7 minus 1.
So the Lemma says that the following
family of hash functions is
a universal family.
What is this family?
It is indexed by p, p is the prime number,
10,000,019, in this case that we choose.
And it also has parameters a and b,
so those parameters are different for
different hash functions in these family.
Basically, if you fix a and b,
you fix a hash function from
this hash functions family,
calligraphic H with index p.
And x is the key, it is the integer
number that we want to hash,
and it is required that x is less than p.
It is from 0 to p minus 1,
or less than p minus 1, but
definitely, it is less than p.
So, to create a value of this
integer x with some hash function, we
first make a linear transform of this x.
We multiply it by a, corresponding
to this hash function, and add b,
corresponding to this hash function.
Then we take the result,
modulo our big prime number p.
And after that, we again take the result
modulo the size of our hash table or
the chronology of the hash
functions that we need.
So all these hash functions indexed by
a and b will have the same chronology m.
And the size of this hash family,
what do you think it is?
Well, it is equal to b multiply
by p minus 1, why is that?
Because there are p minus 1 variance for
a, and independently from that,
there are p variance for b.
So the total number of pairs, a and
b, is p multiplied by p minus 1,
that is the size of our universal family.
And the Lemma states that it really
will be a universal family for
integers between 0 and p minus 1.
We will prove this Lemma in a separate,
optional video.
And here, we'll look at an example
of how this universal family works.
So, for example, we selected hash
function corresponding to a = 34 and
b = 2, so this hash function
h is h index by p, 34, and 2.
And we will compute the value
of this hash function on number
1,482,567 because this integer
number corresponds to the phone number who
we're interested in which is 148-2567.
Well, remember that p that we chose
is a prime number 10,000,019.
So first,
we multiply our number x by 34 and add 2,
and after that,
we take the result modulo b,
modulo 10,000,019, and
the result is 407,185.
Then we take this result and
take it again modulo 1,000,
and the result is 185.
And so the value for our selected
hash function on number x is 185.
And for any other number x, you would do
the same, you would multiply x by 34,
add 2, take the result modulo b,
then take the result modulo 1,000.
And so any value of our hash function is
a number between 0 and 999 as we want.
And if we do different a and
b, instead of 34 and 2,
we'll just multiply x by different a,
add different b.
Take a modulo b, take the result modulo m,
and get the value for our hash function.
So in the general case, when the phone
numbers can be longer than seven,
we first define the maximum allowed
length, L, of the phone number.
And again, convert all the phone numbers
to integers which will derive from 0 to 10
to the power of L- 1, and
then we'll hash those integers.
To hash those integers, we'll choose
a sufficiently large number p,
p must be more than 10 to the power
of L for the family to be universal.
Because otherwise, if we take some
p less than 10 to the power of L,
there will exist two different
integer numbers between 0 and
10 to the power of L- 1,
which differ by exactly p.
And then, when we compute the value of
some hash function on both those numbers
and we take linear
transformation of those keys,
modulo b, the value of those
transformations will be the same.
And then when we take, again, module m,
the value again will be the same.
And that means that for
any hash function from our family,
the value of its function on
these two keys will be the same.
So there will be a collision for
any hash function from the family, but
that contradicts the definition
of universal family.
Because for a universal family and for
two fixed different keys, no more than
1 over m part of all hash functions
can have collision for these two keys.
And in our case, all hash functions
have a collision for these two keys, so
this is definitely not a universal family.
So we must take p more than
10 to the power of L, and
in fact, that is sufficient.
Then, we choose hash table of size m, and
then we use our universal family,
calligraphic H with index p.
We choose a random hash function from this
universal family, and to choose a random
hash function from this family, we need
to actually choose two numbers, a and b.
And a should be a random
number between 1 and p-1,
and b should be an independent
random number from 0 to p-1.
If we selected those two numbers,
we define our hash function completed.
So now we know how to solve
the problem of phone book
in the direction from
phone numbers to names.
So we first define the longest
allowed length of the phone number.
We convert all the phone numbers
to integers from 0 to 10
to the power of L -1.
We choose a big prime number,
bigger than 10 to the power of L.
We choose the size of the hash table
that we want based on the techniques
you learned in the previous video and
then you add
the context to your phone book
as a hash table of size m.
Hashing them by a hash function
randomly selected from
the universal family,
calligraphic H with index p.
And that is the solution in the direction
from phone numbers to names.
This solution will take bit of m memory,
and you can control for m,
and it will work on average in
constant time if you select m wisely
using the techniques
from the previous video.
And now we also need to solve our phone
book problem in the different direction,
from names to phone numbers.
And that we will do in the next video.