Hi, in this video, you will learn how to
prove the upper bound on the expected
chain length in the hash
table using chaining and
a hash function from
the universal hash family.
This proof is needed to be
confident that our hash tables
will work fast in practice.
The proof will use some advanced math,
which we won't cover, but
this video is optional.
We will use probabilities,
mathematical expectation, and
the linearity of expectations.
First, let us recall what
is a universal family.
So if U is the universe, the set of all
possible keys that we want to store and
calligraphic H is the set of function from
this universe to the set of numbers from 0
to m- 1, where m is the selected
cardinality of the hash function.
Then this set, calligraphic H,
is called universal family, if for
any two different keys from the universe,
the probability of collision for
a random hash function on these
two keys is at most 1 over m.
What do we mean by probability?
It is taken over the random choice of a
hash function from the set calligraphic H.
Or in other words, the reformulation
of this definition is that for
any two different keys, x and y from
the universe, at most 1 over m part of
all hash functions in calligraphic H
produce a collision on these two keys.
Let's also recall what is a load factor.
You have a hash table of size m,
storing n keys.
Then n/m is denoted by alpha and
called load factor.
That measures how filled up is your table.
If you store just one key in a hash table
of size 10, then load factor is 0.1.
And if you store nine keys in a hash table
of size 10, then the load factor is 0.9.
We'll also use the property
called linearity of expectation.
It says that for any finite set of
random variables, x1 through xk,
the random variable y, which is equal
to sum of these random variables,
has expectation which is equal to the sum
of expectations of these random variables.
We won't prove it, we will use it
as a fact from probability theorem.
Now the main theorem
is that if you select,
at random, a hash function from
a universal family, calligraphic H and
it is used to hash n keys into hash table
T of size m giving load factor alpha.
Then for any key k,
the expected length of the chain in
table t which contains
key k if it stored in it,
is at most 1 + alpha.
What it means is that on average
the length of the chain containing
any key will be just 1 + alpha,
which is not too long.
Of course, in the worst case,
the chain containing some key can be very,
very long such as n keys, and
all of them are in the same chain.
But, on average, if it's like the random
hash function from the universal family,
the chain length will be at most 1 +
alpha, where alpha is the lowest factor.
So to prove that, we fix some arbitrary
key k and consider all other keys l
and define a random variable
Xkl which takes value of 1 if
the hash value of k is
equal to hash value of l,
if there's a collision between keys k and
l.
And it takes value zero otherwise.
Let's estimate the expectation
of this random variable.
It just takes two different value,
so we need first to multiply,
the first one is zero by the probability
of zero, but we will anyway get zero.
And we need to add 1 multiplied
by the probability of 1,
which is the same as the probability
of collision and we know that for
a universal family that
probability is at most 1 over m.
So expectation of Xkl for k and any l
different from k is at most 1 over m.
Now let's estimate the number
of collisions, and we denote by
Yk the number of collisions that k has
with different keys l in the table.
And to do that,
we can just sum variables Xkl for
all l which are different from key,
and are in the table T.
Why is that?
Because when a collision happens for
some key l different from k,
variable Xkl takes value 1.
Otherwise, it takes value 0.
So the sum of all these variables is just
the number of collisions with key k.
Then the length of the chain containing
key k, potentially, in the table T, is 1.
Because this key itself
could be in the table.
Plus the number of collisions
with different keys, which is Yk.
So the expectation of the number of
collisions is by the property of linearity
of expectation, equal to the sum
of expectations of variables Xkl.
And we have an upper bound on the
expectation of each of those variables,
which is 1 over m.
So this sum is at most sum for
all keys l different from k which
are in the table T of value 1 over m.
And there are at most n
summands in this sum.
Because the size, the number of
keys in the hash table T, Is n.
So at most n of them are both on
the table and different from k.
So this sum is at most n over m.
And that is the same as alpha,
the load factor.
And so the expectation of the chain
length is the expectation of 1 + Yk,
and by linearity, is the same as the
expectation of 1 plus expectation of Yk.
But expectation of constant 1 is just 1,
and
expectation of Yk we've just
estimated from above, and so
we have an upper bound on the expected
chain length, which is 1 + alpha.
So we proved our theorem.
Now here is a corollary from this theorem,
which basically says that if you
work with your hash table right,
then your operations will on
average run in constant time.
More formally, if you do some n
operations with your hash table which
include insertions,
deletions and modifications, but
the total number of insertions is big O of
m, where m is the size of the hash table.
Then, the total time to make all those
operations will be big theta of n.
Well, of course it will be at
least m to make n operations, but
it will be at most proportional to m.
And thus the amortized time for each
operation will be big O of 1 on average.
Let's prove this corollary.
We have big O of m insertions, so
the total number of keys stored at
any moment is, at most, big O of m.
n is big O of m.
And then alpha, which is m over m,
must be big O of 1, must be constant.
And then 1 +alpha,
our upper bound on the expected
chain length, is also big O of one.
And it means that on average,
the expected training time of
the operation, is big O of one.
And then when we sum the expectations for
running time of each operation we get the
expected running time of all n operations,
again by linearative expectations.
And so the expected running time
of n operations is big theta of n,
because it's big O of n,
and also it is at least n.
In conclusion,
we've just proved upper bound 1 +
alpha on the expected chain length.
In the case when we use a hash
table with chaining scheme and
select a random hash function
from a universal family.
And we've also proven constant
amortized expected running time for
operations with a hash table,
If you use universal family and
chaining and you don't put too
many keys on your hash table.
Basically if you keep your loss factor
below 1, as we discussed in one of
the previous videos, then your operations
on average run in constant time.
And in the next video, we'll also prove
that the set of hash functions that was
suggested as a universal family for
integers is really a universal family.
We will prove that formally.