>> Now we know of polynomial
hash family or hashing strings.
But there's a problem with that family.
All the hash functions in that
family have a cardinality of P,
where P is a very big prime number.
And what we want is
the cardinality of hash functions
to be the same as the size
of our hash table.
So, once a small cardinality.
So, we won't be able to use this
binomial hashing family directly
in our hash tables.
We want to somehow fix the cardinality of
the functions in the polynomial family.
And a good way to do
that is the following.
We design a new complex transformation
from strings to numbers,
from zero, to m minus one.
So, we select the cardinality m, and
we want to design a function from strings
to numbers, between zero, and m minus one.
And, to that,
we first apply our random hash function
from the polynomial family to the string.
And we get some integer number module P,
and
then we can apply a random hash
function from the universal family for
integers less than P, and
get a number between 0 and m -1,
if we select it from universal
family from cardinality m.
So, we now have a complex
transformation which is two stage.
First, take a stream and
apply a random function from
the polynomial family and then
apply a random function from the universal
family for integers to the result.
And you get a number from
zero to m-1 from the string.
Note that it is very important that we
first select both random function from
the polynomial family and
the random function from
the universal family of our integers.
And we fix them, and we use the same pair
of functions for the whole algorithm.
And then, the whole function from string
to integer number from between zero and
minus one is a deterministic
hash function.
And it can be shown that the family
of functions define this way
is a very good family.
It is not a universal family, but
it is a very good family with [INAUDIBLE].
More specifically, if you take
any two different strings S1 and
S2 of length at most L + 1, and
you choose a cardinality m, and
you apply the process described to
build a hash family from strings
of length at most L + 1 to integers
numbers between zero and m minus 1.
Then the probability of collision for
random function from that family
is at most 1 over m + L over p.
So, that is not an universal
family because for
a universal family there shouldn't be
any summon L over p the probability of
collision should be at most 1 over M.
But we can be very, very close to
universal family because we can control P.
We can make P very big.
And then L over p will be very small.
And so, the probability of collision
will be at most will 1 over m
plus some very small number.
And so, it will be either even less
than 1 over m or very close to it.
So 1 mL hash, and then universal hash for
integers is a good construction
of a family of hash functions.
A Corollary from
the previous Lemma is that,
if we specifically select the prime number
p to be bigger than m multiplied by L,
then the probability of collision will be,
at most of 1 over m,
so it won't be less than 1 over m itself,
but
it will be at most 1 over m
multiplied by some constant.
Why is that?
Well, because if we rewrite 1 over m
plus L over p by 1 over m + L over mL.
Then the second expression will be
bigger because P is bigger than mL.
And then it is equal is 2 over
m which is big O(1 over m).
So that way, we proved that
combination of polynomial hashing with
universal hashing for integers,
is a really good family of hash functions.
Now what if we take this new
family of hash functions and
apply it to build a hash table?
Well, I say that for
big enough prime number p,
we'll again have running
time on average c=O(1 + a).
The length of the longest
chain will be O(1 + a).
Where alpha is the lowest
factor of our hash table.
And so, by wisely controlling this size
of the hash table on the lowest factor
as we learned in the previous videos.
We can control the running time and
the memory consumption.
Of course, computing the hash
function itself on sum string s
is not a constant time operation,
because the string can be very long.
And we need to look through the whole
string to compute our hash function.
But in the case when the lengths of
the strings in question are bounded,
like for example with names definitely
there are no names longer than a few
hundred characters I think, so
all they are bounded by some constant L.
And so computing hash
function on the names, tags,
of course go off the length
of the stream time, but
it is also we go off constant time
because L is a constant itself, and
so we can implement a map from names
to phone numbers using chaining,
using the newly created family of
hash functions, which is complex.
It first applies polynomial hashing
to the stream, to the name, and
then applies universal family or
integers to the result.
So we can choose a random hash
function from this two staged family.
And store our names, and phone numbers in
the hash table, using this hash function.
In conclusion, you learned how to hash
integers, and strings, really good, so
that probability of collision is small.
You learned that a phone book
can be implemented as two maps,
as two hash tables, one from phone
numbers to names, and another one back,
from names to phone numbers.
And if you manage to do that in such a way
you don't waste too much memory where all
factors of your hash table is between
one five and one, and search and
modification, on average,
work in constant time, which is great.
And then the next lesson.
We'll learn to apply hash functions to
different problems such as searching for
patterns in text.