In this video, I'm going to introduce
Principal Component Analysis, which is a
very widely used technique in signal
processing.
The idea of principal components
analysis, is that high dimensional data
can often be represented using a much
lower dimensional code.
This happens when the data lies near a
linear manifold in the high dimensional
space.
So the idea is, if we can find this
linear manifold, we can project the data
onto the manifold,
and then just represent where it is on
the manifold.
And we haven't lost much,
because in the directions orthogonal to
the manifold, there's not much variation
in the data.
As we'll see, we can do this operation
efficiently using standard principle
components methods,
or we can do it inefficiently using a
neural net with one hidden layer, where
both the hidden units and the output
units are linear.
The advantage of doing it with the neural
net is that we can then generalize the
technique to using deep neural nets in
which the code is a nonlinear function of
the input.
And our reconstruction of the data from
the code is also a nonlinear function of
the code.
This enables us to deal with curved
manifolds in the input space.
So we represent data by where it gets
projected on the curve manifold.
And this is a much more powerful
representation.
In principal components analysis, we have
N dimensional data, and we want to
represent it using less than N numbers.
And so we find M orthagonal directions in
which the data has the most variance.
And we ignore the directions in which the
data doesn't vary much.
The M principal dimensions form a lower
dimensional subspace, and we represent an
N dimensional data point by its
projections onto these M dimensions in
the lower dimensional space.
So we've lost all information about where
the data point is located in the
remaining orthogonal directions.
But since these don't have much variance,
we haven't lost that much information.
If we wanted to reconstruct the data
point, from our representation in terms
of M numbers, we reduce the mean value
for all the N minus M directions that are
not represented, and then the area in our
reconstruction.
Would be the sum over all these
unrepresented directions of the square
difference between the value of the data
point count on that direction, and the
mean value on that direction.
This is most easily seen in the picture.
So consider 2-dimensional data.
This distributed according to an
elongated Gaussian like this.
The ellipse is meant to show kind of one
standard deviation contour of the
Gaussian.
And consider a data point like that red
one.
If we used principal components analysis
with a single component.
That component would be the direction in
the data that had the greatest variance.
And so to represent the red point, we'd
represent how far along that direction it
lay.
In other words we'd represent the
projection of the red point onto that
line, i.e.
the green point.
When we need to reconstruct the red
point,
what we'll do is simply use the mean
value of all the data points, in the
direction that we've ignored.
In other words you'll represent a point
on that black line.
And so the lost in the reconstruction
will be the squared difference between
the red point and the green point.
That is, would have lost the difference
between the data point and the mean value
of all the data, in the direction we're
not representing, which is the direction
of least variance.
And so we obviously have minimized our
loss if we choose to ignore the direction
of least variance.
Now, we can actually implement PCA, or a
version of it, using back propagation,
but it's not very efficient.
So what we do is we make a network in
which the output of the network is the
reconstruction of the data.
And we try and minimize the squared error
in the reconstruction.
The network has a central bottleneck that
only has M hidden units.
And those are going to correspond to the
principal components, or something like
them.
So it looks like this.
We have an input vector.
We project that onto a code vector.
And from the code vector, we construct an
output vector.
And the aim is to make the output vector
as similar as possible to the input
vector.
The activities of the hidden units in the
code vector from a bottleneck.
So the code vector is a compressed
representation of the input vector.
If the hidden units and the output units
are linear, then ordering coder like
this,
we'll learn codes that minimize the
squared reconstruction error.
And that's exactly what principle
components analysis does.
It will get exactly the same
reconstruction error as principle
components analysis does.
But it won't necessarily have hidden
units that correspond exactly the, the
principle components.
They will span the same space as the
first N-principal components, but there
may be a rotation and skewing of those
axes.
So the incoming weight vectors of the
code units, which are what represent the
directions of the components, may not be
orthogonal.
And unlike principal components analysis,
they will typically have equal variances.
But the space spanned by the incoming
weight vectors of those code units will
be exactly the same as the space spanned
by the M principal components.
So in that sense this network will do an
equivalent thing to principal components.
It's just if we use to cast the great
descend learning for this network, it
will typically much less sufficient than
the algorithm used for principle
components.
Although if there's a huge amount of
data, it might actually be more
efficient.
The main point of implementing principal
component analysis using back-propagation
in a neural net is that it allows us to
generalize principal component analysis.
If we use a neural net that has nonlinear
layers before and after the code layer,
it should be possible to represent data
that lies on a curved manifold rather
than a linear manifold in a
high-dimensional space.
And this is much more general.
So our network will look something like
this, the B input vector, and then one or
more, layer of non-linear hidden unit,
typically we use logistic units.
Then there'll be a code layer which might
be linear units.
And then following the code layer,
there'll be one or more layers of
non-linear hidden units.
And then there'll be an output vector,
which we train to be as similar as
possible to the input vector.
So this is a curious network in which
we're using a supervised learning
algorithm to do unsupervised learning.
The bottom part of the network is an
encoder.
Which takes the input vector and convert
it into a code using a non-linear method.
The top part of the network is a decoder,
which takes the nonlinear code and maps
it back to a reconstruction of the input
vector.
So after we've done the learning, we have
mappings in both directions.