In this video, I'm going to describe a
technique called semantic hashing that
provides an extremely efficient way of
finding documents similar to a query
document.
The idea is to convert the document into
a memory address.
And in that memory to organize things so
that if you go to a particular address
and look at the nearby addresses, you'll
find documents that are very similar.
This is much like a supermarket where if
you go to a location where a particular
product is stored and look around, you'll
find similar products.
People have known for a long time that if
you could get binary descriptors of
images, you'd have a very good way of
retrieving images quickly.
Some binary descriptors are easy to get.
For example, is it an indoor scene or an
outdoor scene?
Is to color image or black and white
image?
But it's much harder to get a list of
say, 30 binary descriptors which are more
or less orthogonal to one another, which
is what we really need.
This is a problem that machine learning
can help us with.
We're going to start by looking at the
equivalent problem for documents, but
then we're going to apply it to images.
So consider, instead of getting real
valued codes for documents,
getting binary codes, from the word
cancer documents.
We do this by training a deep
auto-encoder that has a logistic units in
it's code layer.
That by itself is not sufficient because
the logistic units will be used in their
middle ranges where they have real values
in order to convey as much information as
possible about the 2,000 word counts.
To prevent that, we add noise to the
inputs to the code units during the fine
tuning stage. So, we first train it as a
stack of restricted Boltzmann machines.
We can unroll these Boltzmann machines by
using the transposes of the white
matrices for the decoder, and then we
fine tune it with back propagation.
And as we're doing that, we add
additional Gaussian noise to the inputs
to the code units.
In order to be resistant to that noise,
the code units need to be either firmly
on or firmly off.
And so the noise will encourage the
learning to avoid the middle region of
the logistic where it conveys a lot of
information, but it's very sensitive to
noise in its inputs.
At test time, we simply threshold the
logistic units in the middle layer to get
binary values.
So, if we can train an auto-encoder like
this, we will be able to convert the
counts for a bag of words into a small
number of binary values.
In other words, we'll have learned a set
of binary features that are good for
reconstructing the bag of words.
Later on, Alex Krizhevsky discovered that
we don't actually have to add Gaussian
noise to the inputs to the 30 code units.
Instead, we can just make them stochastic
binary units.
So, during the forward pass, we
stochastically pick a binary value using
the output of the logistic.
And then, during the backward pass, we
pretend that we've transmitted the real
value probability from the logistic,
and that gives us a smooth gradient for
back propagation.
Once we've got these short binary codes,
we could of course do a sequential search
where for each known document, we store a
code.
And then when a query document arrives,
we first extract its code, if it's not
one of our known documents, and then we
compare the code with the codes of all
the stored documents.
The comparisons can be very fast, because
they can use special bit operations on a
typical CPU which can compare many bits
in parallel.
But we have to go through a very long
list of documents, possibly billions.
There's a much faster thing we can do,
there's a much faster thing we can do.
We can treat the code as if it was a
memory address.
So, the idea is that we take a document,
and we use our deep auto-encoder as a
hash function that converts a document
into a 30 bit address Now, we have a
memory with 30 bit addresses.
And in that memory, each address will
have a pointer back to the documents that
have that address.
If several documents have the same
address, we can make a little list there.
Now, if the auto-ncoder is successful in
making similar documents have similar
addresses, we have a very fast way of
finding similar documents.
We simply take the query document, you go
to the address in memory that corresponds
to its binary code, and then you look at
nearby addresses.
In other words, you start flipping bits
in that address to access nearby
addresses.
And you could imagine a little humming
ball of nearby addresses that differ by
just a few bits.
What we expect to find at those nearby
addresses is semantically similar
documents.
So, we've completely avoided searching a
big list.
We simply compute a memory address, flip
a few bits, and look up the similar
documents.
It's extremely efficient especially if we
have a very large database of say, a
billion documents.
We've completely avoided the serial
search through a billion items.
I sometimes call this supermarket search
because it's like what you would do in a
supermarket.
Suppose you went to an unfamiliar
supermarket and you wanted to find
anchovies.
You might ask the teller at the
supermarket, where do you keep the cans
of tuna fish?
You'd then go to that address in the
supermarket and you'd look around.
Hopefully, near there is things like cans
of salmon and maybe cans of anchovies.
Of course, if you're unlucky, the
anchovies might have been stored in a
completely different place,
next to the pizza toppings.
And that's the downside of this kind of
search.
Known as supermarket, it's essentially a
2-D surface.
So, it's really a 1-D string of shells,
which have height and that gives you 2-D,
and so you only have two dimensions in
which to locate things. And that's not
sufficient to put all the things you'd
like to be near one another, near one
another.
You'd like, for example, to have the
vegetarian version of things nearby, or
the Kosher version of things nearby, or
the slightly out of date version of
things nearby. And in 2-D you can't do
all that.
But what we have here is a 30 dimensional
supermarket and that's a hugely more
complex space where it's very easy to
have things near an item for many
different reasons because of similarity
along many different dimensions.
Here's another view of what we're doing
in semantic haching.
Most of the first retrieval methods work
by intersecting stored lists that are
associated with cues extracted from the
query.
So, Google, for example, will have a list
of all the documents that contain some
particular rare word.
And when you use that rare word in your
query, they will immediately have access
to that list.
They then have to intersect that list
with other lists in order to find a
document that satisfies all the terms in
your query.
Now, computers actually have special
hardware that can intersect 32 very long
lists in a single machine instruction.
The hardware is called the memory bus.
So, each bit in a 32-bit binary address
specifies a list of half the addresses in
memory.
For example, if the bit is on and it's
the first bit in the address, it
specifies the top half of memory.
If the bit is off, it specifies the
bottom half of memory.
What the memory bus is doing is
intersecting 32 lists to find the one
location that satisfies all 32 values in
the binary code.
So, we can think of semantic hashing as a
way of using machine learning to map the
retrial problem onto the type of list
intersection computer's good at.
As long as our 32-bits correspond to
meaningful properties of documents or
images,
then we can find similar ones very fast
with no search at all.