In this video, I'm going to talk about
the use of binary codes for image
retrieval.
For retrieving documents, people like
Google have such good methods already,
the techniques like semantic hashing may
not be of much value.
But retrieving images is much more
difficult and the methods that convert an
image into a fairly large binary code of
say, 256 bits, seem to work quite well.
However, we don't want to do a very long
sequencial search through vectors of 256
bits so semantic hashing can be used to
first create a short list and then we can
get better quality matches by using
longer binary codes in a serial search.
Now, we get to look at using binary codes
for image retrieval.
Image retrieval of present is typically
done by using the captions.
But why not use the images too?
They obviously contain a lot more
information than the captions.
The basic problem is that pixels are not
like words.
Individual pixels don't tell us much
about the content of an image.
Obviously if you could recognize the
objects in the images, then we'd have
things that were much more like words.
But recognizing objects is hard.
At least it was when we first did this
work.
Now deep neural nets have got much better
at it, and so that may well be the way to
go.
So if we're not going to recognize the
objects, maybe what we should do is
extract a vector that has information
about the content of the image.
And the obvious thing to extract is the
real valued vector.
But the problem is that matching real
value vectors in the real data base is
slow and it also requires a lot of
storage for the real value vectors.
If we can extract a fairly short binary
vector that contains a lot of information
about the image that's much easier to
store and much faster to match, even
faster is to use a two stage method.
So first, we extract a short binary code
of about 30 bids and that short binary
code is used with semantic hashing to
very rapidly get us a short list of
promising images.
So we simply take the short binary code,
and flip a few bits in it to get
candidate images.
The candidate images can then be matched
using 256 bit binary codes that are
stored with each known image.
To search for much better matches than
can be found with a 28 bit binary code.
Even a 256 bit binary code only requires
four words of memory per image.
And even though we're then going to do a
serial on these binary codes.
The search can be done very fast, because
it only requires a few operations to
compare two, 256 binary codes to find out
how many bits they have in common.
The question is, how good is a binary
code of that size at retrieving images?.
Are they going to find images that we
think of as being similar?
So here's a net that trained by Alex
Krizhevsky.
It's working on small color images so
they're only 32 pixels by 32 pixels and
he takes his input the red, green, and
blue channels from those images so 3,000
inputs.
He then expands that to a larger number
of hidden units because we're going to go
from real value inputs to logistic hidden
units,
which probably have less capacity.
We then progressively decrease the number
units in each layer until we get down to
256 bits.
This encoder has about 67 million
parameters.
It's quite big.
It takes a few days to train it on, in
video GPU.
And I'll exchange it on two million
images.
There's absolutely no theory to justify
the architecture we used.
We know we want a fairly deep net.
It makes sense to make it get an arrow as
we go up.
But this particular architecture, where
you have the number of units each layer,
is just a guess.
The interesting thing is, a guess like
this already works quite well.
And presumably, there are some other
architectures that will work better.
The first question to ask is how well
does an ordering coder like this do at
reconstructing the images?
So, here is a face image and it's
reconstruction and you can see that from
the reconstruction you can tell the kind
of an image it is.
Here's another example, where it's a
scene probably at a party, you can't
really tell what kind of scene it is from
the image but you might guess that there
are a number of people involved or you
might not.
Here's an outdoor scene.
And you can see that the reconstruction
captures a lot of information about the
accuracy.
It captures the water in the sky and the
hyphens of thin strip land.
So lets look at the quality of
retrievable we can do within ordering
codes that gives those kinds of
reconstruction.
We'll start with a picture of Michael
Jackson in the red square and Alex
retrieved the most similar images and
above each image you can see how many
bits had differed from Michael Jackson
body.
And you'll notice they're all a fairly
similar number of bits.
In 256 bits, differing by only 61 bits is
extraordinarily unlikely to happen by
chance if they were random images.
It has to be a pretty similar image to
differ by so few bits.
One nice thing about what's retrieved is,
with one exception, they're all faces.
If we look at the retrieval you get by
using euclidean distance on the raw
pixels,
then some of them are faces, but most of
them aren't.
So obviously the ordering coder has
understood something about faces that
isn't in the information about Euclidean
distance.
It's clearly giving much better
retrieval.
Let's take another example, here we took
the image of a party scene and we treat
of the images.
And you can see that about half of them
have images you would think of as fairly
similar that other party scenes.
The tip of the other party scenes with
something bright in the middle, like the
oiginal party scene, and you'll also
notice that most of the bad matches also
have something bright in the middle.
So even though we're getting down to 256
bit binary codes through a lot of hidden
layers, it's still sensitive to quite a
lot about the image structure and where
the brighter patches are.
If you look at what Euclidean distance
does, it's much worse.
Euclidean distance gets one other scene
with a, a group of people.
And then everything else is fairly
dissimilar.
You'll notice with Euclidean distance, it
often gets very smooth images.
That's because if you can't match the
high frequency variation in the image,
it's better to match its average then to
get other stuff with high frequency
variations out of phase.
So when you got a complicated image,
including in distance will typically find
smooth images to match it.
And that's because it's minimizing a
squared error in pixel space.
So obviously we'd like the image
retrievable to be more sensitive to the
content of the image that is stored kinds
of objects in the relationships in image
and less sensitive to the pixel
intensities.
We can do that by first training a big
net to recognize lots of different kinds
of object in real images and we show you
how to do that in lecture five.
Then we take the activity vector, in the
last hidden layer of the big net, and use
that as a representation of the image.
This should be much better than the pixel
intensities at capturing information
about the kinds of objects in the image.
So to see if this approach is likely to
work, we use the net described in lecture
five, the one the image that competition.
So far, we've only tried it on Euclidan
distance, between the activity of vectors
in the last hidden layer.
But obviously if it works for that,
we could then that those activity vectors
and build an ordering code around those
to get them down to binary codes.
So let's first see if it works with the
Euclidean distance.
It turns out it works really well.
We don't know yet whether it will work
with binary codes.
So, in the column on the left, you see
the query images.
And then to the right of them, you see
all the things that were retrieved.
If you look at the elephant query image,
you'll see that what gets retrieved is
other elephants but elephants with very
different poses.
So those images wouldn't have a very good
overlap in pixel space, although the
overlap wouldn't be that bad.
If you look at the Halloween pumpkins,
you'll see that all the retrieved things
are other Halloween pumpkins.
And some of them, would have a pretty bad
overlapping pixel space.
Similar with the aircraft carriers, we
retrieve other images of aircraft carrier
that are very different.
So we anticipate that if we could reduce
the activity vector to short binary code.
We would have a fast and effective way of
retrieving similar images just by the
content of the image.
We'll see in lecture sixteen that we
could actually combine the content of the
image with the caption of the image, to
get an even better representation.