When working with strings, we often need
to extract substrings.
For example, if a string contains a phone
number, we may want to extract the area
code.
In this lecture, I'll introduce two
techniques, indexing and slicing, and
we'll use those to extract substrings of
the strings we're working with.
In this lecture, we'll use the string
learn to program as our running example.
Each character of a string has an index
which, which is it's position in the
string.
So, the string at index zero, indicated
using this bracket notation, is the L.
At index one of the string, we have an e.
At index two, is the first a.
Notice that zero is the first position,
not one.
We start counting from zero.
We can also use negative indices to count
from the end, or from the right hand side
of the string.
So, the string at -one is the m.
At -two is the last a,
At -three is the r, the last r.
So, once we've seen using an index, we can
extract parts of the string one character
at a time. But, we can extract more than
one character using an approach called
slicing.
With slicing, we provide a start index
followed by a colon, followed by an end
index and that gives us a substring from
the start index up to, but not including
the ending index.
For example, we can get this string from
position zero, index zero up to, but not
including index five, and that gives us
the string Learn.
From index six up to, but not including
eight, is the to.
And, from index nine up to sixteen, is the
word Program, string Program.
Sixteen is equal to the length of the
string.
So, an alternative would be to start at
index nine but go up to len of s.
Len is a built in function that returns
the length of the string, so this
expression is equivalent to the one above.
Another alternative would be to go from
nine, put the pole in, and omit the ending
index.
In which case, the default is to go to the
end of the string, so this is also
equivalent to the two expressions above.
The starting index can also be omitted.
So, for example, we can include colon and
go up to index a,
We can also omit both the starting and
ending indices,
And that gives the entire string.
We've seen that negative indices can be
used for indexing, and they can be used
for slicing as well.
Let's get this substring from index one up
to but not including eight.
And our equivalent expression is to get it
from one up to but not including -eight,
Or to go from -fifteen up to but not
including -eight.
So, those three expressions are all
equivalent.
The slicing and index operations do not
modify the string that they act on.
So, the value that s refers to is
unchanged by the operations above.
In fact, we cannot change the value of a
string.
Operations like the following result in
errors.
If I take the string at index six and try
and set it to d, I get an error.
Similarly, if I try to modify the string
from index nine up to sixteen, have it
refer to run, an error also occurs.
But, imagine that we'd like to change
string s to refer to Learned to Program.
Here's one approach that we can take.
We can use the current value of s and get
the word learn, concatenate that with ed
to make it learned, and concatenate that
with the rest of the string, which is, to
program.
That evaluates to give Learned to Program.
And now that we have this new string,
Learned to Program, we can have s refer to
that instead of it's old value.
Notice that we didn't modify the string
that s originally referred to,
We can't modify it.
Instead, we created a new string and had s
refer to that new string.