Hi, in this video, we'll learn how
to find those witness paths that
we need from the previous video.
So just to remind you,
when we contract node v, then for
any pair of incoming edge from
some node u to node v and
outgoing edge from v to some node w,
we want to check if there
is some witness path from u to
w which doesn't go through v,
has length at most equal to the sum
of those length of two edges.
If there is such path, then there is
no need to add a shortcut from u to w
after contracting v because
the shortest path between u and
w will stay the same even if
we don't add this shortcut.
And search for such witness path
is called a witness search.
So first a few definitions,
let's call a node u a predecessor of
v if there is an edge from u to v,
either directed or undirected.
And also let's call w a successor
of v if there is an edge from
v to w again,
either directed from v to w or undirected.
Now, witness search is
actually very straightforward.
So we need to check for
each predecessor of v, and for
each successor of v, whether there is a
witness path between this predecessor and
the successor that doesn't go through v
and that has a length which is smaller or
equal to the length of the incoming edge
plus the length of the outgoing edge.
So for example, in this picture, for
u1 and w1, we need to find some path.
And it is drawn to the left,
which doesn't go through v and
has length at most 1 plus 1 which is 2.
And also for pair u1 w2,
we need to find also a path,
which is drawn to the right under v,
which doesn't go through v again and
which has length equal to or
smaller than 3, 1 plus 2.
To do that, for each predecessor ui of v,
we just run Dijkstra's algorithm,
regular Dijkstra's algorithm from that ui.
And in that Dijkstra's algorithm
we'll always ignore node v.
So we don't add it to the queue.
We don't extract it from the queue because
we want only the paths that don't go
through node v.
So this is essential for
good query performance.
Because again if we don't do this witness
search, we don't find witness paths.
And we will have to add shortcuts for
every pair of neighbors of v, for
every predecessor and every successor.
And this will add a lot of new
nodes in our augmented graph.
And in a graph with a lot of edges,
it's very hard to find shortest paths.
It will take a long time.
So it is essential for us to find
as many witness paths as we can and
don't add the corresponding shortcuts.
But we also want the preprocessing
to work really fast.
And so
we want to optimize this witness search.
So two ideas for optimization,
first is we can stop Dijkstra's algorithm
when the distance from
the source becomes too big.
Basically, if we search starting
from some predecessor and
the distance from this predecessor to
the node currently extracted is very big,
that cannot be a sure witness
path because it cannot be already
shorter than the sum of the incoming and
outgoing edge.
And this is one idea.
We'll discuss it in detail in a minute.
And also another idea,
we can limit the number of hops.
So we can only allow the Dijkstra's
algorithm starting from
some predecessor to go through at most,
let's say five edges.
If it cannot find a path
to some successor,
we just say that there is no such path,
and we add a shortcut.
Of course, we won't find all
the witness paths this way.
But we will do it fast.
And this is a trade off
between the number of edges,
shortcuts added in the augmented graph,
and the speed of the preprocessing.
So first with the stopping Dijkstra,
so in this example if we found,
in our Dijkstra running from
the node ui some node x,
to which the shortest path is of length 4,
then it is already useless
because this length 4 is more
than the maximum sum of incoming edge
into v plus our going as from v.
So it's 4 is more 1 plus 2 which is 3.
And so there is no way there
can be some witness path
going through x to either w1 or w2
because it will be already longer than 4.
And so it will be longer than the path
from ui to the corresponding w through v.
So in general, if when we extract node x,
extract mean from the queue,
the distance from the source
to this x is already bigger
than the sum of the maximum incoming
edge and the maximum outgoing edge.
There is no witness path going through x.
And so there is no point to
exploring further from x.
We can just stop the algorithm here
because all the nodes which will
extracted further in the Dijkstra's
algorithm will be even further than x
by the property of the general
classic Dijkstra's algorithm.
And so basically, what it means is that we
can limit the distance by the sum of two
edges, the maximum sum of two edges.
And as soon as Dijkstra finds node
which is farther from the source,
we just stop the Dijkstra's algorithm.
There is another small improvement.
But it can make it
significant in practice.
Consider any predecessor w
prime of any successor w of v.
So for example, there can be an edge
from w prime to w2 of length 1.
And then let's see.
For example, we found some path ui as the
source of Djikstra's algorithm to w prime.
And that path has length just 1.
Then we already know that there is
a witness path between the ui and
w2 because the path from ui to
w2 through v has length 2, 3.
And now the path from ui to w2
through w prime has length at most 2
because there is a path from
ui to w prime of length 1.
We go through it.
And then go through edge of length 1.
And we get a path of length just 2
which is shorter than the path to v.
So this is indeed a witness path.
So using this idea, we can just go up
to nodes which are previous to us,
which are predecessors of our
successors of v and then stop there.
So basically what it means is
that we limit our distance by
the difference of the sum of
the two longest incoming and
outgoing edges minus the length
of the last edge on the path,
from some predecessor
to some successor of v.
And then there are two criteria
during the Dijkstra's algorithm.
If we found some w prime, which is
connected directly to some successor of v,
and the distance to w prime plus
the length of this edge is smaller
than the corresponding path from
the source to the corresponding successor,
then we've just found the witness path.
And if the distance to
some node is already
bigger than this maximum of maximums
in the bottom of the slide,
we just stop the Dijkstra's algorithm
because we cannot already find
a witness path,
because all the nodes are already too far.
Another idea for
optimizing the witness search is to
limit the number of hops in Dijkstra.
And by hop,
I mean just the jump through an edge.
So we consider basically only shortest
paths from the source from some
predecessor of v,
which contain at most k edges.
As soon as our Dijkstra's algorithm
considers a node, which is at least
k plus 1 edges from the source,
we don't actually process this node.
We ignore it.
And if a witness path is not found
using this Dijkstra's algorithm,
we just consider it as if
there is no witness path.
And we add a shortcut in
the preprocessing phase.
And so this is a tradeoff
between preprocessing time and
the size of the augmented graph.
If k is small,
then we won't find many witness paths.
And then we will add many shortcuts.
But our preprocessing will be faster.
In practice, you can change k
gradually from the start to the end.
And typically, k is smaller in the start,
for now k = 1.
And then in the A, in the end, k = 5.
And this can be based on the degree of
the vertices that you're contracting.
So these are the ideas for
speeding up the witness search.
And this is all for preprocessing.
So in the next video,
we will study how to actually do
the queries in the preprocess graph,
after we preprocess it by contracting
the nodes and adding the shortcuts.