Hi, in this video, I'll will prove that
the algorithm suggested in the previous
video for finding the distance between
two nodes in the augmented graph
always returns correct result.
First, let's formally
define the augmented graph.
So augmented graph G+,
has the same set of nodes,
V, and has the augmented set of edges, E+,
which contains all the initial edges E of
the graph G along with all the shortcuts
added at the pre-processing stage.
And the lemma states that the distance,
d+(s,t) between any two nodes s and
t in the augmented graph.
Is equal to the distance between
the same nodes in the initial graph.
And note that this makes sense,
because actually the only thing we
are doing is we are adding shortcuts.
And those shortcuts are not shorter then
the path which was initially
between those two nodes.
Just has the same length
as the path through
the contracted node V
in the initial graph.
So, always when we add the shortcut,
we don't do anything but the path.
But, more formally, first thing to know
is that edges are only added to G.
So, if there was some shortest
path between s and t and
G, it will also be present in G+.
And so distance in the augmented graph is,
at most, distance in the initial graph.
But also,
if we add some shortcut from u to w,
then at that moment there was a path
from u to w through v of length
of the h from u to v plus
length of the h from v to w.
But this is equal actually to
the length of the shortcut edit.
So, there was a path before adding
this shortcut from u to w through v.
So, if there is some
shortest path from s to t,
going through this edge (u,w)
in the augmented graph.
Then in the initial graph there
was a path going from s to u,
then from u to v, from v to w and then
from w to t, which has the same length.
So there is a path of the same
length in the initial graph.
And so the distance in the augmented
graph is the same as the distance
in the initial graph.
Now [COUGH] let's also define the rank
of vertex, which is the position
of this vertex In the node order
returned by the pre-processing stage.
So, basically,
it's the importance of the node.
So, if our node was constructed first,
it has rank one.
If it was constructed last, it has rank n,
where n is the number of nodes.
And the higher the rank,
the more important is the node,
the later it was contracted.
Also, lets denote increasing and
decreasing path in the augmented graph.
So a path is increasing ff the ranks of
the nodes of this path in order increase.
And also it is decreasing, again, if the
ranks of the nodes in this path decrease.
And what we want to say is this lemma,
that for any source and
target there is a shortest
path in the augmented graph.
Which is first increasing and
then decreasing.
So, it contains two halfs and the first
half is a path which is increasing,
the second half is a path
which is decreasing and
those two halfs meet in some node V.
This is a Justification of
our Bidirectional Search,
which goes only through edges,
which are going upwards.
So the fourth search goes through
edges upwards to V, and the backwards
search goes from target through backward
edges, which go upwards, also to V.
And then they meet, and if we prove
that there is always the shortest path
of this form, then our algorithm from
the previous video works correctly.
Now let's prove it.
But first,
let's look at this proof of the idea.
So again,
we draw here nodes such that nodes
in the bottom are less important
than the nodes in the top.
And want to prove that for
any source as in any target t,
there is a path of this form when it
first goes up and then goes down.
But what if that's not the case,
what if there is some shortest path but
it's not always going first up then down.
Then there is some node, Uk, for
which it goes first down, then again up.
And so both its neighbors are higher.
Then lets consider the moment
when this node Uk was contracted.
Both its neighbors are higher so
they were contracted later than Uk.
And so when Uk was contracted,
both those notes were on the graph.
And those are neighbors of Uk, so
when it was contracted, two cases.
First, there was a new
shortcut edit in blue,
then what we can do is we can remove
Uk from the shortest path and
then just use the blue edge instead of it.
The length will stay the same because
the length of the shortcut is equal to
the length from Uk-1 to Uk and
then from Uk to Uk+1.
And there is no more
problem with this node Uk.
Which is smaller than both neighbors.
The second case is that
no shortcut was added but
then a witness path was found and
this is drawn in green.
But then all the nodes in the witness path
were present when node Uk was contracted.
So they were contracted later.
So they're actually higher than node Uk.
So when we remove Uk again we can
replace it with a witness path and
we will remove our problem with Uk.
This doesn't prove yet
the general case because there
still can be other places where this
going first up then down is violated.
So now let's prove formally.
So assume for the sake of
contradiction that no such path
from source to target which as far
goes up and then goes down exists.
Then for any shortest path from s to t,
there is some node Ui of this path such
that it's rank is smaller than the ranks
of both neighbors, as in the example.
And recall all such nodes, local minimums.
Then, for any shortest path between s and
t, denote by m(P),
the minimum rank of a local
minimum of this path.
So there can be several
local minimum on this path.
But we denote by m(P) the minimum
rank of all of those.
Now let's consider the shortest
path P* with the maximum
m(P) among all the shortest
paths between s and t.
And then consider the local minimum (Uk)
which has the rank equal to this m(P).
And then there are two cases,
when we're contracting (Uk)
either there was a shortcut
added between (Uk-1) and (Uk+1).
Then there is the shortest path with
the shortcut instead of the current
path from Uk-1 to Uk to Uk+1.
And this shortest path,
P' doesn't contain Uk.
And Uk has the minimum rank of all
the local minima in the path P*.
So m(P') is stricted bigger than m(P*).
And this is a contradiction
with the choice of P*,
which has the maximum m (P)
of all the shortest paths.
In other case,
when we were contracting Uk,
there was a witness
path from Uk-1 to Uk+1.
And it was comprised of
nodes which have high rank,
higher than rank of Uk because
they were contracted after Uk.
And so there is another shortest path
P'' with this witness path instead
of the path Uk-1, Uk, Uk+1.
And again m(P'') is
strictly bigger than m(P*).
Which is again a contradiction
with the choice of P*.
So now we have pre-processing
via node contraction.
We have an algorithm for
querying via Bidirectional Dijkstra
in the augmented graph.
And we have proven that this
algorithm always works correctly.
So, are we done now?
Well, it turns out we are not done yet,
because the question is how
to select the node order.
Our algorithm, so far, doesn't specify how
does it order the nodes for contraction.
And it turns out that the ordering of the
nodes influences the pre-processing time
and the query time very significantly.
And so in the next video, we'll finally
discuss how to order nodes in such
a way that both pre-processing and
query work fast.