Hi, in this video you will learn how
to construct a good node ordering for
the contraction hierarchies algorithm.
So far if you think about it,
our algorithm works correctly for
any node ordering.
If you just choose any order and pass
it to the processing procedure, it will
contract the nodes in this particular
order and return an augmented graph.
If you then run queries on this augmented
graph using the bidirectional Dijkstra
approach from the previous videos,
everything will work correctly because
the correctness proof doesn't
depend on any particular order.
However, this order will influence the
order of operations in the bidirectional
Dijkstra algorithm for the queries.
And actually, it will heavily
influence the time required for
queries and for preprocessing.
So we want to choose a good node ordering,
so that our preprocessing and
our queries are really fast.
First thing we want from the order
is we want to minimize the number of
added shortcuts.
Because each time you add a shortcut,
you add an edge to
the augmented graph in the end.
And the more edges, the slower
your Dijkstra algorithm will work.
So we want less shortcuts.
Second, you want to spread
the important nodes across the map.
because from the common sense,
it follows that there are important big
cities in every sufficiently large
region of the country, of the map.
And then in each state,
if you divide it into sub-regions,
there are still relatively big cities
which are important nodes and so on.
And this should work well in practice.
And third, you also want to minimize
somehow the number of edges in
the shortest paths in general
in the augmented graph.
So basically, you want to make your graph
look less like a road network graph and
more like a social network graph, where
bidirectional Dijkstra algorithm is so
much faster than the regular
Dijkstra's algorithm.
Because any two nodes in the social
network are at most six edges away.
And then bidirectional Dijkstra finds,
with forward surge and
backward surge,
in just three steps they meet each other.
You want the same in
the augmented graph and
you can somehow become close to it by
adding shortcuts in the right places.
So in general,
you want these three things.
Now we'll discuss how to do that.
So we want to order nodes
by some importance, so
we need to introduce a measure
of importance for that.
And then, we will at each step
contract the least important node.
However, when we contract a node,
the properties of the nodes which
are neighbors of this node can change.
And then importance can also change for
those nodes after that.
So in general,
the algorithm will work as following.
We'll keep all the nodes in a priority
queue ordered by importance, so
that we can extract the least
important nodes very fast.
But of course, priority will be
something like minus importance so
that the hat of the priority queue
contains the least important node,
not the most important one.
Then, on each iteration we will
extract the least important node.
And we want to contract this node, but
first we need to recompute its importance.
Because it could have changed because
of the contractions of the other nodes.
Then, we need to compare its new
updated importance with the importances
of all the other nodes.
And to do that, we will take
the hat of the priority queue.
Because we've already extracted
these nodes from the priority queue,
it's no longer there.
So we will compare
the importance of this node
with the smallest importance of all
the nodes which are still in the queue.
If the importance of the extracted
node is still minimal,
then we can safely contract it,
it's the least important node.
Otherwise, we will need to put it
back into the priority queue so
that we can extract a node with
even smaller priority from it.
Of course this is only approximate,
because at some point we could extract
the node's recomputed importance and
then decide that it has really the least
importance of all the nodes in the queue.
However, there is some other node which
is still in the queue which has a smaller
importance, but we haven't yet recomputed
it and so we don't know about that.
And that's okay,
we will try just to order the nodes
approximately by this importance.
Also, it can seem that this process
can go on and on indefinitely.
But we'll show that it will actually
stop after a finite number of
iterations, always.
Why is that?
Well, if we dont contract the node,
we update its importance and
it actually changes.
And after that, its importance is
corresponding to the current set of
nodes which are still not contracted.
And after at most number
of nodes attempts,
all the nodes will have
updated importance.
And then, the node with the minimum
updated importance will be
contracted after that,
because it will be extracted and
it will have the smallest
importance at that point.
And then when we recompute its importance,
it will turn out to be the same because
it already has updated importance.
And then we will just contract this node.
So eventually this kind of
iteration always contracts a node.
And in practice, it usually takes one or
two iterations usually,
to actually contract something.
So this works typically fast.
Now, we'll talk about
the importance criteria.
So first is edge difference.
It is related to the number
of shortcuts added and
minimizing the number of
edges in the augmented graph.
Second one down is number
of contracted neighbors.
And this is related to spreading
the nodes across the map.
So if there are already many neighbors
of this node which already contracted,
then we will probably contract
some node in some other place.
Because we want to spread important
nodes and also spread unimportant nodes.
We don't want everything to
be clustered in one region.
Also, shortcut cover is connected with how
important that node is,
how unavoidable it is.
Do you remember the picture with an island
between San Francisco and Oakland?
The treasure island which was unavoidable
if you go from San Francisco to Oakland,
if you want to go with the shortest path?
So shortcut cover will somehow
approximate how unavoidable a node is.
And the last one, the node level,
has something to do with the number
of edges in the shortest
paths in the augmented graph.
So now we'll go through
all of these in detail.
So Edge Difference.
You basically want to minimize the number
of edges in the augmented graph.
So when we try to contract the node,
v, we can actually compute
how many shortcuts would be added
if we actually contract this node.
We can also always compute
the number of incoming edges, and
number of outgoing edges of any node.
And then we can compute
the edge difference.
The number of shortcuts added
minus number of edges deleted,
which is the degree of this node.
And this is called edge difference.
And the number of edges increases by
edge difference after contracting v.
So this influences both the number
of edges in the final graph and
also the number of edges in
the graph being preprocessed.
Which is important because it
influences the preprocessing time.
So what we want is to contract nodes
with small edge differences first.
Contracted Neighbors,
I already talked about this.
We want to contract a node with small
number of already contracted neighbors, so
that the nodes which we contract
don't cluster in one place, but
they're actually spread out in
all the regions of the graph.
Shortcut Covers, very important.
Basically it says how
many nodes are there,
such that we cannot avoid visiting our
node if we want to go to those nodes.
More formally, if we have some node,
v, we can do the number of neighbors,
w of v, such that we have to
create a shortcut, either to w or
from w in the case we need to contract v.
And this basically means
that when we contract v,
we'll lose some shortest path to w.
And that's why we need to
create an additional shortcut.
And so v is important for w, and
if v is important for many, its neighbors,
then it's important.
And so, we need to first contract
nodes with small importance,
with small shortcut cover.
Node level is an upper bound on
the number of edges in the shortest
path from any node s to node
v in the augmented graph.
It can be shown formally
that this is an upper bound,
but I'll tell you the intuition.
So we initialize the level with 0.
And then when we contract some node v,
we update the level of its neighbors.
So for a neighbor u of v, either we could
get to u somehow without going through v,
and then contracting v
doesn't influence its level.
Or we could go to u through node v.
But then to go to node v,
we needed at most,
level of v edges, and
then one more to get from v to u.
So that's why L(u) needs to
be maximized by L(v) + 1.
So in the end,
L(v) is an upper bound on the number of
edges on the shortest path to v.
And so we want to contract
nodes with small level,
because first,
we need to contract non-important nodes.
In the end we proposed
the following importance measure.
We just sum up all those four values.
Note that this is a heuristic value, and
you can actually play with weights of
those four quantities in the importance
and see how preprocessing time and
query time change.
But we think that just summing them
up will already work really well.
However, each of the four quantities
is necessary for fast preprocessing and
queries.
If you avoid implementing
at least one of them,
probably preprocessing or
query time will be too long.
But then you can further
optimize with the coefficients.
For example,
two times added distance plus three
times contracted neighbors, and so on.
So it also means that you need to
find a way to compute all of these
quantities efficiently at any
stage of the preprocessing.
Both in the beginning,
and also when you need to
contract a node but you've already
contracted some other nodes.
This is not very hard and
we'll leave this as an exercise to you.
So, we did a lot of work.
We've come up with a preprocessing stage.
We need a particular node
ordering with that and
we've come up with a complex
importance measure for nodes for that.
And also we need to do
bidirectional Dijkstra, but
not classical bidirectional Dijkstra.
We need to do some tweaks
in the query stage.
So, is it all worth it?
It turns out that yes,
it is well worth it.
If we take for example, a graph of
Europe with 18 million nodes, and
launch the classical
Dijkstra's algorithm on it.
And we generate random pairs of vertices
in different places of Europe and
then compute the shorter distances.
Then on average,
it will work for 4.3 seconds.
However, if we launch
Contraction Hierarchies on
the same graph with the same
pairs of vertices and
we tweak the heuristics inside
the contraction hierarchy as well.
It will work on average just for
18 milliseconds,
which is almost 25000 times faster.
So it is very well worth it.
For example, for
a service like Google Maps or Yandex Maps,
working 25000 times faster means
that you actually can provide
your service to millions of users and
do it blazingly fast.
And the speed-up will only increase
if you increase the size of a graph.
For example, if you go from the graph of
Europe to the graph of the whole world,
the speed-up will only increase.
So now, it seems that we know everything.
We know how to preprocess by
contracted nodes, ordered
approximately by their importance and
we have some importance measure for that.
We know how to query using
bidirectional Dijkstra algorithm.
And our importance function is heuristic,
but
works really well on road network graphs.
And this algorithm works 1000s
of times faster than Dijkstra.
If you tweak it really well, it can work
even tens of thousands times faster.
But at least 1000s of times faster,
this is what is guaranteed for
your own implementations.
You will try to do that in the programming
assignments of this project for
this module.
And you will see that your
solutions are actually much,
much faster than the classical algorithm.
And you will need them to work
1000s of times faster to actually
pass the assignment.
And also, we actually encourage you to
compete on the forums on whose solutions
is the fastest.
So you can take the result by the grader
and then post it on the forums, and
someone can organize the result
table with the top results.
And it's very interesting how you can
come up with your own heuristics for
improving this algorithm.
Because you see there are a lot of
heuristics in the last part of this
lecture, and you can come up with your
own ideas and maybe they will be so
good that you will speed up everyone
else's solution 10 times or 100 times.
So really try to do that.
We will also show you some pointers
to where you can get the data for
real graphs of the road networks of
some parts of US and the whole US.
And in the end, this could become your own
Open Source project which you could show,
for example, to potential employers.
So we wish you good luck with
advanced shortest paths.