Figuring out how to get
the error derivatives for
all of the weights in a multi
line network is the key to
being able to learn
efficiently in these networks.
But there are a number of other issues
that have to be addressed before we
actually get a learning procedure
that's fully specified.
For example, we need to decide
how often to update the weights.
And we need to decide how to prevent
the network from over fitting very badly
if we use a large network.
The backpropagation algorithm is an
efficient way to compute the derivatives
with the respect to each weight of
the error for a single training case.
But that's not a learning algorithm.
You have to specify a number of other
things to get a proper learning procedure.
We need to make lots of other decisions.
Some of these decisions are about
how we're going to optimize.
That is, how we're going to use the error
derivatives on the individual cases
to discover a good set of weights.
Those will be described
in detail in lecture six.
Another set of issues is how to ensure
that the weights that we've learned
will generalize well.
That is, how do we make sure they work on
cases that we didn't see during training?
And lecture seven will be
devoted to that issue.
What I'm going to do now is
give you a very brief overview
of these two sets of issues.
So optimization issues are about
how you use the weight derivatives.
The first question is,
how often should you update the weights?
We could try updating the weights
after each training case.
So you compute the error derivatives on
a training case using backpropagation,
and then you make a small
change to the weights.
Obviously this is going to zig zag around,
because on each training case,
you'll get different error derivatives.
But on average,
if we make the weight changes small
enough, it'll go in the right direction.
What seems more sensible is to use full
batch training where you do a full sweep
through all of the training data, you add
together all of the error derivatives you
get on the individual cases, and then
you take a small step in that direction.
A problem with this is that we start
off with a bad set of weights.
And we might have a very big training set.
And we don't want to do all that work
of going through the whole training set
in order to fix up some weights
that we know are pretty bad.
Really, we only need to look at
a few training cases before we get
a reasonable idea of what direction
we want to move the weights in.
And we don't need to look at a large
number of training cases until we get
towards the end of learning.
So that gives us mini-batch learning,
where we take a small
random sample of the training cases and
we go in that direction.
We'll do a little bit of zig zagging, not
nearly as much zig zagging as if we did
online where we use one
training case at a time.
And mini-batch learning is
what people typically do when
they're training big neural
networks on big data sets.
Then there's the issue of how
much we update the weights,
how big a change we make.
So we could just by hand try and
pick some fixed learning rate.
And then learn the weights by changing
each weight by the derivative
that we've computed times
that learning rate.
It seems more sensible to
actually adapt the learning rate.
We could get the computer to adapt it by,
if we're oscillating around,
if the error keeps going up and down,
then we'll reduce the learning rate.
But if we're making steady progress,
we might increase the learning rate.
We might even have a separate learning
weight for each connection in the network,
so that some weights learn rapidly and
other weights learn more slowly.
Or we might go even further and
say, we don't really want to go in
the direction of steepest descent at all.
If you look at the figure on the right,
when we had a very elongated ellipse,
the direction of steepest descent is
almost at right angles to the direction to
the minimum that we want to find.
And this is typical,
particularly towards the end of learning,
of most learning problems.
So there's much better directions to go in
than the direction of steepest descent.
The problem is it's quite hard
to figure out what they are.
The second set of issues is to
do with how well the network
generalizes to cases it
didn't see during training.
And the problem here is that
the training data contains information
about the regularities In
the mapping from input to output.
But it also contains two types of noise.
The first type of noise is that
the target values may be unreliable.
And for neural noise,
that's usually only a minor worry.
The second type of noise is
that there's sampling error.
If we take any particular training set,
especially if it's a small one, there will
be accidental regularities that are caused
by the particular cases that we chose.
So for example, if you show someone
some polygons, if you're a bad teacher,
you might choose to show them a square and
a rectangle.
Those are both polygons but there's no
way for someone to realize from that,
that polygons might have three sides or
seven sides, there's no way for
them to understand that the angles
don't have to be right angles.
If you're a slightly better teacher
you might show them a triangle and
a hexagon, but
again, from that they can't tell whether
the polygons are always convex, and they
can't tell whether the angles on polygons
are always multiples of 60 degrees.
And however carefully you choose examples,
for
any finite set of examples,
there'll be accidental regularities.
Now when we fit a model, there's no
way it can tell the difference between
an accidental regularity that's just
there because of the particular samples
we chose, and a real regularity that
we'll generalize properly to new cases.
So what the model will do is it
will fit both kinds of regularity.
And if you've got a big, powerful model,
it'll be very good at
fitting the sampling error.
And that will be a real disaster.
That will cause it to
generalize really badly.
This is best understood by
looking at a little example.
So, here we've got six data
points shown in black.
And we can fit a straight line to them.
That's a model that has two
degrees of freedom, and
it's fitting the six Y values,
given the six X values.
Or we can fit a polynomial that
has six degrees of freedom.
And by hand, I've drawn in red
my idea of a polynomial with six
degrees of freedom fitting this data.
And you'll see the polynomial goes
through the data points exactly and so
it's a much better fit to the data,
but which model do you trust?
The complicated model certainly fits the
data much better but it's not economical.
For a model to be convincing,
what you want it to do
is be a simple model that explains
a lot of data surprisingly well.
And the polynomial doesn't do that.
It explains these six data points,
but it's got six degrees of freedom.
So wherever these data points were
it will be able to explain them.
We're not surprised that a model this
complicated can fit that data very well,
and it doesn't convince us
that this is a good model.
So if you look at the arrow, which output
value do you predict for this input value?
Well you'd have to have a lot of
faith in the polynomial model in
order to predict a value that's outside
the range of values in all of the training
data you've seen so far.
And I think almost everybody would
prefer to predict the blue circle that's
on the green line rather than
the one on the red line.
However, if we had ten times as much data,
and all of these data points lay
very close to the red line, then we
would certainly prefer the red line.
There's a number of ways to reduce
overfitting that have been developed for
neural networks and for many other models.
And I'm going to give just
a brief survey of them here.
There's weight-decay, where you try and
keep the weights of the networks small.
We'll try and
keep many of the weights at 0.
And the idea of this is that it
will make the model simpler.
There's weight sharing where again, you
make the model simpler by insisting that
many of the weights have exactly
the same value as each other.
You don't know what the value is and
you're going to learn it but
it has to be exactly the same for
many of the weights.
We'll see that in the next lecture
how weight-sharing is used.
There's early stopping,
where you make yourself a fake test set.
And as you're training the net, you peak
at what's happening on this fake test set.
And once the performance on the fake
test set starts getting worse,
you stop training.
There's model averaging, where you
train lots of different neural nets.
And you average them together in
the hopes that that will reduce
the errors you're making.
There's Bayesian fitting of neural nets,
which is really just a fancy
form of model averaging.
There's dropout, where you try and
make your model more robust
by randomly emitting hidden
units when you're training it.
And there's generative pre-training,
which is somewhat more complicated,
and I'll describe towards
the end of the course.