Hi, in this module you will study
shortest paths in graphs and
algorithms to find them.
These algorithms have
lots of applications.
For example, when you want to
go from one city to another,
you don't want to switch
your transport many times.
And in the travel planning systems, there
are algorithms that help you to minimize
the number of such switches, for example,
to get from Hamburg to Moscow with
the minimum possible
number of flight segments.
When you start a navigation app on your
smartphone to get home from work faster,
one of these algorithms is used to
give you the fastest route possible.
Also, one of these algorithms is
used right now to direct the network
packets with data through the Internet so
that you can watch this video online.
In this module,
we will start with the most direct
route problem about flight segments.
We will then consider the problem
of getting from point A to point B
with the fastest possible route.
And in the end, we'll consider
the problem about currency exchange,
which doesn't seem to be a problem
about graphs or shortest paths, but
actually the same algorithms will help
you to exchange currency in the optimal,
most profitable way.
Let's start with the most
direct route problem.
It is formulated very simply.
What is the minimum number of flight
segments to get from one city to another?
For example, if we look at this map
you could go from Hamburg to Moscow
with five flight segments, but
this is obviously not optimal because
you could go from Hamburg to
Moscow with a direct flight.
We can consider it as a graph problem on a
graph where nodes correspond to cities and
directed edges correspond to available
flights from one city to another.
The edges are directed because
flights can be available one way and
not available another one, for example,
because there are no tickets left.
And, of course, in the typical real world
graph there are many more cities and
many more possible flights but
this is just an illustrative example.
So here the graph problem is
to get from node correspondent
to Hamburg to node
correspondent to Moscow.
And one way to do that is to use
these five edges corresponding
to the five flight segments
we saw on the map,
but this is obviously not optimal in
terms of minimization of number of edges.
For example, we could get from
Hamburg to Paris first, and
then from Paris to Moscow, and
that would be just two edges.
Or in this case, you could go just
directly from Hamburg to Moscow,
and obviously this is the optimal way,
to use just one flight segment,
which is not always possible.
For example,
to get from Hamburg to Helsinki,
you'd need at least three
edges on this graph.
Also notice that as soon as we
formulate it as a graph problem,
we don't need to name the nodes
like Hamburg or Moscow.
We can just name them to A,
B, C, D, E, and
then solve the problem
on an abstract graph.
So let's talk about paths and graphs.
So, we define length of the path L(P),
where P is the path,
as the number of edges in this path.
For example,
if we consider the path from D to B,
which consists of edges from D to E,
then from E to S, from S to A,
and from A to B,
then the length of this path is 4.
And note that this is an undirected graph,
but
we will also look at
the directed example soon.
Another example of a path is from
D to B again, but through S.
From D to S to C to B, and
the length of this path is 3.
Now the distance between two vertices or
nodes in the graph is the length of
the shortest possible path between them.
For example, the distance between D and
B is just 3 because this is the path from
D to B which contains just three edges,
and there are no paths that
contains less than three edges.
And the distance from C to A is just 2,
because there is a path through S.
There is another one through B,
which is also of length 2,
but there is no direct edge from C to A.
The situation changes a little bit when
the graph is directed because not all
edges can be taken.
And so distance from D to B in this graph,
which looks like the same but
has directed edges, is now 4 instead
of 3 in the undirected case.
This is because we cannot take the edge
from D to S because it is directed
in the wrong direction.
So distance from D to B is 4 because
there is this path in green and
there is no shorter path.
And the distance from C to
A in this case is infinity
because there is actually no path from C
to A, because you cannot go from C to F.
And even if you go from C to B,
it cannot go from B to A because
the edge is going the wrong direction.
Now let's consider the paths
from some origin node S.
It turns out that to find the shortest
path from A to B is not simpler
than finding shortest paths from
A to all other nodes in the graph,
or at least almost all
the other nodes in the graph.
And so we will be studying the problem
of finding shortest path from
one starting node S to all
other nodes in the graph.
When we select the starting node,
we can lay out the same graph in
a different way using distance layers.
In this case,
we have three distance layers.
The first one is layer 0,
which contains just node S,
which is a distance 0 from itself.
Then we have layer 1, which contains
four nodes a distance 1 from node S.
And then we have layer 2,
which contains just one node, B,
which is a distance 2 from node S.
If we added another node to this graph,
for example,
node F, which is only connected with B,
then it will have 4 layers, and
additional layer 3 contains just node F,
which is a distance 3 from node S.
Note that there cannot be an edge
from D to F in such layered graph
because otherwise there would be
a path from S to F of length 2, S, D,
F, and then F would be in the layer 2 and
there would be no layer 3.
And another example is that there cannot
be an edge from S to F because in this
case the distance from S to F would be
1 and so F would be in the layer 1.
And again there wouldn't be no layer 3.
And the general property is that
the only edges which are allowed
in such layered graph are edges
inside the layer, like edge from D
to E in this example, and
edges between a layer and the next layer,
like edges from S to layer 1, edges
from A and C to B, and edge from B to F.
Now let's consider the directed case.
We directed all the edges downwards and
so the layers didn't change.
We still have layer 0 with just S,
layer 1 with four nodes, and layers 2 and
3 with nodes B and F correspondingly.
What about additional edges here?
For example, can F be connected to D?
So yes, it can be connected to D,
but in this direction, from F to D,
because this edge from F to D doesn't
give us any shorter path from S to F.
And so
the shortest path is still of length 3.
Also, it is possible to connect F
directly to S in this direction, or
to connect B directly to S because
the shortest paths don't change.
However, it is not possible
to add an edge from C to F,
because if we add this edge,
the layer structure will change.
because the distance from S to F will
be just 2, from S to C and from C to F.
And the general property is that
there cannot be any edge from a layer
to another layer which is
farther from S by at least two.
So there can be an edge from
a layer to the next layer.
There can be an edge
within the layer's edges,
an edge from D to E in this example.
And there can be an edge from a layer
to any of the previous layers,
such as the green edges in this example.
But there cannot be any red edges,
such as an edge from C to F,
which is an edge from
the layer 1 to the layer 3,
which is at least farther
by two from S than layer 1.
So there cannot be any such edges
in the layered distance graph.
And in the next video,
we will discuss an efficient algorithm
to traverse the graph layer by layer so
that in the end every node is
assigned to some layer, and we know
the distance to this node as the number
of the layer to which it was assigned.