Hi, in this video we will discuss
breadth-first search an efficient
algorithm to find distances from an origin
node to all the nodes in the graph.
And we will use the layered
distance structure
of the graph from the previous video.
We will start from the version of the
algorithm which is easier to understand.
We marked as S a blue node
which will be our origin, and
we will find distances from this
origin to all the nodes in the graph.
We'll start with a state when all
the nodes are colored in white.
And the node colored in white means that
this node hasn't yet been discolored.
During the algorithm, we'll discover some
nodes, and then we will process them.
When we discover the node
we cover it with grey.
At first, we discover the origin node S.
And when we process the node
we cover it with black.
And of course after discovering
the origin node, we start processing.
We will process the graph layer by layer.
We'll start with layer zero,
which only consists of the node S and
we'll start processing it.
When we start processing a layer, we take
all of the edges outgoing from this layer
and we discover all of
the nodes ends of those edges.
So basically when we start from layer
zero, we discover the whole layer one
because the edges from the layer
zero node, S, go to layer one nodes.
Of course there could be an additional
edge from S to itself, but
then we would ignore this edge because it
goes to the node we've already discovered.
In this case, there is no such edge, so
all the ends of the edges going from
S are new nodes, white nodes,
which are not yet discovered and
we color them with gray to mark
the fact that we have discovered them.
After we have discovered all of them,
all the layer one we start processing
all those nodes simultaneously.
So we process all six
nodes of the layer one.
And to do that we take all the edges
outgoing from those nodes and
discover the new nodes at
the ends of those edges.
You may notice that there
are a few red edges.
And those are the edges which go
from the nodes in layer one, but
which go to the nodes which were
already discovered previously to S and
to the nodes of the same layer one.
And there are a lot of bold black edges,
which go also from the nodes of the layer
one, which we are not processing, but
they go to the new nodes,
which were not discovered previously.
And we mark those nodes with gray.
And when we process edges from the layer
one we get all the nodes of the layer two,
because the edges from layer one go
to layer two to the same layer and
to the previous layers.
When edges go to the same layer or to
previous layers, we mark them with red and
we don't do anything with the nodes
on the ends of those edges.
And the edges go to the next layer,
we discover nodes of the next layer.
And of course,
all the nodes of the next layer,
of the layer two,
have some incoming edge from layer one.
So after processing layer one,
we've discovered the whole layer two.
And after we've discovered it,
we start processing it.
So we process the outer circle,
all the nodes from the layer two.
And to that we consider all their
edges which are outgoing from them.
And you see that there are only red edges
because all the edges from layer two
go to either the same layer two or
to S or to layer one nodes.
And all of them have been
discovered before that, so
we don't do anything with those nodes.
So we don't discover any new nodes.
And it means that we don't have
anything new to process, so
our algorithm stops with that.
And we now can assign
each node to a layer.
Obviously node s, origin node,
is in the layer 0.
The nodes we discovered on the first
step are the nodes of the letter 1.
So, they're at the distance 1 from S.
And the nodes discovered on the next
step are nodes of the letter 2,
and they're at distance 2 from S.
And so, we've found distances from
S to all the nodes in the graph.
But actually not to all of them,
because there can be some nodes
which are not connected to S,
which are not reachable from S.
And such nodes must have
infinite distance from S.
And we'll solve this issue by
initializing all the distances from
S to all other nodes with infinity.
And then, setting the distance
from S itself to 0 and
implementing the algorithm
that I've just told you.
Then every node,
which is reachable from S,
will get some finite distance from S, and
all the nodes which are unreachable from
S, will stay with their infinite distance.
Now let's look how this same algorithm
will work with an undirected graph.
So we have basically the same graph,
we just removed the arrows from the edges.
So all the edges became undirected,
and again we have the same origin S,
marked with blue.
We start with all the nodes being white,
because they are not discovered yet, we
discover node S, and color it with grey.
And then we start processing it, and
color it with black to process it without
take all the edges outgoing from it.
And you see that now there
are more edges outgoing from S,
because some of the edges which are
incoming into S in the previous example,
now are also outgoing from S
because they are undirected edges.
So, we discovered seven nodes instead
of six, as in the previous example.
And after we discovered all these
seven nodes, this is our layer one.
These are all the nodes
of distance one from S.
We discovered them.
Now, we start processing them.
And to do that, we consider all the edges
out going from those seven nodes.
All black ones, but for S.
And you see that some red edges appear.
Those are edges inside layer one, and
edges from layer one to S, and
there are a lot of bold black edges.
Those are the edges from the nodes
of layer one to the new nodes,
which are not discovered before.
And we've discovered almost all
the nodes of the outer circle, but for
the one in the bottom which
was discovered before.
So we have discovered 11 new nodes.
We have discovered them, and
now we need to process them.
And to do that, we consider all
the edges outgoing from those 11 nodes.
And all of those edges
are red because they all
go to the nodes we previously discovered.
So nothing new is discovered and
we stop our algorithm.
And now we can assign distances.
And again,
distance from S to itself is zero.
Distance from S to the nodes discovered in
the first step is one, this is layer one.
And distance from S to the 11
nodes in the outer circle is two.
This is our layer too.
And again we've found all
the distances from S.
And we have found all the layers, and
also if there are some nodes which are not
connected with us initially,
we initialize the distances to infinity.
And so, they stay with this
infinite distance to them.