This is basically how the algorithm works,
and
this is more or
less clear that it defines distances
correctly because it just goes
through the graph layer by layer.
But to actually implement the algorithm,
we need to do everything turn by turn.
We cannot just take a couple of nodes and
process them simultaneously.
We need to have some order on those nodes.
And now let's solve this problem.
So we return to our initial example
of a directed graph with S origin.
And now we want to process
each node one by one.
To achieve that, instead of processing
each layer of nodes simultaneously,
we will have a queue of notes.
So the nodes will get into the queue and
wait for their turn.
And as soon as every node which was in the
queue before this node has already been
processed, this node goes out of
the queue, and it is being processed.
So, when we discover node,
we put it into a queue.
And when we need to process it,
we take it from the queue and process it.
And it means that the nodes
which were discovered earlier
will also be processed earlier.
And so, in general the order
of layers won't change because
first layer 0 nodes will
get into the queue,
then all the nodes from layer
1 will get into the queue.
And then after they all are processed,
we'll process nodes of layer 2,
which were discovered
after notes of layer one.
Now let's see how all it works.
So we discovered node S, and
we already know by that time
that the distance to S is 0.
It is layer 0 and
there are no more nodes in the layer 0.
Now we start processing this node,
and to do that,
we process the edges outgoing
from S in some order.
It doesn't mean which is the order.
It can be just the order in which they
were saved in our data structure for
the graph.
So we chose our first edge, and
we discover node to the right.
And we know that the distance to this node
is 1 because this is a layer 1 node we
discovered.
And instead of starting to process it,
we go to the next edge from S and
we discover another node of layer 1 and
assign the distance to 1, and
again, and again, again, and again.
And so now, we have discovered
all the nodes from the layer 1.
And we put them all in
the queue in the order
starting from the node to the right and
counterclockwise order.
So now we've processed our node S and
we need to process something else.
What to process?
The node which is the first in the queue,
and this is the node to the right from S.
So we start processing this node.
And to go through the edges from this
node in the order they were saved.
I don't know that order, so let's see.
Okay, so the first edge
outgoing from this node was to
another node from the first layer.
So it is a red edge because it goes to the
node which has already been discovered.
We don't do anything with this edge.
Then the next edge goes to the right,
and we discover a node from layer 2,
which is to the right, and
we set its distance to 2.
Then the edge goes to the node right and
up,
and we also assign distance
to this node to 2.
And the last edge goes to the node
to right and down from our node.
And it also gets distance 2
because this is a layer 2 node.
And what we do next?
We've processed our node to the right from
S and we need to process something else.
And this something else is
the next node from the layer 1 in
the counterclockwise order.
This is this node to the right and
up from node S.
We'll start processing it.
In some order we'll process edges from it.
So the first edge is a red edge to the
left, and we don't do anything with it.
And the second edge is a red edge
to the node to the right and
up from it, which is familiar too, but
it has also been already discovered.
And then the next edge gives
us new nodes from layer 2.
And the next one also gives
us a new node from layer 2.
So we finished processing this node and
we go to the next one.
Again, red edge,
red edge, new node discovered, new node
discovered, next node from layer one.
Our red edge, our red edge,
a new node from layer 2, and new node.
And again,
with another node from layer 1 and
the last node from layer 1, we process it.
Okay, so we've processed
all the nodes from layer 1.
We've discovered all the nodes
from layer 2 in some order.
I don't even remember
the order of those nodes.
It is mostly counterclockwise but
not completely.
So let's see In the slides,
what is the correct order?
So the first one to be discovered
was the node to the right.
And start processing it, and there is
a red edge from it, and another one.
And there are no more
edges from this node so
we'll start processing the next
one in the counterclockwise order.
And there is a red edge from it, and
it looks like there are no more edges from
it, so we finished processing this node.
And then we go to the node
to the right and down, and
there is a red edge from it,
and that's all.
And so, we go through the nodes in the
second layer and all the edges from them
are obviously red because we've discovered
everything that's connected to S already.
So we go and
test that all the edges are red, and
now we've finished, and
again we have the graph which is layered.
Node S is in the layer 0,
6 nodes in the layer 1,
and 12 nodes in the layer 2.
And if we have some node
which was not connected to S,
then it stays with the distance
estimate of infinity.
So this is how breadth first search
actually works, and in the next video
we will discuss the pseudocode that
actually implements this algorithm.