Hi.
In this video,
we will prove the correctness of
the breadth-first search algorithm for
finding distances from an original
node to all the nodes in the graph.
We will also prove some properties of this
algorithm, which can be useful when you
want to extend this algorithm
to other kinds of problems.
First, recall that node u is
called reachable from node S,
if there is a path from S to u.
And the lemma states that the reachable
nodes are discovered during breadth-first
search.
And they get a finite
estimate of distance from S.
And unreachable nodes are not
discovered during breadth-first search.
And they stay with infinite distance
estimate, infinite distance value.
First, let's prove it for reachable nodes.
So, suppose for the sake of contradiction
that some reachable nodes were
not discovered during
the breadth-first search.
Then select out of those
nodes the one closest to S in
terms of the length of the path.
So, let's assume that u is
the closest to S unreachable node,
which was not discovered during
the breadth-first search.
Then take the shortest path,
some shortest path from S to u.
It goes from S to some nodes
of v1 from there to v2 and so
on and up to vk and from vk it goes to u.
Then u will be discovered,
actually, while processing vk.
Why is that?
Well, because first,
we will discover and process S.
Then we will discover and process v1.
Then we will discover and
process v2 and so on.
And we will go up to vk.
And when we process vk,
u will be discovered.
So this is a contradiction with
the assumption we made for
the sake of contradiction that
some reachable node is not discovered
during breadth-first search.
So we proved that reachable
nodes are discovered.
And of course,
they will find its estimation of distance.
Because this is how the algorithm works.
As soon as the node is discovered, it gets
estimation of distance, bigger by one,
than the estimation for
the node b process.
Now let's prove this statement
about unreachable nodes.
Let's suppose, again, for
the sake of contradiction that some
unreachable nodes were discovered.
And let u be the first such
unreachable node to be discovered.
Now let's see when it was discovered.
It was discovered while
processing some other node v.
And as u is the first unreachable
node that was discovered and
v was discovered before u, because u is
discovered when v is already processed,
it means that v is a reachable node.
And it means that there is
a path from s to v, but
then it means that there is
a path from s to u through v.
So u is actually reachable, and this is
a contradiction, and so we proved that
unreachable nodes are not discovered
during the breadth-first search.
So it works correctly at least in
the sense that it finds some distances to
reachable nodes and doesn't find any
finite distances to unreachable notes.
Now we will prove the order lemma,
which states something about
the order in which nodes are discovered
and dequeued from the queue.
It says that by the time some
node u at distance d from
the original node is dequeued,
it started processing.
All the nodes at distance at most
d have already been discovered.
So they have already been
enqueued in the queue.
And maybe some of them have
already been processed.
Some of them are still in the queue, but
at least,
they have already been discovered.
So let's prove this
again by contradiction.
Suppose that this lemma is not true and
considered the first time
this order was broken, so
that some node u at distance d has already
started processing, and
that's why it is filled with black.
And some other node v at distance d',
which is at most d has not yet
been discovered.
Let's suppose that.
So we know that d' is at most d,
and we know that node u
was discovered while
processing some other node u'.
And we know that the distance
to this node u' is at least d-1,
because if the distance
to u' was less than d-1,
then the distance to u would be less than
d because there's an edge from u' to u.
Also, we know that the node
v has an edge from
some node v' with distance d'-1 from s,
because there is some
shortest path from s to v.
And there is the previous node before
v on this path, and this is v'.
And distance to v' is exactly d'-1,
because this is a shortest path.
So, it can be less than
d'-1 because otherwise,
distance to v will be less than d'.
And it cannot be bigger
than d'-1 because then
the shortest path to v
would be longer than d'.
So, distance from s to d' is exactly d'-1.
And we know that the prime is at most d,
and from that,
we know that d'-1 is at most d-1.
And it means that v' was discovered before
u' was dequeued because we know that
the first time that order lemma
was wrong was with nodes u and v.
And now u' and v' were before that.
So that point of time
order lemma still works.
So we know that v' was discovered
before u' was dequeued.
So it means that v' was gray
before u' became black.
[COUGH] And this means that also,
v' became gray before u became gray,
because u became gray while processing u'.
So v' was enqueued and
filled with gray before u was enqueued,
discovered, and filled with gray.
What that means is that because our
queue works as first in first out, and
v' was discovered before u, it means that
v' was also started processing before u.
So v' was dequeued and
filled with black before u was dequeued,
and immediately after v' was dequeued,
v would be discovered,
because there is an edge from v' to v.
So either v was discovered
even before that, or
it was discovered during processing v'.
And we see that v is already discovered,
and u is not yet dequeued.
So it is a contradiction with the fact
that when u is already black,
v was still white and not discovered.
So we proved our order
lemma by contradiction.