How do we reconstruct the shortest
path given the shortest path tree?
So, the nice property of the shortest
path tree is that it somehow
contains all of the shortest paths
from the origin to all the nodes.
Why is that?
Because if we go by edge
of the shortest path tree,
we decrease the distance exactly by what?
So if we start with some node, and
go by edges of shortest path tree
by directed edges one by one.
We will each time decrease
the distance by one.
And so it means that if
the distance to the node was D,
then exactly after D steps,
we will end up in the origin node.
Because we will be at distance zero.
So, we will make D steps.
We will have a path of length D,
where D is the shortest path
length from S to this node.
So we'll have the shortest path itself
because its length is the same as distance
to this node.
So what do we need to do in the code?
We write down the procedure
reconstruct path, which takes in
the origin node as the node U for
which we need to construct the path,
and the prev,
which BFS procedure builds for us.
And the results variable
will store the path itself.
So we will start with an empty path.
And then, we'll go back from
node U until we come to node S.
So we start with our node U, and
while it is not yet equal to S.
We append it to the shortest path, and
then we go by the edge of the shortest
path tree by assigning prev of U to U.
And the we repeat, repeat,
repeat it until we come to node S.
And U will be equal to S, and
our while loop will start.
By this time, we have the shortest path
from S to U in the result variable, but
for one thing.
It is in the reverse order so
we have first the And note which is U.
Then we have the prev of U,
then prev of prev of U, and so on up to S.
So the path is in the reverse order.
So to return the actual shortest
path from origin to node U.
We need to reverse this path and
then, we return the result.
So of course this procedure works fast,
it only needs
amount of steps which is equal to
the distance from node S to node U.
Which is definitely less than or equal to
number of nodes in the graph for example.
But in most cases,
it will be even less than that.
So in conclusion, we can now find
the minimum number of flight
segments to get from one city to another,
if we have the graph of cities and
available flights between them.
We can also not only find
this number of flights.
But we can actually reconstruct
the optimal path between some city and
another city.
For example,
you can go from Moscow to San Diego in
the minimum number of flight segments.
And we also can build the tree of
all shortest paths from one origin.
So we not only can build a shortest path
from one node to another, but we actually
can build all the shortest paths from
one node to all the nodes in the graph.
And all this works in time for
personal to number of edges plus
number of nodes in the graph.