Hi.
In this video,
we will briefly review the main
ingredients of greedy algorithms and
the first of them is
reduction to a subproblem.
Basically, when you have some problem,
you make some first move and
thus reduce your problem to a similar
problem, but which is smaller.
For example, you have fewer digits left or
fewer gas stations left in front of
you and this similar problem,
which is smaller is called a subproblem.
Another key ingredient is a safe move and
the move is called safe if it is
consistent with some optimal solution.
In other words, if there exists some
optimal solution in which the first
move is the same as your move,
then your move is called a safe move and
not all first moves are actually safe.
For example,
to go until there's no fuel is not a safe
move in the problem about car fueling.
And often, greedy moves are also not safe,
for example,
to get to the closest gas station and
refuel at it is not a safe
move while to get to the farthest gas
station and refuel there is a safe move.
Now the general strategy of
solving a problem goes like this.
First, you analyze the problem and
you come up with some greedy choice and
then the key thing is to prove that
this greedy choice is a safe move and
you really have to prove it.
Because, otherwise, you can come
up with some greedy choice and
then come up with a greedy algorithm and
then even implement it and test it and
try to submit it in the system.
Only to learn that
the algorithm is incorrect,
because the first move is actually not
a safe move and there are cases in which
this first move is not consistent
with any optimal solution.
And in that case,
we will have to invent a new solution and
implement it from scratch.
All the work you've done
before will be useless.
So please prove your algorithms and
prove that the first move is a safe move.
When you prove that,
you reduce a problem to a subproblem.
And hopefully, that is a similar problem,
problem of a same kind and
then you start solving
this subproblem the same way.
You make your greedy choice and
you reduce it to subproblem, and
you iterate until there are no problems
left or until your problem is so
simple that you can just
solve it right away.
And in the next lessons,
we will apply greedy algorithms
to solve more difficult problems.