Hi, in this video you will learn to
significantly improve the running time of
the Rabin-Karp's Algorithm.
And to do so we'll need to look closer
into the polynomial hashing and
its properties.
Recall that to compute a polynomial
hash on the string s but
first choose a big prime number for the
polynomial family, then we choose a random
integer x from 1 to p minus 1 to select
a random hash function from the family.
And then the value of this hash
function is the polynomial of x
with coefficients which
are characters of the string S.
And to compute this hash functional
substring of text T starting in position i
and having the same length as the pattern
for which we are looking in the text.
We need to also compute
a similar polynomial sum.
It goes from character
number i to character number
i plus length of the pattern minus 1.
And we need to multiply each character
by the corresponding power of x.
For example T of i will be multiplied by
x to the power of zero because this is
the first character of the substring and
the last character will be multiplied by
x to the power length of the pattern minus
1, and here is a formula on the slide.
And the idea for the improving of the
running time is that the polynomial hash
value for
two consecutive substrings of text
with length equal to the length of
the pattern are very similar and
one of them can be computed given
another one in constant time.
We introduce a new notation,
we denote by H[i].
The hash value for the substring of
the text starting in position i and
having the same length as the pattern.
Now let's look at the example,
our text is a, b, c, b, d.
And we need to convert the characters
to their integer codes.
And let's assume for simplicity that
the code for a is zero, for b is one, for
c is two, and for d is three.
Then our text is actually 0, 1, 2, 1, 3.
Also, we will assume in this example,
that the length of the pattern is three.
We don't need to know the pattern itself,
we just fix its length.
So we will need to
computer hash values for
the substrings of
the text of length three.
There are three of them,
abc, bcd, and cbd.
We start with the last one, cbd.
To compute its hash value, we first
need to write down the powers of x
under the corresponding
characters of the text.
Then we need to multiply each power
of the x by the corresponding
integer code of the character and
we get 2x and 3x squared.
And then we need to sum them and we also
need to take the value module of b, but
on this slide we'll just ignore module of
p, it will be assumed in each expression.
Now let's look at the hash value for
the previous substring of
lines three which is bcb.
We again need to write down the powers of
x under the corresponding integer codes of
the character.
And again need to multiply the powers of
x by the corresponding integer codes and
get one to x and x squared,
we need to sum them.
Now note the similarity
between the hash value for
the last substring of line three and
the previous substring of line three.
To get the last two terms for bcb, we can
multiply the first two terms for cdb by x.
And we will use this similarity to compute
the hash for bcb given the hash for cdb.
So again H[2] is the same as hash
value of cbd because it starts
in the character with index two and
it's equal to 2 + x + 3x squared.
Now let's compute the age of 1 based on
that this is the hash value of bcb and
we know it's equal to 1 +
2x + x squared module of p.
Now let's rewrite this using this property
of multiplication by x the terms for
the cbd.
So it's equal to 1 + x multiplied by
the first two terms for cbd which are 2+x.
Now we don't want to use just
the first two terms for cbd, we.
We want to use the whole cbd so
we write this as following 1+ x
multiplied by the whole expression for
cbd but now we need to subtract
something to make the equality true.
And that something is the last term,
x multiplied by 3x squared,
which is the same as 3x cubed,
so we subtract 3x cubed.
Now we regroup the summons, and
we right as this is equal to
x multiplied by the hash value for
cbd which is big H[2],
we add 1 to it and
we subtract through 3x cubed.
In the general case,
there is a very similar formula.
So, here is the expression for
big H[i + 1], and
notice that the powers of x are,
in each case j- i- 1 because the substring
starts in position i plus one.
So, we subtract i + 1
from each j in the sum,
and the expression for
big H[i] is very similar.
But, for each power of x,
we subtract just i from j.
Because the substring
starts in position i.
Now let's rewrite this expression so that
it is more similar to the gauge of i + 1.
And to do that, we start summation
not from i, but from i + 1 and
also end it one position later.
So, the first sum is now very
similar to the expression for
H[i+1], which has the powers
of x are always bigger by one.
And also we need to add T[i] which
is not accounted for in the sum, and
we need to subtract its last term, because
it's not In the expression for big H[i].
And that is T[i] plus
length of the pattern,
multiplied by x to the power
of length of the pattern.
Now we notice that the first sum
is the same as x multiplied by
the value of hash function for
the next substream, big H[i+1].
And the second and
third terms are the same.
So now we get this recurrent formula.
To compute the gauge of i,
if we know already the gauge of i + 1,
we need to multiply it by x and
then add T[i] and subtract another term.
Notice that T[i] and T of i plus
length of the pattern we just know.
And x to the length of the pattern
is a multiplier that we can pre
compute and use for each i.
Now let's use this in the pseudo code.
Here's the function to pre compute all
the hash values of our polynomial hash
function on the substrings of
the text t with the length equal
to the length of the pattern, and with
prime number, P and selected integer x.
We initialize our answer,
big H, as an array of length,
length of text minus length
of pattern plus one.
Which is the number of
substrings of the text
with length equal to
the length of the pattern.
Also initialize S by the last
substring of the text
with a length equal to
the length of the pattern.
And you compute the hash value for this
last substring directly by calling our
implementation of polynomial hash with the
substring prime number P and integer x.
Then we also need to precompute the value
of x to the power of length of the pattern
and store it in the variable y.
To do that we need
initialize it with 1 and
then multiply it length of P times
by x and take this module of p.
And then the main for loop, the second for
loop goes from right to left and
computes the hash values for
all the substrings of the text, but for
the last one for
which we already know the answer.
So to compute H[i] given H[i + 1],
we multiply it by x.
Then we add T[i] and we subtract y,
which is x to the power of length of P,
by T[i + length of the pattern].
And we take the expression module of p.
And then we just return the array
with the precomputed values.
So to analyze its training time, we know
that initialization of array H of s and
with the accommodations with the hash
value of the last substring,
I'll take time proportional
to the length of the pattern.
Also pre-computation of the x to
the power of length of P takes time
proportional to the length of the pattern.
And the second for
loop takes time proportional to length
of the text minus length of the pattern.
And all and all it's big O of length
of the text plus length of the pattern.
Now again, polynomial hash is computed
in time proportional to
the length of the pattern.
First for loop, computing the power of x,
also and the second for
loop, which goes through all the
substrings of the text with length equal
to the length of the pattern, x length
of text minus length of pattern time.
And the total precomputation time is
proportional to the sum of length of
the text and the pattern.
And in the next video we'll
use these precomputed values
to actually improve the running
time of the Rabin-Karp's Algorithm.