Hello everybody, welcome back to data
structures and algorithms specialization.
Today, we're going to be talking about
what really goes into computing runtimes
and really understanding how
long it takes a program to work.
So in particular,
today we're really going to dive in.
Up to this point we're
using this sort of rough
number of lines of code executed count.
And today we're going to talk
about how accurate this is and
what sorts of complications come in.
And in particular we'll see that if we
actually want something that's sort of
fundamentally an accurate measure of
runtime, it's going to be a huge mess.
We're going to have to bring in all
sorts of extra data that aren't
really convenient for us.
And so, we're really sort of
talking about the problem that comes in
with computing runtimes in algorithms.
Something that we're not going to
resolve really until the next lecture.
So to start with, let's look at
this algorithm that we had for
computing Fibonacci numbers.
Remember we created an array.
We assigned the 0th element to 0.
The first element to 1.
Then, we have this big for loop where
we set the i'th element to the sum of the i
minus first and
i minus second elements and
then at the end of the day we
return the nth element.
So we determined that when we ran this
program we executed about 2n + 2 lines
of code.
But we should really ask ourselves,
is this number of lines of code executed
really sort of an accurate description
of the runtime of the algorithm?
And, I mean, somehow, implicitly,
this measure of lines of code
assumes that, sort of, any two lines of code
are sort of comparable to each other.
They're sort of one basic operation.
And so, let's actually look at
this program in some detail and
see what goes into some of these lines of
code and see how valid this assumption is.
So to start with, we create this array.
And what happens when you
try to initialize an array?
Well, this depends a lot on
your memory management system.
Fundamentally, all you have to do is
find some space in memory and
then get to pointer to the first location.
On the other hand, how exactly you find
this, maybe you need to shuffle some other
things around to make room for it, maybe
after you allocate the array, you then
want to zero out all of the entries so
that you don't have junk sitting in there.
And so, it's not entirely clear.
It depends a little bit on how exactly
your program is being interpreted.
But it could be pretty fast.
It could actually take a while,
depending on circumstances.
Let's look at the next line.
This is just a simple assignment,
we set the 0 entry to 0.
However, if you really look at this,
at the machine level, you're doing a bit
more work, you need to load up the pointer
to the 0th element to the array, you maybe
then have to do some pointer arithmetic,
you then need to store this literal
0 into that spot in memory.
It could actually be not one operation but
a few operations.
Similarly when we set
the first element to one,
you have to do
this very similar set of things.
Next there's this for loop and
with the for loop, again every time you
you have to do a few things,
you need to increment the value of i.
You then need to compare i to n to see
if you need to break out of the loop and
if it is, you need to branch,
you need to move to another instruction
in your program after the for loop.
Next up there's this addition and
here we have to do some things, we have to
look up two values in the array, we have
to write to a third value in the array.
All of this involves the same
sort of pointer arithmetic,
and memory lookups, and writes that
we were talking about before, but
we also have to do this addition.
And if it were just a normal addition,
maybe it wouldn't be such a big deal.
However, this is addition of
two Fibonacci numbers, and
if you'll recall from a couple of lectures
ago, we found that Fibonacci numbers were
pretty big, in fact, so big, they probably
don't fit in a single machine word.
So adding two of them together actually
takes a non-trivial amount of time.
So somehow,
not only do you have to do all of these,
array arithmetic things but,
the actual addition of the Fibonacci
numbers is actually a pretty
non-trivial operation.
And then we do this return stuff where we
have to do an array lookup which involves
all the sorts of things we talked about
already and then have to do a return which
sort of is going to operate
with the program stack and
pop it up a level and
return an answer.
So in conclusion, this program
has six lines of code to it but
the amount of work being done in various
lines of code is very, very different.
Exactly what goes into each line of
code is not sort of at all the same thing.
Maybe we want to reconsider
the fact that this count,
that the number of lines of code,
is sort of our runtime.
Maybe we need to measure something else.
So what else should we do?
Well, if you want to be totally correct
about what we actually care about,
what you need to say is, well,
we're going to take this program,
we're going to run it on
some real life computer.
And we'd like to know how much
actual time it will take for
this program to finish. That is
fundamentally what we want to know.
Unfortunately, in order to figure that
out we need to know all kinds of messy
details.
We need to know things like the speed of
the computer that we're running it on.
If you run it on a big supercomputer,
it'll take a lot less time than
if you run it on your cell phone.
The system architecture of
the computer will matter.
Exactly what operations your CPU
supports and exactly how long they take
relative to one another, those are all
going to have an effect on your runtime.
The compiler being used is also
going to make a difference.
In practice, what you'll do is, you'll
write this program in some high-level
language, in C or Java or Python or
something, and then you'll run it through
a compiler to turn it into machine code.
And then the compiler,
though, isn't just sort of doing
something completely obvious.
It's performing all kinds of
interesting optimizations to your code.
And which optimizations it performs, and
how they interact with
exactly what you've written.
That's all going to have
an impact on the final runtime.
Finally, you're going to care about
details of the memory hierarchy.
If your entire computation
fits into cache,
it will probably run pretty quickly.
However, if you have to start
doing lookups into RAM,
things will be a lot slower.
RAM lookups actually
take a fair bit of time.
If, on the other hand, you run out of
memory in RAM and having to start writing
some of these memory operations to disk,
things are going to go a lot slower.
Lookups to hard disk can take milliseconds
which are forever in computer time.
And so, exactly how much memory is stored
in these various levels of the hierarchy,
and exactly how long the lookups take,
and how good the algorithms
about to predict what things you're
going to look up in the future are.
Those are all going to
affect your runtime.
And so, putting it all together,
we found basically a problem.
Figuring out accurate
runtimes is a huge mess.
You need to know all of these details and
you need to figure out
how everything interacts.
And we're going to be talking about
a lot of algorithms in the class.
And we're going to need to tell you
about runtimes for all of them and
we don't want to have to do this huge mess
every single time we have a new
algorithm that we want to analyze.
And this is an issue.
And another issue it was just that,
in practice I mean, this is all assuming
that you did know these details.
In practice, you don't know a lot of these
details, because you're writing a program,
it's going to be run on
somebody else's computer, and
you've got no idea what their system
architecture looks like on that computer,
because you don't know
what the computer is.
You don't know who's running it.
In fact, there'll be several people
running it on different computers with
different architectures and
different speeds, and it'll be a mess.
And you really don't want to
compute the runtime separately for
every different client.
So we've got a big problem here
and we're not going to solve it today but
next lecture we're going to talk
about how we get around this.
And what we really want is we want a new
way to measure runtime that allows
us to get some reasonable answer
without knowing these sorts of details.
And one of the key tricks that
you should be looking at,
that we'll be using to solve this problem,
is we're going to be getting things that
really give us results for
very large inputs.
They tell us,
not necessarily how long it
actually takes in terms of real seconds,
minutes, and hours, but tell us sort of
how our runtime scales with input size.
And in practice this is a very
important thing, because oftentimes,
we really do care what happens
when we have huge inputs,
millions of data points that we need
to analyze, how long does it take?
And so, come back next lecture,
we'll talk about how we resolve some of
these issues, and talk about some very
useful notation that we will be using
throughout the rest of this sequence.
So I hope you come back then,
and I'll see you there.