We have stored collections
of data using lists.
And have used indices to
access the items of lists.
In this lecture, we will explore
Python's dictionary type, and
learn how to store and
access information, using dictionaries.
In an earlier lecture, we used a nested
list to keep track of assignments, and
grades on those assignments.
Each inner list was a two item list
containing the assignment name,
a string and a grade which is a number.
We can use indexing to access
the items of the list.
Grades at zero are first at
the list with A1 and its grade.
Grades at one the first circle is
containing A2 and its grade and
grades at two refers to the list
containing A3 and its grade.
To find out the name of a particular
assignment we need to use the first
index of that two element list.
So for example to find
the name of the assignment for
grades in X1,
we use index zero to get the name.
To access the grade associated
with that assignment,
we use index 1 of the inner list.
We will now use a dictionary to
store the same grades information.
And we'll see that accessing the mark
associated with a particular assignment
is going to be simpler when
working with the dictionary.
The variable assignment to grade
will refer to the new dictionary.
And the notation for
a dictionary is braces.
Each entry of a dictionary has two parts,
and the two parts are separated by colons.
This dictionary has three key value pairs.
A1 is a key, A2 is a key and A3 is a key.
80 is a value,
it is the value associated with key A1.
70 is a value,
it is the value associated with key A2.
And 90 is a value,
it is the value associated with key A3.
To look up the grade
associated with assignment A2,
we can use the bracket notation
that we used with the nested list.
However, rather than put an index
between the brackets, we will put a key.
So we want to look up the value
associated with key A2,
and that gives us the value 70.
This notation for
looking up a mark associated with
an assignment is much simpler than the two
indices needed to look up the mark
associated with an assignment.
Using the nested list.
However, it reveals something
about dictionaries.
In order to be able to look up
a particular value associated with a key,
that key must be unique.
It can only occur once in the dictionary.
So assignment names A1, A2,
and A3 are unique names.
The marks associated with
those assignments, or
the values of the dictionary,
could be duplicated.
So it's possible that A1 and A2, those
keys, could have the same value, say, 80.
If we try to access a list, and an index
that does not exist an error occurs.
And the same is true for dictionaries.
If we try to access a dictionary
using a key that does not exist,
then a key error occurs.
They key A4 is not present in
the dictionary that assignment to grade
refers to.
Before accessing a key of a dictionary,
we can check for
its existence in the dictionary.
So we could have checked to see
wether A4 is in asn_to_grade.
It's not, so False is the value
that our expression evaluates to.
Of course A2 is a key in the dictionary,
so this expression will evaluate to true.
This inoperator is checking for
the presence of keys, not values.
So if we check whether 80
is in assigned to grade,
this expression will also evaluate False,
since 80 is not a key in that dictionary.
Currently there are three
key-value pairs in the dictionary.
The len built-in function,
that trends the number of key-value pairs.
Like lists, dictionaries are mutable,
that means the key-value pairs
can be added to a dictionary.
The value associated with
the key could be changed and
key-value pairs can be
removed from a dictionary.
Let's start by adding another
key-value pair to this dictionary.
We're going to add the assignment A4 and
we indicate this using the same
bracket notation that we use to
access the value at a particular key.
But we use it in conjunction
with an assignment statement.
So the dictionary that assigned to grade
refers to will get a new key A4 and
the value associated with that key is 85.
The len function now
returns 4 because there
are four key value pairs
in assign to grades.
Using the same notation we can also
update the values associated with a key.
So for key A4.
We're going change its
value now from 85 to 90.
Because A4 already exists in
the dictionary, this becomes a change.
If the key A4 didn't exist,
like before, then the new key
value pair would be added.
Key A4 originally had the value
85 associated with it.
And now it has the value
90 associated with it.
Notice that the value 90 is associated
with the key A3 and with the key A4.
Values can be duplicated,
as mentioned before, but keys cannot.
Now let's remove a key value
pair from the dictionary.
To do this we will use the operator
del and then the dictionary
reference and the key,
using the same bracket notation.
So we'll remove key A4 along with
its value from the dictionary.
The dictionary's line is
now going to be three.
And the dictionary no longer has
the key value pair A4 and 90.
We can use a for loop to loop
over the keys of a dictionary,
like we did to loop over the characters
of a string, or the items of a list.
Because we're looping over the keys,
the variable name that I'm going to choose
here will be representative
of the key of the dictionary.
I'm going to use the word assignment for
my variable name.
For each assignment in
the dictionary asn_to_grade,
we'll print that assignment, that key.
The keys A1, A3 and A2 are printed.
However, this doesn't match the order in
which we added the key value pairs to
the dictionary.
We put A1 in its value first, then A2
with its value and A3 with its value.
The order that key value pairs are are
added to the dictionary has no effect on
the order in which the for
loop accesses the keys.
Therefore when looping over
the keys of a dictionary,
we cannot rely on the keys being
accessed in any particular order.
In this case we can't rely on A1
before being printed before A2 and
A2 being printed before A3.
This time rather than printing the keys of
the dictionary, let's print the values,
all of the for loops that we write over
dictionaries will be loops over the keys.
So we're going to leave
the header exactly the same,
rather than printing the key assignment
we'll look up the value associated with
that key in the dictionary and
print that value instead.
The values 80, 90 and 70 are printed.
And finally,
let's print both the key and the value.
When we call print,
we can pass two arguments.
The key assignment, and
then the value associated with that key.
That prints each assignment and
the mark associated with it.
Our introduction to dictionaries
is almost complete, but
there are a couple more
important things to point out.
First, a dictionary can be empty.
And we use just the opening and
closing braces to indicate
this with nothing in between.
The length of an empty dictionary is 0.
Finally, we need to make an important
note about the types that the keys and
values of a dictionary may have.
Keys and values can be of different types.
So we could have a sting for a key and
another key could be an int.
However, the type of keys
must always be immutable.
Since lists are mutable,
a list cannot be used as a dictionary key.
This assignment statement which attempts
to add a list with numbers 1 and
2 as a key along with the value banana,
will result in an error.
When we want to use a sequence as a key,
rather than using a list,
we can use a tuple,
because tuples are immutable.
The following is acceptable.