We're now ready to present all
the details of the Kruskal Algorithm.
Namely, we will prove that
the Kruskal strategy is optimal,
it produces a spanning tree
of minimum total weight,
and we will also present implementation
details of this algorithm.
Recall that the idea of this
algorithm is the following.
We start with an empty set X,
and we repeatedly add to this set
the next lightest edge that
doesn't produce a cycle.
So it is not difficult to see that
at any point of time the set
of edges X forms a forest.
That is a collection of trees.
Let me illustrate this.
Assume that we have some set of vertices
and initially, the set X is empty,
which means that each of our
vertices forms a tree of size 1,
namely a tree that contains 1 vertex and
no edges.
Initially each vertex is
isolated in our set X.
Now, we start adding edges.
Probably, this is the first one,
then we add this edge, then this edge,
then this edge,
then this edge, for example.
At this point of time,
our set X consists of three trees.
So this is the first tree, T1.
This is the second tree, T2.
And this is the third tree, T3.
In particular,
the tree T3 contains just one vertex.
It is an isolated vertex, okay?
Assume also that the next vertex that
the next edge that Kruskal's Algorithm
is going to add is the following.
[NOISE] So, it is the next lightest
edge that doesn't produce a cycle.
The first thing to note is that
the edge e must join two edges
that belong to different trees, right?
Because if they were in the same tree,
this would produce a cycle.
Okay, now we need to show
that adding e is a safe move.
For this,
we need to use cut property, right?
And in turn for using cut property,
we need to construct, we need to show
a partition of the set of vertices
such that e is the lightest branch
in our graph that joins vertices
from different parts of partition.
To construct such a cut, let's just take
all the vertices from one of these trees
As one part of this cut namely
this is going to be the set S so
this is one part of our partition and
all other vertices is the other
part of this partition.
In this case,
we see that e is the lightest edge
that joins two vertices
from different parts.
Which means in turn that cut
property justifies that adding
e in this case is indeed a safe move.
In other words,
if our carbon set tax is a part
of some optimal spanning tree, then x with
e added Is also a part of
some minimum spanning tree.
Once again, initially, the set X
in the Kruskal algorithm is empty,
which means that each
vertex of our initial graph
forms a separate connected component.
So this is how initially
the set x looks like.
So each vertex lies in
a separate connective component.
Then we start adding edges to x.
This creates [NOISE] a forest.
In this forest currently,
we have three trees.
This is the first tree.
This is the second one.
And this is the third one.
Assume now that the next lightest
edge that Kruskal's Algorithm
considers is the following one.
First of all, we need to be able to check
whether it joins two vertices that lie
in the same tree or in other words,
that lie in the same connected component.
In this case, they lie in
the same connected component, so
Kruskal's Algorithm will
not edit through the set x,
because otherwise,
it would produce a cycle in our set x.
Now, assume that next set that Kruskal's
Algorithm tries is the following.
Again, we need to check whether
the corresponding two end points lie in
the same connected component.
In this case, it is not a case.
They lie in different connected component.
So we add this edge and to this point,
we should update the data structures that
we use to indicate that now we
actually merge trees T1 and T2.
So what we need to check in our data
structure is whether two given vertices
lie in the same set or in the same
connected component, and also if they lie
in different connected components, we need
to merge the corresponding two trees.
So the perfect choice for data structure
for this algorithm is, of course,
the disjoint sets data structure.
Once again,
to check whether two given vertices lie
in different connected components,
we just check whether find of
one endpoint is equal to find of
the other end point of this edge.
If they are different then they lie
in different connected component.
And when adding an edge to the set X, we
need to merge the corresponding two tree
and this is done by calling the method
union of the corresponding two end points.
We will now illustrate
this on a toy example.
This is a toy example where
we have six vertices.
Let's first call them A,
B, C, D, E, F, and
let's assume that we have a data
structure disjoint set and
let me show the contents of this
disjoint sets of this data structure.
So initially,
each vertex lies in a separate set.
No we start processing edges in
order of non-decreasing weight.
So the first lightest edge is AE.
We check whether A and E, at this point,
lie a different connected components.
For this way,
we call find of A and find of E.
This gives us different IDs because
they stay in different sets.
So we add this edge to
our current solution and
we also notify our data
structure that now A and
E actually lie in the same
connected component.
So now it looks like this.
The next lightest edge if the edge CF.
Again we ask our data structure whether
C and F belong to the same set and
each replies that they do not belong
to the same set because find of C is
not equal to find of F, so it is safe
to add this edge to our solution.
We also notify our data structures and
C and
F now lie in the same set by
calling union of C and F.
So now C and F lie in the same set.
The next edge is A, E,
D and we see that A and
D lie in different connected components so
we just add this etch to a solution and
also notify our data structures
that we need to merge sets
that contain the vertex A and
the vertex D.
So now, we have three different
disjoint sets in our data structure,
which actually corresponds to
vertices of our three trees.
So the first tree contains vertices AED,
the second one contains the vertex B, and
the last one contains vertices C and F.
Now, the next lightest edge is DE,
it has weight 3.
However, we see that D and
E belong to the same connected component.
This, in turn, means that if we added
the edge DE to our current solutions,
this would produce a cycle.
So we just keep the edge DE, and
we continue to the next lightest edge.
The next one is AB, and we see that A and
B lie in different connected components,
so it is safe to add the edge
AB to the current solution.
We also need to merge
the corresponding two sets.
So after this merge,
our sets look as follows.
Now, the lightest edge is the edge BE,
it is of weight five,
however, B and E belong to the same set,
so we skip it.
And the last edge that we actually
add to our solution is the edge BBF.
It is of weight 8 and, at this point,
we also nudge two sets.
And now, all our vertices lie
in the same connected component,
which means that we constructed
an optimal spanning tree,
that is a spanning tree
of minimum total weight.
The pseudocode of the Kruskal
algorithm looks as follows.
First, for each vertex in our graph,
we create a separate disjoint set.
We do this by calling MakeSet method
of disjoint sets data structure.
Then we initialize the set
of edges X by empty set.
The next step is that we sort the edges,
all the edges of our graph, by weight.
Then we process all the edges in
order of non-decreasing weight.
This is done in this is fold.
Then for reach such edge, we need to check
whether adding in the x safe or not.
Namely, whether it produces a cycle or
not.
To do this, we just check whether u and v
belong to different connector components.
For this, we need to check where to
find a few equal to find a v or not.
If they're different, then they lie
in different connected components.
In this case,
it is safe to add the edge u,
v to the set X and
produces in this line and
also in this case we need to
notify our data structure that all
the vertices that before that lied in
connected component with u and three,
now lie in the same connected components,
because we just joined these two trees,
and this is done by calling
union of of u and tree.
Finally, in the end,
we just return the resulting set X.
It remains to estimate the running
time of the Kruskal's algorithm.
We start by sorting the edges, so
this requires big O(E log E) time, right?
This in turn can be rewritten
as big O(E log of V squared),
just because a simple graph
has at most V squared edges.
This, in turn,
can be rewritten as just E times 2 log V.
Again, log of V squared
is equal to 2 log v, so
we rewrite it as follows, and this is
math analysis is just big O of E log V.
So this is an upper bound on
the running time of the first step.
Then we need to process all the edges.
For this,
we make two equals to find that region.
Why two equals, well,
just because we process all the edges and
follow each edge, we make two calls
to define that region mainly, for
one endpoint and for the other endpoint.
Then we also make at most V minus
one calls to the union procedure.
Why V minus one?
Well, just because initially we
have n connected components.
Namely, when the set x is empty,
each vertex of our graph forms
a separate connected components.
Then each time when we call union, we
actually merge two connected components.
And in the end of the run
of our algorithm,
we have just one connected component.
So all the vertices lie in the same tree.
So initially, we have n connected
components and then we have 1 and
each time we call union, we reduce the
number of connected components by 1 which
means that we make exactly V
minus 1 calls to union procedure.
Okay, so we have roughly E calls to find
and roughly V calls to union procedure.
Now recall that if we implement the
disjoint set data structure as a forest or
as a collection of disjoint trees and
we use union by rent.
Heuristic than the running time that
abound on the running time of each
iteration is just log v, which gives
us that amount E plus V times log v.
Recall also that in our case,
the graph is connected,
which mean that e is at least v minus 1,
which in turn means that E plus V,
is at most 2E.
Which allows us to rewrite it as follows.
So the upper bound on
the running time of the second
step is actually the same as for
the first step.
It is O of E log V,
which gives us that the upper bound
on the running time of the whole
algorithm is big O(E log V).
Now recall that we actually know that if,
for our implementation
of disjoint sets data structure,
we use both union by run heuristic and
past compression heuristic then we
can state a strong upper bound.
That is, instead of using log v here,
we actually have log star of v,
the iterated log, right?
This gives us a stronger upper bound for
the second step.
Unfortunately, this
doesn't improve the total
running time because
still the upper bound for
sorting all the edges delineates
the upper bound for the second step.
However, for some applications, the edges
are given to us already in sorted order,
which means that, in this case,
we do not need to spend E log V time for
sorting the edges.
So that the total running time in this
case becomes equal to E times log* of V.
Which makes the Kruskal algorithm
in this case even more efficient.
So in this case,
the running time is upper bounded
by E times log star of V,
which is nearly linear.