In this video,
we can see the Prim's Algorithm.
Recall that in this algorithm,
the set X always forms a tree,
and we regularly grow it.
At each iteration we attach a new vertex
which is not currently in the tree
to the current tree by
the lightest possible edge.
And this is in fact very similar
to Dijkstra's algorithm.
Recall that Dijkstra's algorithm finds
the shortest paths between two nodes
by constructing the tree of shortest
path from a given source node.
We will now illustrate
this on a toy example.
Consider the following toy
example that we've already seen.
We are now going to grow a tree which will
eventually become a minimum spanning tree.
At each iteration we're going to
select the vertex such that it can
be attached to the current tree
by the lightest possible edge.
To select such a vertex we will use
the priority queue data structure.
So initially, we know nothing about
the graph, so the cost of attaching
each vertex to the current tree
is just equal to infinity.
So initially the priority was
a cost of attaching each vertex
to the current tree is equal to infinity.
That is, we show here the priorities
of all other vertices
in the priority queue data
structures that we're going to use.
Then we declare some vertex,
just randomly picked vertex,
as a root of the tree that
we are going to grow.
Assume that we consider
this vertex as a root.
Now we can change its
priority to be equal to 0.
It costs us nothing to attach
this vertex to the current tree.
It is the root.
Now we need to process all
address going out of this tree.
Namely, we change the priority
of this vertex to 1 because we
see that there is an edge of cost 1 that
attaches this vertex to our current tree.
And for
this vertex we change its priority to 8.
Okay, now we have five
vertices in our priority cube,
all of the vertices except for the root.
And the cost of one of them is
equal to 1 because of priority.
The priority of the second
one is equal to 8, and
the priority of the remaining three
vertices are equal to plus infinity.
So we select the vertex with
the smallest priority, this is 1.
So we attach it to our current tree.
So our current tree looks as follows.
Now we need to process all the address
that grow out of this tree.
Namely, when we add a new vertex,
we need to check whether new vertices
can be attached to this vertex.
When we see this, first we see that
there is a match of weight 6 so
we need to change the priority of
this vertex to 6 because it now
can be attached to the current
tree by the edge of weight 6.
Also we change the priority
of this vertex to 9.
Okay, now we have four vertices in
our priority queue data structure.
And we select the vertex
with the minimum priority,
which is the vertex with priority 6.
So now this vertex is also in our tree
which is joined by this
edge to our current tree.
Now we need to process all the edges
going out of this vertex to
the vertices that are not
currently in our tree.
When processing the edges, we change
the priority of this vertex to 4.
And we change the priority
of this vertex to 5.
Namely, we just found a cheaper way of
connecting this vertex
to our current tree.
Okay, now we have three
vertices in our priority queue
so we extract the minimum value.
This gives us the following vertex,
so we include it in our tree,
which gives us, and
attach it by this node.
Then we need to process
all the edges going out of
this vertex to vertices that
are currently not in the tree.
We see that we need to change
the priority of this vertex to 1 because
there is a vertex of, because there
is a match of weight 1 that connects
this vertex to, there's a vertex
which is currently in the tree.
And we need to change this priority to 2,
right?
Okay, great, now we have two vertices in
our priority queue, one of priority 1,
and one of priority 2.
So we select this vertex.
Now it is in our tree, and
it is connected by this edge, right?
When processing all the edges
going out of this vertex,
we see that there is a match of weight 3.
However, it doesn't decrease
the course of attaching
the remaining vertex to the tree.
So we keep the perimeter
of this vertex unchanged.
So in the last step, we extract the only
remaining vertex which is this one.
And we see that the cost of
attaching this vertex to the current
tree is equal to 2, and
this is done by this edge.
So, now, let's compute the total
weight of the resulting tree.
It is 2 plus 1 plus 4, which gives us 7.
Plus 6, which is 13.
Plus 1, so
this gives us the tree of total weight 14.
We now provide the full pseudocode
of the Prim's algorithm.
As we've discussed before, it is very
similar to Dijkstra's algorithm.
So, once again the Prim's Algorithm
gradually grows
the tree which eventually turns
into a minimum spanning tree.
We used the priority queue
data structure to keep for
each vertex the minimum cost of
attaching it to the current tree.
At each iteration we use priority
queue to quickly find the vertex
which can be attached to the current
vertex by the lightest edge.
So specifically we do the following.
Initially we have for
each vertex we do not
know the cost of attaching
it to the current tree so
we just put infinity into the array cost.
We'll also going to keep
array parent which we'll
actually define as a tree, okay.
Initially we do not, for each vertex of
our graph, we do not know its parent.
Then we select any vertex of our graph,
u0.
And we declare this vertex as the root
of the tree which we are going to grow.
We then update cost[u0] to be equal to 0.
So, we say that attaching this node,
this vertex to the current tree is,
the cost of attaching this node is equal
to 0 because it is already in our tree.
We then create a priority queue.
So at this point and
we use costs as priorities.
At this point all the vertices
lie in priority queue.
And the priorities are all of them except
for u0 are equal to plus infinity,
while the priority of u0 is equal to 0,
okay?
Then we do the following.
At each iteration, we extract the vertex
with the minimal priority
out of our priority queue.
This means that we're actually attaching
this vertex to the current tree.
When we do this, we also need to go
through all the neighbors of the vertex V
and to check whether the edge that
leads from V to this neighbor of V,
it has actually cost less
than the current cost, or
than the current priority
of this neighbor.
Specifically we do the following, when
we add the vertex V to our current tree,
we iterate through all its neighbors.
This is not in this for loop.
So we iterate through all
neighbors z of the vertex v.
And we check if z is still in
the priority queue, namely,
if z is not in our current tree,
and if the current cost of z
is greater than the weight
of the edge from v to z.
Then, this means that
we've just found a cheaper
way to attach the vertex z
to the current tree, right?
And in this case,
we just update the value of cost at z.
So we assign cost at z to be equal
to the weight of the edge v z.
And we also say that in this case
if we attach the vertex v to
the current tree,
then this will be done through the edge v,
z, which means that v is
going to be the parent of z.
Finally, we notify our priority
queues that we need to
change the priority of the vertex
z to the updated value cost of z.
Since the Prim's Algorithm is very
similar to Dijkstra's Algorithm,
its running time is also similar.
So essentially,
what we are doing here is the following.
We make V calls to ExtractMin procedure,
right, and
also we make at most E calls to
ChangePriority method, right?
And the total running time depends
on the implementation of
the priority queue data structure.
If we just use array to
store all priorities and
at each iteration, this means that
change in priority is very cheap,
because we just change
the corresponding value in our array.
However, for finding the minimum value,
we need to scan the whole array.
In this case, we get V squared
upper bound on the running time.
Why is that?
Well once again, because ExtractMin in
this case has running time big O of V.
So this is V times big O of V,
while ChangePriority has
running time big O of 1, right.
It is a constant time operation.
Since the numbers of edges in
the graph is at most V squared,
this gives us big O of V squared.
If on the other hand we implement
our priority queue data structure as
a binary heap, then both these operations
have running time big O of log V.
In this case, we have the following
running time, V + E times log V.
And since, in our case, again the graph
is connected, E is at least 3 minus 1.
So this allows us rewrite the whole
expression as big O of E times log V.
So once again the running time
depends on implementation.
If we use array to implement our
priority queue, this gives us V squared.
If we use binary heap,
this gives us E log V.
Which one is better depends on
whether our graph is dense or not.
We are now ready to summarize.
In this module we considered
two greedy algorithms for
the minimum spanning tree problem.
And it uses the following idea.
At each iteration we add the next
lightest edge to our current solution
if this edge doesn't produce a cycle.
To check whether the current
edge produces a cycle or not,
we use disjoint sets data structure.
Namely, for the current edge
uv we just check whether u and
v belong to the same connected component.
If they do, we just skip the current edge.
The next algorithm is due to Prim.
It uses a slightly different but
still greedy strategy.
Namely, we greedily grow a tree.
At each iteration we attach a new vertex
to the current tree by a lightest
possible edge.
To find such a vertex quickly we use
the priority queue data structure.