So in this lecture we're talking
about arrays and linked lists.
In this video,
we're going to talk about arrays.
So here's some examples of declarations of
arrays in a couple of different languages.
Along with, we can see the one dimensional
array laid out with five elements in it,
and then a two dimensional array with one
row, sorry two rows and five columns.
So what's the definition of an array?
Well we got basically
a contiguous array of memory.
That is one chunk of memory.
That can either be on a stack or
it can be in the heap,
it doesn't really matter where it is.
It is broken down into
equal sized elements, and
each of those elements are indexed
by contiguous integers.
All three of these things
are important for defining an array.
Here, in this particular example, we have
an array whose indices are from 1 to 7.
In many languages, the same indices for
this particular array
would be from zero to six.
So it would be zero based indexing, but
one based indexing is also
possible in some languages.
And other languages allow you to actually
specify what the initial index is.
What's so special about arrays?
Well, the key point about an array
is we have random access.
That is, we have constant time access
to any particular element in an array.
Constant time access to read,
constant time access to write.
How does that actually work?
Well basically what that means is we
can just do arithmetic to figure out
the address of a particular array element.
So the first thing we need to do is
start with the address of the array.
So we take the address of the array and
then we multiply that by
first the element size.
So this where the key part that every
element was the same size matters, so
that allows us to do
a simple multiplication.
Rather than if each of the array
elements were of different sizes,
we'd have to sum them together, and
if we had to sum together n items,
that would be order n time.
So we take our array address, we add
to it the element size times i which
is the index that's of interest
minus the first_index.
If we're doing zero based indexing,
that first index isn't really necessary.
I like this example because it really
shows a more general case where we do have
a first index.
Let's say for instance we're looking
at the address for index four.
We would take four minus the first index,
which is one, which would give us three.
Multiply that by whatever
our element size is, and
then add that to our array address.
Now of course, we don't have to do this
work, the compiler or interpreter does
this work for us, but we can see how
it is that it works in constant-time.
Many languages also support
multi-dimensional arrays,
if not you can actually kind of roll your
own through an example I'll show you here,
where you do your own arithmetic.
So here, let's look.
Let's say that the top left element is at
index (1, 1), and here's the index (3,4).
So this means we're in row 3, column 4.
How do we find the address
of that element?
Well, first off what we need
to do is skip the rows that,
the full rows, that we're not using.
So that is,
we need to skip two rows, or skip 3,
which is the row index minus 1,
which is the initial row index.
So that gives us 2 times 6 or
12 elements we're skipping for
those rows in order to get to row 3.
Then we've got to skip the elements
before (3,4) in the same row.
So there are three of them.
How do we get that?
We take the column index,
which is 4 and subtract it from
the initial column index which is 1.
So this basically gives us 15.
Six for the first row, six for
the second row and then three for
the third row before
this particular element.
We take that 15 and
multiply it by our element size and
then add it to our array address.
And that will give us the address
of our element (3,4).
Now we made kind of a supposition here.
And that was that the way this was laid
out is we laid out all the elements of
the first row, followed by all of
the elements of the second row, and so on.
That's called row-major ordering or
row-major indexing.
And what we do is basically, we lay out,
(1, 1), (1, 2), (1, 3), (1, 4), (1, 5),
(1, 6).
And then right after that in memory (2,
1), (2, 2), (2, 3), (2, 4), (2, 5),
(2, 6).
So the column index is changing
most rapidly as we're looking at
successive elements.
And that's an indication
of it's row-major indexing.
We could lay out arrays differently,
and some languages or
compilers actually do that, where they
would lay out each column in order, so
you'd have the first column, then the
second column, and then the third column.
And so that, then, the successive
elements would be (1, 1), (2,
1), (3, 1), followed by (1,
2), (2, 2), (3, 2), and so on.
So there we see that the row index
is changing most rapidly, and
this is called column-major ordering.
How long does it take
to perform operations?
We already said to read any
element is O(1), and
to write any element is O(1).
That is a standard feature of arrays.
What happens if we want to add
an element at the end of an array?
So let's say we have allocated
seven elements for an array.
We're only using four of them, okay?
So we have kept track that we're using
four and we want to add a fifth element.
And again there's room for seven.
Then all we know it was just add it,
then update the number of
elements that are in use.
That's an O(1) operation.
If we want to remove
the last element as well,
that's an O(1) operation because we just
update the number of elements that are in
use, and so that's an O(1) operation.
Where it gets to be expensive,
is if we want to, for instance,
remove the first element.
So we remove the five here, and
what we've got to do then,
we don't want to have holes left in it.
So we need to move the 8 down,
move the 3 down, move the 12 down.
That's an O(n) operation.
Same thing would happen if he
wanted to insert at the beginning.
So we would need to move the 12, move
the 3, and move the 8 to make space for
our new element.
So that also would be O(n).
And if we want to add or
remove somewhere in the middle,
again that's an O(n) operation.
If we want to add exactly in the middle,
we have to move n/2 items,
which is O(n).
Same thing for removal.
So arrays are great if you want or
remove at the end.
But it's expensive if you want to add or
remove in the middle or at the beginning.
However, remember,
a huge advantage for arrays
is that we have this constant time
access to elements, either read or write.
In summary then, an array consists
of a contiguous area of memory.
because if it were non-contiguous then we
couldn't just do this simple arithmetic
to get where we're going.
We have to have equal-size elements
again so our arithmetic works.
And indexed by contiguous integers
We have constant time access to
any element, constant time to add or
remove at the end and linear time to add
and remove at any arbitrary location.
In our next video we're going to
talk about linked lists.