There is a way to make popping
the back and adding before cheap.
Our problem was that although
we had a way to get from
a previous element to the next element,
we had no way to get back.
And what a doubly-linked list says is,
well, let's go ahead and
add a way to get back.
So we'll have two pointers,
forward and back pointers.
That's the bidirectional arrow
we're showing here conceptually.
And the way we would
actually implement this is,
with a node that adds an extra pointer.
So we have not only a next pointer,
we have a previous pointer.
So this shows for
example that the 10 element has a next
pointer that points to 4 but
a previous pointer that points to 7.
So at any node we can either go forward or
we can go backwards.
So that means if we're trying to pop the
back, that's going to work pretty well.
What we're going to do is update the tail
pointer to point to the previous element
because again we ca get
there in an O(1) operation.
And then update its next pointer to be
nil and then finally remove the node.
So that's O(1).
So if we have a doubly linked list it's
slightly more complicated (our code) because
we've got to make sure to manage both
prev pointers as well as next pointers.
So if we're pushing something in the back,
we'll allocate a new node.
If the tail is nil, which means it's
empty, then we just have a single node
whose prev and next pointers are both nil
and then head and tail both point to it.
Otherwise, we need to
update the tail's next pointer for
this new node,
because we're pushing at the end and
then go update the prev pointer of this
new node to point to the old tail and
then finally update the tail
pointer itself.
Popping the back,
also pretty straightforward.
We're going to again check to see whether
this is first an empty list,
in which case it's an error.
A list with only one element,
in which case it's simple.
Otherwise we're going to go ahead and
update our tail to be the prev tail,
and the next of that node to be nil.
Adding after, fairly simple again we just
need to maintain the prev pointer but
adding before also now works in
the sense that we can allocate our node,
our new node and
its prev pointer will be the prev pointer
of the existing node we're adding before.
We splice it in that way and
then we'll update the next pointer of that
previous node to point to our new node.
And finally,
just in case we're adding before the head,
we need to update the head.
So in a singly-linked list,
we saw the cost of things.
Working with the front
of the list was cheap,
working with the back of the list
with no tail, was all linear time.
If we added a tail,
it was easy to push something at the end,
easy to retrieve something at the end,
but hard to remove something at the end.
By switching to a doubly linked list,
removing from the end (a PopBack)
becomes now an O(1) operation,
as does adding before which used
to be a linear time operation.
One thing to point out as we
contrast arrays versus linked lists.
So in arrays, we have random access,
in a sense that it's constant
time to access any element.
That makes things like
a binary search very simple,
where we start searching in the middle,
and then tell (if we have a sorted array),
and then can decide which
side of the array we're on.
And then, go to one side or the other.
For a linked list, that doesn't work.
Finding the middle element
is an expensive operation.
because you've got to start either
at the head or the tail and
work your way into the middle.
So that's an O(n) operation
to get to any particular element.
Big difference in between that and
an array.
However, linked lists are constant time
to insert at or remove from the front,
unlike arrays.
What we saw in arrays,
if you want to insert from the front, or
remove from the front, it's going to take you
O(n) time because you're going to have to move
a bunch of elements.
If you have a tail and doubly-linked,
it is also constant time to
work at the end of the list.
So you can get at or remove from there.
It's linear time to find
an arbitrary element.
The list element are not contiguous
as they are in an array.
You have separately allocated
locations of memory and
then there are pointers between them.
And then, with a doubly-linked list
it's also constant time to insert
between nodes or to remove a node.