Hello, everybody.
Welcome back to the graph
algorithms course.
Today, we're going to start talking
about directed graphs versus undirected,
in particular, talk about directed acyclic
graphs and some of their properties.
So what's the motivation for this?
The point is that sometimes we
want to talk about the edges of
a graph that have a direction.
This is just because I mean, sometimes,
like pairs of things are related in a way,
but the relation isn't symmetric.
One of them comes before the other,
or it's a one way viewership or
something like that.
And so we define a directed graph to
be a graph, where each edge has sort of
a designated start end and an end end.
So what are examples where
you might want to use this?
For example, if you've got a city map
where lots of your streets are one way
roads, the direction that the road's
pointing is actually very relevant if you
want to navigate the city.
You can't just follow any series
of roads you like because you'll
be driving down some one way streets
in the wrong order, so you really
do need to keep track of this orientation
if you want to navigate the city.
But then also some of the examples
that we gave, links between webpages,
the web graph is probably
a directed graph, because usually,
if you've got two webpages and A links
to B, B probably doesn't link back to A.
Similarly, if you have
followers on a social network,
it depends on the social network.
I mean, in Facebook,
friendships are symmetric.
So they're sort of two-directional.
That might be an undirected graph.
But on lots of them, you can follow
somebody without them following you, and
so then you end up with wanting
to have a directed relation for
when someone's following someone else.
A final example that we'll look at in some
more detail today are sort of dependencies
between tasks.
So, we have this directed graph, and we've
already built up a lot of this theory that
works for undirected graphs with this
sort of exploring DFS algorithms.
But most of this sort of actually
still holds for directed graphs.
We can still run DFS on a directed graph.
The slight modification now is
that when we run our explores,
we only want to check for
directed edges out of v.
So when we say for all neighbors w of v,
if w has not been visited, etc,
we really want to say neighbors where v
points to w, not the other way around.
And what this will do is it
means that when we explore v,
we find things that
are actually reachable from v,
using the edges in the direction
that they're intended.
So we're only sort of allowed
to follow these one-way roads
in their appropriate direction.
Now using this new depth first search, we
can still compute pre- and post-orderings.
They still have many of
the same properties.
The algorithm for
DFS still runs in linear time.
Basically, everything's the same.
The context is now
a little bit more general.
Okay, so
let's look at a sort of specific example,
where directed graphs are important.
In particular, suppose that we have
the following morning routine.
We've gotta do a bunch
of things every morning.
We need to wake up, we need to get
dressed, we need to eat breakfast,
we need to go to work,
we need to shower, all of these things.
We need to do these things in some order,
but we can't do them in any old order.
Because well,
we need to wake up before we get showered.
And we need to dress before we go to work.
And we need to eat breakfast before
we go to work, and all of this stuff.
And one way of representing these sorts
of dependencies is by a directed graph.
If we need to do A before we can do B,
then we draw a directed
edge from A pointing to B.
And so, this gives us some
sort of dependency relation.
And it's not just these sort of
trivial examples of how do I
get dressed in the morning.
But if you've got some sort of complicated
system of libraries, where some of them
require other ones in order to work,
you can end up with some sort of similar
graphic dependencies, which you actually
do need similar techniques to handle.
Okay, so what do we do when
we have these dependencies?
Well, one of the things that we'd
like to do is we'd like to find
the ordering of the tasks in a way
that respects these dependencies.
We'd like to wake up before we,
well, fine.
For example, suppose that we woke up
at 7 o'clock and then showered at 7:05,
got dressed at 7:15, had breakfast
at 7:20, and went to work at 7:30.
This puts all of our events in some order.
And you'll note that this order
respects all of our dependencies.
We wake up before we shower, before
we get dressed, before we go to work.
And we eat breakfast before we go to work,
and everything works out nice.
And so,
if we have one of these dependency graphs,
we'd like to linearly order the vertices
to respect these dependencies.
Now one thing to ask is,
is it always possible to do this?
And it turns out the answer is no.
The sort of best counter example is
this following chicken and egg problem.
I mean, the point is that you need
a chicken in order to lay eggs, and
you need eggs to hatch chickens.
And so you can't like put them in some
order where one of them comes first.
If you put chickens first,
then it would just point you from
eggs back to chickens going
in the wrong direction.
You put eggs first,
there's this pointer from chickens
back to eggs in the wrong direction.
Without someplace to have gotten started,
there's sort of no way you
can get this ordering and go.
In fact, in general there's a slightly
more complicated way in which this can
fail to happen.
In fact, if your graph has any cycle, a
cycle here is a sequence of vertices, v1,
v2 to vn, such that each one connects
to the next using a directed edge.
So you've got a bunch
of vertices arranged.
The circles just that each one connects
to the next one all the way around.
And the theorem is that if G contains
a cycle, it cannot be linearly ordered.
Okay, so just to make, well, fine.
Let's take a look at the proof here.
So suppose their graph has a cycle,
v1 through vn,
everything connected up in order.
And suppose that additionally,
we can linearly order this graph.
Well, if you linearly order these things,
there are finitely many.
One of them needs to come first.
So suppose that vk comes
first in this order.
But now we're putting vk before vk-1,
and vk-1 points to it, so
we have an arrow pointing in the wrong
direction, which gives us a contradiction.
So, if we have a cycle,
we cannot be linearly ordered.
So, what this means is that in
order to be linearly orderable,
you need to be what's known as
a directed acyclic graph or DAG.
And this is just a name for a directed
graph that has no cycles, fair enough.
Now, by the above theorem, it is necessary
to be a DAG in order to linearly order.
But one question we should ask
ourselves perhaps is, is it sufficient?
Can we necessarily linearly
order it if it's a DAG?
Well, okay, this is a question to
ask a little bit later, but for now,
let's just review.
We have the following four graphs.
Note that the edges here are sort of
the same, except for their orientations.
And which one of these graphs is a DAG?
Well, it turns out that only A is.
B has the cycle noted in red, and
C has this other cycle noted in red.
But if you work out A,
you can actually see that it
does not have any cycles to it.
Okay, but
the question that we were posing was,
is it the case that any DAG
can be linearly ordered?
And the theorem that we'll
actually show is that yes,
if you have any directed acyclic graph,
you can linearly order it.
And next time, what we're going to do
is we're going to prove this theorem.
But not just that.
In addition to proving this theorem, we're
actually going to make it algorithmic.
We're going to come up
with an algorithm that,
given a DAG,
actually produces this linear order.
So that's what you have to look forward
to next time, and I'll see you then.