Hello everybody, welcome back
to our graph algorithms course.
Today we're going to be talking about
notions of connectivity in directed graphs
which it turns out will be a little
bit more complicated than those in
the undirected case.
And we'll talk about various
notions then get to this idea
of a strongly connected component.
So in undirected graphs,
connectivity is a pretty simple notion.
We have these connected components where
any two things in the same component
you can get from one to the other.
And if you've got two
different components,
they've got no edges between them.
Nothing connects at all.
In directed graphs the story
is a bit more complicated.
So let's consider
the following example graph.
Now in one sense this graph is connected,
you can't separate it out into two islands
such that you can't reach
one island from the other.
On the other hand if you want to look at
which vertices can be reached from which
others, the story is
a bit more complicated.
From vertex D it turns out you can
reach every other vertex in this graph.
However, D is a source for attacks.
Once you leave D,
there's no way to get back to it,
there are just no edges that come into it.
Now A just sort of, sorry,
A F is sort of the opposite here.
From every vertex in the graph you can
reach F, but once again, once you do,
you can't get back.
Then again, G and A, neither of them
can be reached from each other.
H and I, you can get between them but
once you leave, again, you can't get back.
It's sort of a lot more complicated if
we want to figure out which things
are reachable from which others.
Now, there are actually a bunch of
possible notions of connectivity that show
up in directed graphs.
The first one is sort of that these two
points can't be separated from each other,
that you can't put them on
two different islands where
nothing in one island connects
to anything in the other.
And this sort of says that it means you
can get from one vertex to the other,
following edges in any all direction.
And I mean, okay, this says you
can't put them on different islands,
but it doesn't say you can reach
either from the other one without
breaking traffic laws by following
one-way streets in the wrong direction.
So, a second notion is that maybe
we want one of the vertices
to be reachable from the other using the
actual edges and their intended direction.
And this is a more practical notion.
However, it has its weird irregularities
that makes it hard to deal with.
So, third notion that's maybe a little
bit stronger is that you should have two
vertices, v and w,
where not only can you reach w from v,
but you can also go back and
reach v from w.
And this third notion turns
out to be pretty nice.
So when we say that two vertices v and
w in a directed graph are connected,
we mean this.
We mean that you can reach v from w,
and also can reach w from v.
But the theorem now is that using this
notion we actually recover much of
the power that we had
in the undirected case.
A directed graph can always be partitioned
into strongly connected components
where two vertices are in the same
strongly connected component, if and
only if they are connected to each other.
So, for example, the graph that we looked
at has five strongly connected components.
After you can get it all
around around there,
but there's no way to get
from it to anything else.
H and I you can get from one to the other
but not necessarily to other things.
A, B, C and E from any of those four
vertices you can reach any other one, but
once you leave again you can't get back.
D and G are each their own components and
that's it.
Within each of these components you can
get from everywhere to anywhere else.
But again once you leave it,
you can't come back.
So to make sure we are on the same page,
we have the following graph.
What is the strongly connect
component of A in this graph?
Well, it turns out to
be the following set.
A, B, E, F, G, and
H are in this component.
The other ones aren't.
And to see this,
we can see that sort of you can
actually get around any of these six.
A goes to E goes to H goes
to F goes to B goes back.
B goes to G goes to H
goes to F goes back to B.
Sort of you can use these to navigate
around, everywhere you like.
But from D you can't get to
D from this other component.
And C and I, once you get there you can't
get back to the other vertices here.
So the result is that you
have a directed graph.
It can always be partitioned into
strongly connected components.
Such that two vertices are connected if
and only if they're in the same component.
And the proof of this is
very similar to the proof of
the sort of similar thing
in the undirected case.
Again, we need to show that
connectivity in the strong sense is
an equivalence relation.
That if u is connected to v, and v is
connected to w, then u is connected to w.
But while if these connections happen,
there's a path from u to v, and
a path from v to w.
And so pushing them together,
there's a path from u to w.
Similarly, there's a path
from w back to u, and
from v back to, sorry,
w back to v and v back to u.
And composing them again gives
you a path from w back to u.
And so that completes our proof.
Now there's something more to say though.
Once we've split our graph
into connected components,
they still have edges connecting
these components to each other.
So one useful thing to do is to
draw what's known as the metagraph,
which sort of tells us how these connected
components connect to each other.
So this metagraph has vertices that
correspond to the connected components of
the original graph.
And you have an edge between the two of
them if there's an edge in that direction
connecting those vertices.
So D connects to A, so there's an edge
between D and the component of A.
It also connects to G, A, B, C or
E, those guys have edges
leading to H including F and so
they have edges into those components and
so on and so forth.
And this is our metagraph.
Now one thing to note about this metagraph
is if you stare for a little while,
you can actually see that it's a deck and
this is in fact no coincidence.
It turns out that the metagraph
of any graph G is always a DAG.
Now the proof of this is not so
hard, suppose that it's not.
What that means is that there's a cycle.
And what happens if you have
a cycle is that every node
in the cycle can be reached
in every other node
because you just travel along
the cycle until you get there.
Now, this would be true if
they were individual vertices,
but it's also true if you have a cycle
between strongly connected components.
Because you just, since everything in one
component connects to everything else,
you can just get to the guy
leading to the next component, and
then to the vertex leading
to the next component,
and this sort of follows all
the way around the cycle.
And so everything in all of those
components are all connected
to each other.
But since everything is connected,
they should all be the same
strongly connected components.
However the single vertices of
the metagraph are strongly connected
components, so you can't have two vertices
that are connected to each other and
that gives us a contradiction.
Okay, so in summary,
we can always partition our vertices
into strongly connected components.
We have a metagraph, describes how
these strongly connected components
connect to each other, and
this metagraph is always a DAG.
So, this is what we have.
Next time what we're going
to do is we're going to actually talk
about how to compute these things.
How do we compute the strongly
connected components of the graph,
how do we find the metagraph?
So, come back for the next lecture and
we'll talk about that.