Hello, everybody.
Welcome back to our
Graph Algorithms course.
Today, we're going to talk
about how to get an algorithm
to efficiently compute the strongly
connected components of a directed graph.
So if you recall from last time,
what we had was we find this notion
of connectivity in directed graphs,
where two vertices were connected if you
could get from one to the other and back.
Now, we said this graph necessarily
would be divided into strongly connected
components, where within a component,
you could get from everything
to everything else, but sort of once you
leave the component you can't get back.
Now, these components are connected to
each other by what we call the metagraph.
And the metagraph was always a DAG,
which is sort of a useful
a thing as we'll see today.
So the problem we're going to look
at today is, given a graph, G,
a directed graph, G, how do we find
the strongly connected components of G?
Now there's a pretty easy algorithm for
this, it turns out.
For each vertex v, run explore on v and
determine all the vertices
reachable from v.
Once you've done that for every vertex,
you know that for a vertex v what you
want to do is find all the vertices u
that are both reachable from v and
can also reach v.
And that, it turns out, will give you
the strongly connected component of v.
And so this gives you the strongly
connected component of v, you run this for
all v, that gives you all
the strongly connected components.
And so the runtime of this
algorithm is a little bit slow but
you need to explore from
every single starting vertex.
So the run time is something like
o of v squared plus v times e.
This is okay but
we'd like to find something faster.
And what's the idea?
The key idea of this
algorithm is the following.
If you take a vertex v and run explore,
you find everything you can reach from v.
Now this includes the components of v.
But if there are other
components downstream of that,
you might find vertices from other
connecting components as well.
However, there's a case
when this doesn't happen,
if v is located in a sink
strongly connected component.
That means there are no edges out of
that strongly connected component.
So when you explore from v, you will find
exactly it's strongly connected component.
Which is good, because we want to find
the strongly connected component.
So, if you actually find one,
that's a good start.
So how do we do this?
Well, we need to find the vertex in
a sink strongly connected components
which takes some thoughts.
Well, there's a theorem it
turns out that will help.
If C and
C prime are two strongly connected
components where there's an edge from some
vertex of C to some vertex of C prime.
It turns out that the largest
post number in C Is larger
than the largest post number in C prime.
Now to prove this,
we split into two cases.
When we run our depth first search,
either we visit a vertex in C
before we visit a vertex in C prime,
or it could be the opposite way,
visit a vertex in C prime
before we visit a vertex of C.
In the first case, where we visit C first,
well, from a vertex in C you can reach
everything else in C,
because it is the same component.
There's also an edge from C to C prime,
so you can also,
it turns out, reach everything
in C prime from that vertex.
And that means that while you're still
exploring that first vertex in C,
you actually explore everything else in C
and everything in C prime as a subroutine.
This means, that because of
the way subroutines work, you have
to finish exploring all those vertices
before you finish that last vertex in C.
So, that one vertex in C has
the largest post number of any vertex
in either component.
The second case is you
visit C prime first.
Here the proclaim is that you can't
actually reach C from C prime.
Because if you could reach C from C prime,
and
you still follow the edge from C back
to C prime and you'd have a cycle.
And this is not just any cycle.
This is a cycle in the metagraph,
which you can't have because
the metagraph must be a DAG.
And this means that you
can't reach C from C prime.
When you explore C prime,
you'll never actually find C in
the middle of that exploration.
So, in fact,
you have to finish exploring C prime
before you can even begin exploring C.
And so, once again, the vertex with
the largest post has to be in C.
Okay, so what does this mean?
If you look at the large
vertex with the single largest
post order number in the entire graph,
what can we say about that?
Well it has to come from a component
with no other components pointing to it.
That vertex needs to be the source
component, which is great.
It's almost what we wanted.
What we wanted was a vertex
in a sink component.
Well, there's a trick for doing this.
So if you have a graph,
we're going to define what's called the
Reverse Graph, which is just what you get
by taking a graph reversing
the direction of all the edges.
So if a graph on the left is G, the graph
on the right is the reverse graph.
The edges are all the same, they're just
pointing in the opposite directions.
Now the cute thing here is
that the reverse graph and
G both have the same strongly
connected components.
I mean, v and w are connected if you
can go from v to w and w back to v.
But if you reverse all the edges,
you can just follow those paths
in the opposite directions,
from v to w and w back to v.
And so, the strongly connected
components are the same, but
the edges in the metagraph are different.
Because if you have a source
component in the reverse graph,
that means that you have edges
coming out of it but not into it.
Well, when we reverse the edges
to get the original graph G,
the edges come into it and not out,
and you find the sink component.
So in order to find the vertex in the sink
component of G, what you do is you run
depth first search on the reverse graph,
which by the way is easy to compute,
you just take every edge and
reverse the direction.
because we run depth first
search on the reverse graph and
take the vertex to largest post order.
Okay so just to review.
Which of the following is true?
The vertex with the largest post
order number in the reverse graph
is in the sink component?
The vertex with the largest preorder
number is in the sink component?
Or the vertex with the smallest
Well, all of these sound
roughly equivalent.
But if you work them out,
only one of them is true.
The first one.
The vertex with the largest postorder
number is in a sink component.
The other ones sound plausible,
but just don't work.
Okay, but this gives us an algorithm.
And the point is the following.
We run depth first search
on the reverse graph.
We let v be the vertices of
the largest post number and
this has to be in the sink
component of the G.
We now explore v and
because it was in a sink component,
the vertices we find are actually
a strongly connected component of G.
So, we take them,
we remove them from G and then we repeat.
So, here's our graph,
we depth first search the reverse graph,
the largest post number is that 18.
So, we explore that, we find one vertex.
That's our first component.
We're now going to remove that
from the graph and try again.
Depth first search on the reverse graph,
16 is the largest post.
We explore from there,
we find this new component.
Great.
Depth first search the reverse graph,
find the largest post, explore that.
We have a third component.
Depth first search the reverse graph, 10
is the largest, and we explore from that.
We find these four guys as a component,
and then there's the one
vertex we find out.
So that gives us a strongly
connected components.
Unfortunately, this algorithm's
a little bit inefficient again.
Because we need to run depth first
search repeatedly on the reverse graph.
But it turns out that that's
actually unnecessary.
Because remember, the theorem that we had
was that if you had an edge between two
components, the one that was further
upstream always had the larger post order.
In fact, when we reversed the edges,
now it's the one downstream has
the largest post order, but whatever.
But the point is that after you
remove the sink component, and
if you just then look for the vertex with
the single largest remaining post order,
that's going to be a sink
component of the new graph.
It doesn't point to anything else,
except for
maybe some components that
you've already removed.
And so the new algorithm, we just run
depth first search once on the reverse
graph, then we look for
v in the graph in reverse postorder.
Any v that has not yet been visited,
we explore that v, and
mark the vertices that we found as
a new strongly connected component.
So we have this graph.
We depth first search
on the reverse graph.
We record the post numbers.
Now the largest post is 18.
We explore that vertex,
find this component.
Next is 17, which we explore and
Then 15 finds this guy, 10 finds this 4,
and 6 finds the last guy, and that's it.
A much faster algorithm.
In fact, the runtime,
we essentially just ran a depth first
search on the reverse graph and
then ran another depth first search on G,
which is the slight modification
that we wanted to visit our vertices in
this outer loop in some specific order.
And also, we need to record
the connected components we found.
But basically, this is just two depth
first searches, the runtime is linear O of
V plus E, and this gives us
a nice efficient algorithm for
finding our strongly connected components.
Well, that completes our unit
on this graph exploration and
decomposition algorithms.
These tell us how to find ways to get
from one vertex in the graph to another.
However, when you're actually trying
to solve this problems in practice,
you don't just want any route
on your map that gets me from
where I am in San Diego to say,
Los Angeles.
The route that I find might
pass me through New York and
Florida on the way, and
I don't want to do that.
What I really want to do is I
want to find an efficient path.
How do I get there which spends
as little time as possible, or
maybe as little money as possible.
And this is what we're going to
start talking about in the next unit
where Michael is going
to be talking to you
about how to find
shortest paths in graphs.
So, I hope you enjoyed this unit and
will come back for the next one.