Hello everybody, welcome back.
Today, we're going to start
talking about binary search trees.
In particular, we're going to talk about
what the binary search tree data structure
is, how it's constructed, and the basic
properties that need to be maintained.
So last time we came up with this
idea of a local search problem,
we wanted a data structure
to be able to solve it.
And we know that none of the data
structures we had seen up till this point
were sufficient to solve
the problems that we wanted.
But one maybe came closer than the others.
Sorted arrays were okay, in that you could
actually do searches efficiently on them.
But unfortunately, you couldn't
do updates in any reasonable way.
But the fact that these things allowed for
efficient binary searches sort of
maybe gives us a good starting point for
what we're looking for.
So, what we should look at is,
we should really see this
operation of binary search.
What does it entail, and
what exactly makes it work?
And so we all know how
a binary search works, right?
So you've got your list of numbers,
you pick the one in the middle.
You ask, is the thing I am looking for
bigger than this or less than this?
If it's smaller, I sort of look at
the middle of first half of the array, and
say, is it bigger or less than that?
If it's larger, I look to the second
half of the array, and ask,
is it bigger or less than that?
And I sort of keep on
asking these question and
each time it sort of narrows down my
search space until I get an answer.
But as you'll note,
sort of associated to this sort of binary
search procedure is a search tree.
If you sort of consider
which questions you ask.
First, I ask about,
is it bigger or less than seven?
If it's smaller, I ask about four.
If it's bigger, I ask about 13.
If I got four and said it was bigger
than four, I'd then ask about six.
And I have this sort of
whole tree of possibilities.
Every time I ask a question it sort
of splits into two different cases.
And maybe the key idea here is that
if you want to do a binary search,
instead of doing it on the array,
you could just have this search tree.
You start at the top of the tree,
at seven.
And then you head down to 4 or 13,
depending on where you go, and
then you keep going down
until you find your answer.
And so in some sense,
the search tree is as good as the array.
But while a sorted array,
as we saw, was hard to insert into,
the tree is actually a lot
easier to work with in that way.
And it turns out this search tree going
to be the thing that allows us to
implement these operations
in much better way.
Okay, so what do we need to
be the case for the subtree?
Well, I mean, like all trees,
it should have a root node,
each node should have two children.
It should have a left side, which is sort
of where you're going to go when you
find out that things
are smaller than that.
And then you have a right side,
which is where you go when
things are bigger than that.
So, to be a little bit more formal,
the tree is constructed
out of a bunch of nodes.
Each node is sort of a data type
that stores a bunch of things.
Importantly, it stores a key, it stores
a value that you're comparing things to.
It also should have a pointer
to the parent node and
a pointer to the left child and
a pointer to the right child.
And to be a search tree, it needs to
satisfy one very critical property.
If you look at the key of a node X,
then, well,
the stuff on the left should be where
you're going if you do a comparison and
find the thing you're looking for
is smaller than X.
And that means that, all the keys stored
on all the nodes in the left subtree of x,
all the descendants of its left child,
need to have a smaller key than X does.
And similarly, if you found that
something was bigger than X and
go to the right,
it had better actually be on the right.
And so, the things whose keys are larger
than X need to be on the right
subtree of X.
So just review this.
I mean, we have this following
three trees, A, B, and C.
Which one of these trees satisfy
the Search Tree Property?
Well, it turns the only correct one is B,
B it works out.
A has this issue that up at
the top you've got this node 4 and
on the left side,
it has everything bigger than 4 and
on the right side,
it has everything smaller than 4.
And it's supposed to be
the other way around, but
if you switch 4's left and right sides,
everything would work out there.
Now case C is a little bit more subtle.
There's really only one problem here.
And that's that you have
this root node which is a 5.
And there's another 4, but
4 is part of 5's right subtree.
And remember,
everything on the right subtree of
any node has to be larger than it.
And this 4 is smaller.
And so other than that one mistake,
things are okay there as well.
Okay, so this is the structure.
Next time we're going to talk
about how to do basic operations
on binary search trees and sort of
give a little bit of pseudocode for
how to do these things and then we'll sort
of have a basic start for this project.