Hello everybody, welcome back.
We're continuing to talk
about binary search trees.
And today, we're going to talk about
how to implement the basic operations
of a binary search tree.
So we're going to talk about this and
talk about a few of the difficulties
that show up when you're trying it.
Okay, so let's start with searching.
And this is sort of the key thing that
you want to be able to do on the binary
search tree.
And the primary operation that
we're going to look at for
how to do this is what
we're going to call Find.
Now Find is a function.
What it takes is a key k and
the root R of a tree.
And what it's going to return is the node
in the subtree with R as the root
whose key is equal to k.
Okay, that's the goal and
the idea is pretty easy.
I mean the search tree is set
up to do binary searches on.
So what we're going to do is we're going
to sort of start at the top of the tree.
We're going to compare 6,
the thing we're searching for, to 7.
6 is less than 7 and
that means since everything less
than 7 is in its left subtree,
we should look in the left subtree.
So we go left.
We now compare 6 to 4,
the root of this left subtree.
6 is bigger than 4.
Everything bigger than 4 in
the place that we're looking
is going to be in 4s right subtree,
so we had down in that way.
We now compare 6 to 6.
They're equal, and so
we are done with our search.
And so this algorithm is actually
very easy to implement recursively.
If the key of R.Key = k, then we're done.
We just return the node R at the root and
that's all there is to it.
Otherwise, if R.key > K,
we need something less than R,
so the thing we're looking for
should be in the left subtree.
So we recursively run Find on k and
R's left child.
On the other hand, if R.key < k,
we have to look in the right subtree, so
we find k in the subtree of Rs child.
Okay, this works fine as long as the thing
we're looking is in the tree, but
what happens if we're looking for
a key that isn't there?
So we're trying to find 5 in this tree.
We checked it's less than 7.
It's more than 4.
It's less than 6.
6 doesn't have a left child.
We have a null pointer,
what do we do here?
Well, in some sense we could just return
some errors saying the thing you were
looking for wasn't there, but
we did actually find something useful.
We didn't find 5 in the tree,
because its not there, but
we sort of figured out where 5 should
have been in the tree if it were there.
And so, if you stop your search right
before you hit the null pointer,
you can actually something useful.
You find the place where
k would fit in the tree.
So it makes a little bit of sense
to modify this Find procedure so
that if say R.key > k, then instead of
just checking the left points here,
we first check to see if R
actually has a left child.
If Rs Left child isn't null,
we can recursively try to
find k in the left subtree.
But otherwise, if it is null,
we'll just stop early and return R and
do something similar for the other case.
And this sort of means that
if we're searching for
something that's not in the tree,
we at least give something close to it.
Okay, so that's one thing we can do.
Another thing that we might want to do
is sort of talk with adjacent elements.
If we've got some element in the tree,
we might want to find the next element.
And so in particular another function
we might want which we will call next.
It takes a node N and outputs the node in
the same tree with the next largest key.
And maybe one way to think about this is
instead of searching for every key and has
we should search the tree for something
just a tiny bit bigger than that.
And, now if N has a right
child this is kind of easy.
The first bunch of steps lead you to
the node N, and then you want to go right,
because it is bigger than N.
But after you do that you
just keep going left,
because it's not, it's smaller
than all of these other things.
They're a little bit bigger than N.
And you just keep going until you hit a
node where you can't go left any further.
It's left pointer is null, and
that's going to be the successor.
Now, this doesn't work if N has no right
child, because you can't go right from N.
You also go looking on the left side of N,
doesn't work.
Everything is going to be smaller there.
So instead what you have to do
is you have to go up the tree.
You check its parent, and
if its parent is smaller than n as well,
you have to check the grandparent.
You just keep going up until you find
the first ancestor that's bigger than n.
And once you have that,
that will actually be the successor.
So, the algorithm for next involves
a little bit of case analysis.
If N does not have a right child,
we're going to run this protocol we call
RightAncestor, which goes up until
you take the first step right?
Otherwise, we are going to return what
we're going to call the LeftDescendant of
Ns right child which means you sort of go
left, until you can't go left anymore.
Now both of these are easy to implement,
recursively for
LeftDescendant if you don't have a left
child, you're done, you return N.
Otherwise you take one step left and
repeat.
For RightAncestor you check to see if your
parent has a larger key than you if so
you return your parent otherwise
you go up a level and repeat, and
just keep going until you find it.
And so
putting these together that computes next.
Now it turns out that this range search
operation that we talked about before,
this you're given two numbers x and
y and the root of the tree and
you'd like to return a list of all
the nodes whose keys are between x and
y you can implement this pretty
easily using what we already have.
So, the idea is, well,
you want to find the RangeSearch, say,
everything between 5 and 12.
First thing you do is you do a search for
the first element in that range,
in this case, it will be 6.
Then you find the next element,
which is 7, and the next element,
which is 10 and the next element is 13,
it's too big so you stop.
So the implementation is pretty easy.
We create a list L that's going
to store everything that we find,
we let N be what we get when we try to
find the left N point x within our tree.
And then while the key of this note
N that we're working at is less than
y as long as the key is bigger than x,
we're going to this node to our list and
then we're going to replace N by Next(N).
We're just going to iterate through
these nodes until they're too big, and
then we return L.
Okay, so that's how you do range search.
And nearest neighbors, you can
figure it out, it's a similar idea.
Now, the interesting things are how
do we do inserts and deletes?
So, for insertion we want to be given
the key k and the root R of the tree and
we'd like to add a node with
key equal to k to our tree.
And the basic idea is that unlike with our
certain array with the tree we can just
have a new element and just have
it hanging off one of our leaves.
And this works perfectly well.
There is a big of a technical
problem here, though.
We can't just have it hang off anywhere.
I mean, three that we're
inserting is smaller than seven,
so it needs to be on
the left side of seven.
And furthermore, there are a whole bunch
of other things that needs to satisfy to
keep the search property working out.
But, fortunately for us,
this find operation.
If we tried to find A node
that wasn't in our tree
actually did tell us where
that node should belong was.
So to insert we just find our key
within R, and that gives us P,
and the new node that we want should be
a child of P, on the appropriate right or
left side, depending on
the comparison between things.
And that's that.
A little bit more difficult is Delete.
So, here we just want to node N,
we should remove it from our tree.
Now there's a problem we can't just
delete the node because then its
parent doesn't have a child.
It's children don't have parents,
it breaks things apart.
So we need to find some
way to fill the gap.
And there is a natural
way to fill this gap.
The point is you want to fill the gap with
something nearby in the sorted order, so
you try and find the next element,
X, and maybe you just take X and
fill the gap that you
created by deleting this.
Unfortunately, there could be a problem.
Now, X turns out because it's
the next element that often not
going to have a left child, because the
left child would be sort of even closer.
But it might have a right child and
if it does have this right child,
then by moving X side of the way it's
right child is now going to be orphaned.
It's not going to have a proper parents.
So in addition to moving X to
fill that gap you have to move Y
up to fill the gap that you made
by moving X out of the way.
But once you do that it's
actually perfectly good.
You've done a reasonable rearrangement
tree and removed nodes you want.
So the implementation takes
a little bit of work.
First you check to see
if N has a right child.
If it's right child is null then it
turns out we're not in this other case.
But you can just remove N and you need
to promote Ns left child, if it has one.
So Ns left child should now
become the child of Ns parent
instead of the other way around.
Otherwise we're going to
let X be next of N and
note that X does not have a left child.
And then we're going to replace N by X and
promote Xs right child to sort of
fill the gap that we made
by moving X out of the way.
But this all works.
Just to review it, so
if we have the following tree and
we're deleting the highlighting node.
Which of the following three
trees do we end up with?
Well the answer here is C.
The point is that we deleted 1 so
we want to replace it with
the next element which is 2.
So we took 2 and
put it to the place where 1 was.
Now 2s child, 4, needs to be promoted.
So 4 now becomes the new child.
Six and everything works nicely and
in this tree.
Okay so if I tell you implement some
basic operations for binary search trees
next time we'll going to talk about
the run time of these operations, which
are going to leads us to some interesting
ideas about the balance of these trees.