Hi.
In this lesson, you will learn about
applications of hashing to problems
regarding strings and texts.
We will consider the problem
of finding patterns in text.
The problem is, given a long text T,
for example a book or a website or
a Facebook profile, and some pattern P
which can be a word, a phrase, a sentence.
Find all occurrences of
pattern in the text.
Some examples of that can be that you
want to find all occurrences were name on
the website or you want to find all
the Twitter messages about your company to
analyze the reviews of your new product.
Or, you could potentially want to detect
all the files in your computer which
are infected by specific computer virus
and in that case you won't find letters
in text, you will find code patterns
in the binary code of the program.
Anyway the algorithm will be the same.
First we introduce some new notations,
substring notation, we denote by S from
I to J the substring of string S, starting
in position I and ending in position J.
Both I and
J are included in the substring.
For example, if S is the string ABCDE,
then S from zero to four
is the same string ABCDE because
we index our characters from zero
and A is the character number zero and
E is the character number four.
S from one to three is bcd because b
is the character with index one and
d is the character with index three.
And S from two to two is also allowed.
It's a sub-string of length one, string c.
And I shouldn't be more than J of
course because otherwise there
is no sub-string from I to J.
So, the formal version of our
problem to find pattern in text
is that you're given strings T and
P as input and
you need to find all such
positions I in the text T
that pattern P occurs in text
T starting from position I.
That is the same that to say
that a substring of t from I to
I plus length of T minus one, the
substring of T starting from I with length
equal to the length of the pattern
is equal to the pattern.
So we want to find all such
positions i and, of course,
i can be from zero to length of
text minus length of pattern.
It cannot be bigger because otherwise
the pattern just won't fit in the text,
it will be ending to the right
from the end of the text.
So we've start with a naive
algorithm to solve this problem.
Physically we go through
all possible positions,
i from zero to difference of
the length of the text and pattern.
And then for each such position I would
just check character by character,
whether the corresponding
sub string of T starting in
position number I is equal
to the pattern or not.
If it is equal to the pattern we
advance position I to the result.
First we need to implement a function
to compare two strings and
we start with checking whether their
lengths are the same or not of cvourse if
the lengths of strings is different then
the strings are definitely difference.
If that's not the case,
then the length of the strings are equal.
And then we go through all
the positions in both strings with
I going from zero to length of
the first string minus one.
And if the corresponding symbols
on the ith position differ,
then the strings are different.
Otherwise they are the same.
Now we will use this function to find
our occurrence of pattern in the text.
The procedure find pattern naive
implements our naive algorithm.
So let's start with an empty list in
the variable result and then we'd would
go through all the possible positions
where pattern could start with X for
I from zero to lines of text
minus length of the pattern and
we check whether the substring
starting in I with
length equal to length of the pattern
is equal to the pattern itself.
If it is, then we append position
I to the result because this is
a position where pattern occurs in
text and then, we just return the list
that we collected by going through all
possible positions of pattern in the text.
I'd say that the running time of
this naive algorithm is big O of
length of the text multiply
by length of the pattern.
Why is that?
Well, each call to the function AreEqual,
runs in time big O,
of length of the pattern,
because both strings we pass there,
are of lengths,
the same as the length of the pattern.
And, the running time of AreEqual,
is linear.
And then we have exactly
length of T minus length of P
plus one calls of this function,
which total to big O of length
of T multiplied by length of P,
because we always consider that length
of the text is bigger than the length of
the pattern, and so this is the upper
bound for our running time.
Actually, this is not just the upper
bound, it's also lower bound.
For example, consider, text T,
which consists of many,
many letters, a, and pattern P,
many letters a, and
then letter b in the end, and also
we choose such text that it is much longer
than the pattern which is basically
almost always true in
the practical problems.
For each position i and
t which we try to observe
the goal to our equal to make
has to make all of the maximum
possible number of comparisons which is
equal to the length of the pattern B.
Why is that?
Because one would call our equal for
substring of T starting in position I and
for the pattern B.
We see that they differ only in the last
characters so our equal has to check all
of the previous characters until it comes
to the last character of P and determines
that actual pattern is different from
the corresponding substring of D.
Last in this case the naive algorithm
will do at least proportional
to length of T multiplied
by length of T operations.
That's our estimate is not just big O,
it is big letter which means that
it is not only in upper bound but
also a lower bound on the writing
time on the naive algorithm.
In the next video we will
introduce an algorithm based on
hashing which has better running time