Hi, in this video,
we'll introduce Rabin-Karp's Algorithm for
finding all occurrences
of a pattern in the text.
At first it will have the same
running time as the Naive Algorithm
from the previous video.
But then we'll be able to improve it
significantly for the practical purposes.
So we need to compare our pattern
to all substrings S of text T,
with length the same as
the length of the pattern.
And in the Naive algorithm,
we just did that by checking character by
character whether pattern is equal
to the corresponding substring.
And the idea is we could use hashing to
quickly compare P with substrings of T.
So, how to do that?
Well, let's introduce
some hash function h and
of course if it is
a deterministic hash function.
And we see that the value of hash
function on the pattern P is
different from the value of this
hash function on some string S.
Then definitely P is not equal to S,
because h is deterministic.
However if the value of hash function on
P is equal to the value of hash function
on S, P can be equal to S or it can be
different from S if there is a collision.
So to exactly check
whether P is equal to S or
not we will need to call
our function AreEqual(P,S).
And so this doesn't yet save us any time.
But we hope that we could
call this function AreEqual
less frequently because there
will be only few collisions.
So we'll use polynomial hashing family.
Polygraphic P with index p small
with some big prime number p.
And if P pattern is not equal
to S substring of text,
then the probability that the value
of the hash function on the pattern
is the same as the value of hash
function on the sub string is at
most length of the pattern divided
by our big prime number p.
And we'll choose,
a prime number P big enough, so
that this probability will be very small.
So here is the code,
of our algorithm RabinKarp.
It takes its input, text T, and pattern P.
And it starts by initializing the hash
function from polynomial family.
We first choose a very big prime number p.
We'll talk later about how to choose it,
how big it should be.
And we also choose a random
number x between 1 and p- 1.
Choose the specific hash function
from the polynomial family.
Initialize all our list of positions where
pattern occurs in text with an empty list.
We also precompute the hash
value of our pattern, and
we call the PolyHash function to do that.
And then we again need to go through all
possible starting positions of pattern and
text.
So we go from i from zero to difference
of the length of text and pattern.
And for each i, we take the substring
starting in this position i and
of length equal to
the lengths of the pattern,
which is t from i to i plus
length of the pattern minus 1.
And you compute the hash
value of this substring.
And then we'll look at the hash of
the pattern and the hash of the substring.
If they are different,
then it means that definitely,
P is not equal to this substring.
And so,
P doesn't occur in position i and so
we don't need to do anything in this
iteration so we just continue to the next
iteration of the loop
without calling AreEqual.
However, if has values pHash and
tHash aren't equal,
then we need to check if it's true that
P is really equal to the substring
of T starting in position i or it is
just a collision of our hash function.
And to do that we make
a call to AreEqual and
pass there the substring and the pattern.
If AreEqual returns true,
it means that pattern is really equal to
the correspondence substring of texts, and
then we advance position i to resolve.
Because pattern P occurs in
position i in the text T.
Otherwise we just continue to
the next situation of our for loop.
So this more or less the same as naive
algorithm, but we have an additional
checking of hash value, and so
we're not always calling AreEqual.
We are calling AreEqual either if P
is equal to the corresponding sub
string of T or if there is a collision.
Let's estimate the running
time of this algorithm.
So first we need to talk
about false alarms.
We'll call false alarm the event
when P is compared with
a substring of T from i to
i plus length of P minus 1.
Compared inside the AreEqual procedure,
but
pattern P is actually not
equal to this substring.
So there's a false alarm in the sense
that P doesn't occur in the text T
starting from position i, but
we still called the AreEqual function.
And we need to go character
by character through P and
the substring to test that
they're actually not equal.
So the probability of false alarm as
we know from the previous lesson,
is at most length of the pattern over
prime number P, which we choose.
So on average, the total number of false
alarms will be the number of iterations
of our for loop,
multiplied by this probability.
And so this total number of false
alarms can be made very small if we
choose prime number P, bigger than
the product of length of the text,
and length of the pattern.
Much bigger.
So now let's estimate the running
time of everything in our
code except for
calls to the AreEqual function.
So the hash value of the pattern is
computed in time big O of length of
the pattern.
Hash of the substring corresponding
to the pattern is computed
in the same big O of length
of the pattern time.
And this is done length of text minus
length of the pattern plus 1 times
because that is the number of
iterations of the for loop.
So the total time to compute
all those hash values
is big O of length of text multiplied
by the length of the pattern.
Now what about the running
time of all calls to AreEqual?
Each call to AreEqual is computed in big O
of length of the pattern because we pass
there are two strings of length
equal to length of the pattern.
However, AreEqual is called only when
the hash value of the pattern as
the same as the hash value of
the corresponding substring of T.
And that means that either P
occurs in position i in text T or
there was a false alarm.
And by selecting the prime
number to be very big,
much bigger than the product of the length
of text, and the length of pattern,
we can make the number of false alarms
negligible, at least on average.
So, if q is the number of times
that pattern P is actually found,
in different positions in the text T,
then the total time spent in AreEqual,
on average, is big O of q.
Which is number of times P is
really found, plus the fraction
T minus P plus 1 multiplied by P and
divided by prime, p.
Which is the average number of
times that a false alarm happens.
So q plus number of false
alarms is the number of
times that we need to actually
call function AreEqual.
And then the time spent inside
the function AreEqual is proportional to
the length of the pattern.
So, this is the same as the O of q
multiplied by the length of the pattern,
because the second summoned
can be made pretty small,
less than 1 if we choose
big enough prime number p.
And we'll only get the first summoned
multiplied by the length of the pattern.
And now the total running time of
the Rabin-Karp's algorithm in this variant
is big O length of text multiplied
by length of pattern plus
q multiplied by the length of pattern.
But, of course we know that the number of
times that pattern occurs in text is not
bigger than the number of characters,
in text.
Because there are only so many different
positions where the pattern could start,
in text.
So, this sum is dominated by
the sum of big O of length of text,
multiplied by length of the pattern.
So, this is basically the same
running time as our estimate for
the naive algorithm.
So we haven't improved anything yet,
but this time can be improved for
this algorithm with a clever trick.
And you will learn it in the next video.