Hi, in this video we'll use the
precomputed hashes from the previous video
to improve the running time of
the RabinKarp cell algorithm.
And here is the pseudo code.
Actually it is very similar to
the pseudo code of the initial
RabinKarp algorithm and
only a few lines changed.
So again, choose a very big prime
number p and we choose a random number
x from 1 to p- 1 to choose a random Hash
function from the polynomial family.
We initialize the result
with an positions.
And we compute the hash of
the pattern in the variable pHash
directly using our implementation
of polynomial hash.
And then we call
the PrecomputeHashes function from
the previous video to precompute big H,
an array with hash values
of all sub strings of the text with
length equal to the pattern p.
We need them to check whether it
makes sense to compare pattern to
a sub string if their hashes are the same.
Or maybe if their hashes
are different then,
there is no point comparing them character
by characte,r because it means that
pattern is definitely
different from the substream.
So, then our main for loop goes for
all i, starting positions for
the pattern, from 0 to length of text
minus length of pattern as in the previous
version of the RabinKarp's algorithm.
And the main thing that changed is that.
We compare the hash of the pattern,
not with a vary
of hash functions computed on the fly, but
with the pre-computed value of the hash
function for the substream
starting in position i, H[i].
If they are different, it means that
the pattern is definitely different from
the substream starting in position i and
we don't need to compare them character
by character, so we just continue to
the next iteration of the for loop.
Otherwise, if the hash value
of the pattern is the same
as the hash value of the substring,
we need to actually compare them on
the quality, character by character.
And to do that, we call function AreEqual
for the substring and the pattern.
If they are actually equal,
we append position i to the result
to the list of all the occurrences
of pattern indexed.
Otherwise, we proceed
to the next iteration.
And in the end, we return result,
the list of all positions in
which pattern occurs in the text.
Let's analyze the running time of this
version of RabinKarp's algorithm.
First we compute the hash
value of the pattern in time
proportional to its length.
Then we call
the PrecomputeHashes function,
which we estimated in
the previous video around
in time proportional to the sum of
length of text and the pattern.
And then the only other thing that
we do is we compare the hashes,
and for some of the substrings
we call function AreEqual.
And we already know from the previous
videos that the total time spent in
AreEqual is on average, proportional to
q multiplied by length of the pattern,
where q is the number of
occurrences of pattern and text.
Why is that?
Because we only compared pattern
to a substring if they're equal or
if there's a collision.
You can compare such a big prime P, that
the collisions have very low probability,
and on average,
they won't influence the running time.
So, on average, total time spent
in AreEqual is proportional to q
multiplied by length of the pattern.
And then the total average running time,
is proportional to length of the text,
plus q plus 1,
multiplied by length of the pattern.
And this is actually much better, than the
time for the algorithm, because usually
q is very small, q is the number of times
you actually found pattern in text.
If you are, for example, searching for
your name on a website or
for infected code pattern in
the binary code of the program,
there will be no or only a few
places where you actually find it.
And that their number is q and it is
usually much, much less than the total
number of positions in the test
which is length of the test.
So the second sum of [q plus 1 multiplied
by 1 looks like by length of the pattern
is much smaller than length of the text
multiply it by length of the pattern.
And if pattern is sufficiently long,
then the first summoned is also
much smaller than length of the text
multiplied by length of the pattern.
So we improved our running time for most
practical purposes very significantly.
Of course it's only an average, but
in practice, this will work really well.
And to conclude.
In this module, we cited hash tables and
hash functions, and we learned that hash
tables are useful for storing sets of
objects and mappings from one
type of object to another one.
And we managed to do it in such
a way that you can search and
modify keys and values of the hash
tables in constant time on average.
And to do so,
you must use good hash families, and
you must select random hash
functions from good hash families.
And you also learned that
hashes are not only useful for
storing something, but they're also
useful while working with strings and
texts, for finding patterns in long texts.
And actually, there are a lot
more applications of hashing
in distributed systems, for
example, and in data science.
And I'll tell you about
some applications and
distributive systems in
the next few optional videos.