Now, let's talk about the final
way to do amortized analysis,
which is the physicist's method.
The idea of the physicist's method
is to define a potential function,
which is a function that takes
a state of a data structure and
maps it to an integer
which is its potential.
This is similar in spirit to what you
may have learned in high school physics,
the idea of potential energy.
For instance, if you have a ball and
you take it up to the top of a hill,
you've increased its potential energy.
If you then let the ball roll down the
hill, its potential energy decreases and
gets converted into kinetic
energy which increases.
We do the same sort of thing for
our data structure, storing in it
the potential to do future work.
Couple of rules about
the potential function.
First, phi of h sub 0.
So, phi is the potential function.
h sub 0 is time 0 of the data structure h,
so that means the initial
state of the data structure, and
that has to have a potential of 0.
Second rule is that
potential is never negative.
So, at any point in time, phi of h
sub t is greater than or equal to 0.
So, once we've defined
the potential function,
we can then say what amortized cost is.
The amortized cost of an operation
t is c sub t, the true cost,
plus the change in potential, between,
before doing the operation and
after doing the operation.
So, before doing the operation,
we have phi(h sub t-1) after we have
phi(h sub t), so it's c sub t plus
phi(h sub t)- phi(h sub t-1).
What we need to do is choose
a function phi, such that,
if the actual cost is small,
then we want the potential to increase.
So that we're saving up some potential for
doing later work.
And if c sub t is large,
then we want the potential to decrease.
In a way to sort of pay for that work.
So, the cost of in operations
is the sum of the true costs
which is a summation from
i goes from one to n of c sub i.
And, what we want to do is relate
the sum of the true costs to the sum of
the amortized costs.
So, the sum of the amortized costs is
the summation from i equals 1 to n of
the definition of the amortized cost.
Which is (c sub i + phi(hsub i) -
phi(h sub i-1)).
Or, we could just rewrite that.
So, removing the summation is c sub 1
+ phi of (h sub 1)- phi of (h sub 0),
+ c sub 2 + phi of (h sub 2)-
phi of (h sub 1) and so on.
What's important to note is that we have
a phi of h sub 1 in the first line and
then a minus phi of h sub 1 in the second
line, so those two cancel out.
Similarly, we have a phi of h
sub 2 in the second line, and
we have a phi of h sub 3 when we look
at the amortized cost at time three.
And, that goes on and
on until at time n-1, we would have a phi
of h sub n-1 positive and
a negative phi of h sub n-1 negative.
So, if all these cancellations and
all we're left with is
the very first term phi of h sub 0,
negative phi of h sub 0,
and the very last term in the last
line which is phi of h sub n.
So, this really just equals phi of h sub n
minus phi of h sub 0 because all the other
phis cancel, plus the summation
from i equals 1 to n of c sub i,
that is the true costs.
Since phi of h sub n is non negative and
phi of h sub 0 is 0,
this value is greater than or equal to
just the summation of the true costs.
What that means then is we've
come up with a lower bound on
the sum of the amortized
costs which is the sum of the true costs.
So therefore, if we want to look at a cost
of a entire sequence of operations,
we know it's at least
the sum of the true costs.
So, let's look at applying this
physicist's method to the dynamic array.
So, we're going to look
at n calls to PushBack.
Phi of h, so, at any given time
the data structure's going to be two
times the size minus the capacity.
So, as the size increases,
the potential's going to be increasing for
a given fixed capacity.
Phi of x sub here, so
we want to make sure that our phi
function satisfies our requirements.
So, first phi of 0 is 2 x 0- 0,
assuming we have an initial array
of size 0, and that's just 0.
Also, phi of h sub i
is 2 x size - capacity.
We know that size is at
least capacity over 2, so
therefore, 2 x size - capacity
is greater than 0.
Now, let's look at our amortized cost.
So, we're going to assume we
don't have to do a resize and
let's look at the amortized cost.
So, we add a particular element i and
the amortized cost is
the cost of insertion plus
phi(h sub i) - phi(h sub i-1).
So, the cost of insertion is just going to
be 1 because we're adding an element and
we don't have to do any
moving of elements.
Phi of h sub i is 2 x size
of i - the capacity of i, and
phi of h sub i- 1 is 2 x
size i- 1 - capacity i- 1.
Well, what do we know?
Since we're not resizing and
the capacities don't change.
So, the capacities cancel themselves out.
And so, we are left with 2
times the difference in sizes.
What's the difference in size?
Difference in size is just 1,
because we added one element, so
this is 1 + 2 x 1 or 3.
It's no accident that this 3 is the same
value that we saw when we
used the banker's method.
And then, let's look at the cost
when we have to do a resize.
So, we're going to define
here k is size sub i-1,
which is the same thing
as capacity sub i-1.
Why is it the same?
because we're about to do a resize.
So, that means that after
the previous operation,
we must have made the dynamic array full.
And then,
phi(h sub i-1) is just 2 times the old
size minus the old capacity,
and that's just 2 x k - k, or k.
Phi(h sub i) is 2 times
the size of i - capacity of i, and
that's 2(k + 1), because
the size sub i is
one more than the size of i-1, minus 2k.
Why 2k?
Because we double the capacity each time.
So, that's just equal to 2.
So, the amortized cost of adding the
element is c sub i + phi(h sub i) -
phi(h sub i - 1), which is just size of i,
because that's the number of elements we
have to, we have to move size of i-1
elements and then add the one new element,
so, that's size of i.
So, we have (sizei)+2-k,
which is just (k+1)+2-k, which is 3.
So, what we have seen now is
that the amortized cost using
the physicist's method
of adding elements is 3.