As usual before going into the details
of efficient implementation
let's check what is wrong
with naive implementations?
For example, what if we store
the contents of a priority
queue just in an unsorted array or
in an unsorted list?
In this example on the slide,
we use a doubly linked list.
Well, in this case inserting
a new element is very easy.
We just append the new element
to the end of our array or list.
For example, as follows,
if our new element is seven we can just
put it to the next available cell in our
array where we can just append
it to the end of the list.
So we put 7 to the end.
We say that the previous element of 7 is 2
and that there is no next element, right?
So it is easy and
it takes constant time, okay?
Now, what about extracting
the maximum element in this case?
Well, unfortunately we need to scan the
whole array to find the maximum element.
And we need to scan the whole
list to find the maximum element
which gives us a linear running time.
That is we O(n), right?
In our previous naive implementation
using an unsorted array or
list, the running time of
the extract max operation is linear.
Well, a reasonable approach
to try to improve this,
is to keep the contents of our array,
for example array, sorted.
Well, what are the advantages
of this approach?
Well, of course, in this case,
extract max is very easy.
So, the maximum element,
is just the last element of our array.
Right?
Which means that the running time of
ExtractMax in this case is just constant.
However, the disadvantage is that now
the insertion operation takes linear time,
and this is why.
Well, to find the right position for the
new element we can use the binary search.
This is actually good, well it can
be done in logarithmic time.
For example, if we need to
insert 7 in our priority queue,
then in logarithmic time we
will find out that it should be
inserted between 3 and
9 in this for example.
However unfortunately after
finding this right position,
we need to shift everything to
the right of this position by one.
Right just to create a vacant position for
7.
For this we need to first
shift 16 to this cell.
Then we move 10 then to this cell,
then we move 9 to this cell, and
finally we put 7 in to this cell,
and we get it sorted already.
So in the worst case, we need to shift a
linear number of cells, a linear number of
elements, which gives us a linear running
time for the insertion operation.
As we've just seen, inserting an element
into a sorted array is expensive
because to insert an element
into the middle we need to shift
all elements to the right
of this position by one.
So, this makes the running time of
the insertion procedure linear.
However if we use a doubly linked list,
then inserting into the middle of this
list is actually constant time operation.
So let's try to use a sorted list.
Well, the first advantage is
that the extract max operation
still takes constant time.
Well this is just because, well,
the maximum element in our list
is just the last element, right?
So for this reason,
we have a constant time for extract max.
Also, another advantage is that
inserting in the middle of this list
actually takes a constant amount of work,
not linear, and this is why.
Again let's try to insert 7 into our list.
Well, this can be done as follows.
We know that inserting 7 should
be done between 3 and 9.
So we do just the following.
We will remove this.
We remove this pointer and
this pointer.
We'll say that now the next
element after 3 is 7 and
the previous element before 7 is 3.
And also the next element after 3, after 7
is 9, and previous element before 9 is 7.
So inserting an element just
involves changing four pointers.
Right?
So it is a constant time operation.
However everything is not so
easy, unfortunately.
And this is because just
finding the right position for
inserting this new element
takes a linear amount of work.
And this in particular because we
cannot use binary search for lists.
Given the first element of this list and
the last element of this list, we cannot
find the position of the middle element of
this list because this is not an arry.
We cannot just compute
the middle index in this array.
So for this reason, just finding
the right position for the new element
I mean to keep the list sorted takes
already a linear amount of work.
And for this reason,
inserting into a sorted list still
takes a linear amount of work.
Well to conclude if you implement
a priority queue using a list or
an array sorted or
not then one of the operations insert and
extract max takes a linear amount of work.
In the next video we will show
a data structure called binary heap
which allows to implement
a priority queue so
that both of these operations can be
performed in logarithmic amount of work.