Hello everybody, welcome back
to the graph algorithms course.
Today we're going to be talking about
notions of connectivity in a graph,
in particular,
talking about connecting components, and
how to compute the connected
components of an undirected graph.
So, to begin with, last time we talked
about this notion of reachability,
what does it mean to be able to reach
another vertex from a given one?
And what we'd like to understand now
is really what sort of classifies
reachability in a graph?
Really not just from a single vertex but
you sort of want to understand which
vertices are reachable from which others?
And it turns out that for
an undirected graph, there's actually
a very clean categorization of this.
In particular for any graph G,
we can always partition it
into Connected Components such that two
vertices v and w are reachable from
each other, if and only if they
are in the same connected component.
So, sort of we break this
graph up into islands,
where any two islands are completely
unconnected from each other, but
within any island, you can get
from anywhere to anywhere else.
So just to make sure
we're on the same page.
If we have the following graph, how
many connected components does it have?
Well, this graph is going to have 4.
So if you look at these four things, from
each of these things they're all connected
up, but there are no edges
between any pair of them.
Okay, so let's see how the proof
of this theorem works.
Why can we always divide it
into connected components?
And basically the idea is you
need to show that reachability is
an equivalence relation.
That means three things, first is that
v is reachable from v which is easy.
Also that if v can be reached from w,
w can be reached from v which sort of is
just following the path in
the opposite direction.
And then there's the difficult one,
that if v is reachable from u and
v is also reachable from w,
then w is reachable from u.
What this says if you sort of take v and
you take everything that it connects to,
in fact,
everything in that whole region connects
to everything else in that whole region.
And that last step is not so
hard once you write it down.
The point is that you can reach u from v,
which means there's a path from v to u.
You can also find a path from v to w.
And if you should have glued these paths
together at v then you have a path
from u to w.
So they can be reached from each other.
Okay, so that completes the proof but
what we'd now like to do
is do this algorithmically.
Given a graph G, we'd like to find
the connected components of this graph.
Okay, fair enough.
Let's find an algorithm.
Well the basic idea of
this is pretty simple.
If you run explore(v),
this finds the connected component of v.
It finds everything you can reach from v.
That's the whole connected component.
And you just need to repeat this
to find all the other components.
It turns out you can do this actually with
only sort of a slight modifications of
the original depth first
search algorithm tha we saw.
Now, in order to make this algorithm,
we're about to see
a little bit more cleanly.
We're going to modify
our goal a little bit.
Instead of actually returning sort of
returning sets of vertices that are our
connected components, what we're going to
do is we're going to label the connected
components, we're going to give everything
in the first one a label of 1, and
everyone in the second components
a label of 2, and so on and so forth.
Okay, so how does this work?
First we modify our Explore procedure,
we visit the vertex,
we also make sure to visit
all of its neighbors.
We also assign the vertex a number
corresponding to it connect component,
the CC number.
Now the thing is that this variable
CC is not going to change as we
make these recursive calls to explore.
And so everything else that gets
found through the same explore
will all get assigned the same number.
However when we actually run our
DFS first search, we're going to
between different explores, between
different vertices that we explore and
then go off to find a new vertex,
we increment this number.
And so the second explore that we do
everything gets the number one bigger.
So to see how this actually works,
on this graph our counter starts at 1.
We find it on vertex say that one,
it gets labeled with a 1.
We keep exploring from that vertex and
we find these other three,
all of them get labeled with 1.
But now we are done exploring that first
vertex, so we increment the counter and
find a new unexplored vertex,
say that one.
Which we now label 2.
We keep exploring and the other vertex
that we found also gets labeled with a 2.
But then we finish that explore call.
We now increment our counter to 3 and
find a new vertex, this one.
We explore that and
everything we find gets labeled with a 3.
And now we're done.
We've got three connected components.
Everything in the first one is labeled 1.
Everything on the second
one is labeled 2 and
everything in the third one is labeled 3.
So sort of what we wanted.
Okay, to show that this is correct,
we note that each new explore call finds
a full, new connected component because
it finds everything connected to that V.
And of course,
because V had not been found yet,
it was not in a connected component
that we had already seen.
Secondly, because of the way
this outer loop and depth for
search works, every vertex
eventually gets found, because
every vertex we eventually check to see if
it's visited, and if not, we explore it.
Now the run time of this is basically
just the run time of depth for search.
We only made sort of cosmetic
modifications to it.
So the run time is still O
of size of V plus size of E.
Okay, so that's our discussion of
how to compute connected components.
Next time we're going to talk about some
other applications of depth for search.
So I'll be happy to see
you in the next lecture.