Hello everybody, welcome back
to the Graph Algorithms course.
Today, we're going to talk about
previsit and postvisit orderings.
And these are sort of some numbers that
you can do when running a depth for
search that sort of records some
information about the order in which you
visited vertices.
And and
we're going to discuss a little about
why these numbers might be important.
But mostly it's going to be that they
will turn out the be very useful in some
algorithms we're going to discuss later.
Okay, so
let's talk about depth [INAUDIBLE],
it is algorithm that we came up last time.
And it's a little bit
weird as an algorithm,
because well what happens
when you run depth for surge?
It doesn't return anything,
it does modify the state of some things.
It marks vertices as visited or unvisited.
But in the end it just ends up
marking any vertex as being visited.
If all that you wanted to do is mark every
vertex as visited there are easier ways
to do it.
On the other hand the order in
which we find these vertices and
away that involves their connectivity
is actually very useful.
For example with slight modification,
keeping track of a little bit of data we
saw how to use depth for
a search to compute connected components.
So in general, if we want to make
that depth [INAUDIBLE] useful,
we need to keep track of some extra
information about its execution.
So what we're going to do for
this is we're going to augment some of its
functions in order to store
additional information.
So for example, let's look at Explore.
What we're going to do is we're
going to mark the vertex as visited.
But then before we do anything else,
we're going to run some previsit function.
This is just some extra
things that we're doing,
just to maybe record some information or
do a little bit of extra work sort
of just as we found this new vertex.
Then we go in this loop over neighbors and
exploring all the unexplored neighbors.
And then right before we're
about to finish exploring v,
we run some other post visit blocks.
Some thing that we did,
do it right before we're finishing.
So what are these functions going to be?
They could be a number of things.
We'll come up with an example shortly,
but the idea is to augment our
functions a little bit to keep
track of some extra information.
So what sort of extra
information do we want?
Well one that we might want to
do is to keep track of sort
of what order are we visit vertices in.
And so one way to do this
is we sort of have a clock.
This clock keeps track of time,
it ticks forward once every time we hit
a previsit or postvisit for a vertex.
Every time we discover a new vertex for
the first time or sort of leave
an old vertex for the last time.
And every time we do one of these
things we'll also core the time
which that happens.
So for each vertex, we will have
a record of the previsit time and
the postvisit time.
So to what you seen what I mean by this,
let's look again this example.
The clock starts at 1,
we visit our first vertex, its gives
us previsit number assigned as 1.
From there, we explore the second
vertex which is previsit 2, and
then a third vertex which
gets previsit of 3.
From there, we start, well,
we're done exploring that vertex.
All of its neighbors have
already been visited.
So we assign it postvisit 4 and move on,
this other vertex gets postvisit 5.
We now have a new vertex to explore,
it gets previsit 6 and postvisit 7.
And our original postvisit 8 and
that wraps up our first explore.
We now find a new vertex,
who gives previous at 9 and
his neighbor previous at 10.
And then they get post
visit numbers 11 and 12.
Finally, we've got a new guy with previsit
13 and his neighbors get 14 and 15 and
they get postvisits 16,
17 and 18, we wrap them up.
And we are now done and
we just assigned the numbers 1 through 18
as the previsit and postvisit numbers
of these 9 different vertices.
So the way we compute this
is actually pretty easy.
We just have to initialize our clock to be
1 the beginning of our depth first search.
And then in the previsit
block of our explorer,
we set the previsit number of v to be this
clock value and then increment the clock.
And for the post visit block we set post
visit number of the vertex to be the clock
value and increment the clock.
Very easy, doesn't really change
the run time of anything, but
allows us to compute these numbers.
Now, what are these useful for?
Well, really the previsit and
postvisit numbers,
the tell us something about
the execution of the depth first search.
And we'll see a little bit of this
as we prove the following Lemma.
So suppose that you have
any two vertices u and v.
From these u,
v intervals pre(u) to post(u) and
then pre(v) to post(v),
these are two intervals.
And the claim is that these intervals
are either nested or disjoint.
And in a particular whether are nested or
disjoint will actually tell us something
useful about the sort of
way in which the depth for
search ran on these two vertices.
So let's take a look at
what we mean by this.
If you have two intervals,
there are a few ways in which they
can intersect with each other.
Firstly, could be the case that one
interval is strictly contained in
the other one.
These means that they're nested.
It could also be that they're
disjoint from each other,
that they don't overlap at all.
Finally, we could have two
intervals that are interleaved.
They sort of overlap
over part of their ends,
but not over the entire
interval either side.
And what we're saying in this dilemma
is that the interleaved case is
actually not possible.
So let's see the proof.
We first assume that
without laws of generality,
the first visit to u happens
before the first visit to v.
We now have two cases to consider.
First thing that we find v for the first
time in the midst of exploring u.
And this really is an indepth research
tree that we produced by this exploration.
We found v as a descendant of u,
we found v while exploring u.
The second thing is we could find
v after we're done exploring u.
So it's sort of v and
u are different branches of the tree,
they're cousins of each other.
So let's look at the first case.
If we explore v while we're
in the middle of exploring u,
then explore v is actually being
run as a subroutine of explore u.
And because of the way subroutines work
we can't finish exploring uuntil we
are finished exploring v.
And therefore the post of u is
bigger than the post of v and
these two intervals are nested.
In the second case, we explore
the after we're done exploring u.
So we start exploring u and
then we finish exploring u,
and then sometime later we start
exploring v and then finish exploring v.
And so
these intervals are going to be disjoined.
And so these are the only cases the
intervals are nested or they're disjoined.
And which case we're in will actually tell
us something useful about the order in
which we visited vertices in this graph.
Now just to review we've got these two
tables here sort of pre and post numbers,
but only one of them is a possibly
valid table of pre and post numbers.
Which one is not valid?
Well the one on the right can't be
correct, because these two intervals
from pre to post for vertices A and
B Are interleaved, and that can't happen.
So that sort of pre and post orders will
see a lot more usefulness later, but
in the next lecture, we're going to
introduce something a little bit more new.
We've been talking a lot
about undirected graphs.
Here, we're going to be talking about
what happens when the edges actually have
an orientation to them.
So please come back next time,
and we can talk about that.