Hello, and welcome to the next lesson
in the dynamic programming module.
In this lesson, we will be applying the
dynamic programming technique for solving
a wide range of problems where your goal
is to find an optimal order of something.
We will illustrate this
technique by solving
the so-called placing parentheses problem.
In this problem, your input is
an arithmetic expression consisting of
numbers or digits and arithmetic
operations, and your goal is to find
an order of applying these arithmetic
operations that maximizes the radian.
You specify this order by
placing parentheses, and
that's why the problem is
called placing parentheses.
As usual we start with problem overview.
Consider the following toy
arithmetic expression.
1 + 2- 3 x 4- 5.
In this case we have five digits and
four arithmetic operations.
And we would like to find an order
of applying these four arithmetic
operations to maximize
the value of this expression.
So when the order of operation is fixed,
you do the following.
You take the first operation.
You take two adjusting digits,
and you apply these operations.
For example, if the operation is
multiplication, in this case, so
then two digits are 3 and 4.
So you multiply 3 and 4, you get 12,
and you just replace 3 times 4 by 12.
You then take the next operation,
apply it also, and replace two numbers and
the arithmetic sign by this result,
until you proceed in a similar fashion.
In the end here, you get a single number.
And your goal is to find an order
that guarantees that this
number is as large as possible.
You can specify an order just by placing
a set of parentheses in your expression.
For example, if you would like to
apply all your four operations just
from left to right,
you place the parentheses as follows.
In this particular case,
we compute the results as follows.
So we first compute 1 + 2, this is 3.
We then subtract 3 from the results.
This gives us 0.
We then multiply the result by 4.
This is still 0.
And finally, we subtract 5.
So this gives us -5.
And this is actually non-optimal, because
for example, there is a better order.
In this case, we first multiply 3 and
4, this gives us 12.
We then subtract 5, this gives us 7.
Then we go to compute the sum of 1 and
2, this gives us 3.
So when the final operation is
subtraction, we subtract 7 from 3.
This gives us -4.
So in this case the order of applying
operations was the following.
So we first compute the product of 3 and
4, so this is the first operation.
We then subtract 5.
This is the second operation.
We then compute the result of 1 + 2.
So this plus is the third operation, and
this minus is the fourth operation,
the last one.
It is not difficult to see that the
optimal value in this case is equal to 6.
And it can be obtained as follows.
You first subtract 5 from 4.
This gives you -1.
You then multiply it by 3, and you get -3.
You then compute the sum
of the first two digits.
This is 1 + 2, and that is equal to 3.
Finally you subtract -3 from 3.
This is the same as 3 + 3,
it is equal to 6.
Well, you might find
the result as follows,
you just go through all possible orders.
Let's see how many
different orders are there.
Well, there are four arithmetic
operations in this case, so
you can choose any of the four possible
arithmetic operations to be the first one.
You can choose any of these three
remaining operations to be the second one,
and you can select any of the two
remaining operations to be the third one.
And the last one is unique,
it is the only remaining operations.
So, in total, there are 4 by
3 by 2 by 1 different orders.
This is equal to 24, and you can just
enumerate all of them, write them down,
compute an answer for each of these
orderings and select the maximal value.
However, our method of going through all
possible orderings does not scale well.
And this is why.
Consider the toy example
shown on the slide.
In this case we have six digits and
five arithmetic operations.
This example will require us to go
through all possible 120 orderings.
So just because there are five iterations,
so any of five of them can be
the first one, any of the remaining four
of them can be the second one, and so on.
So this is 5 by 4 by 3 by 2 by 1,
which is equal to 120.
This is already not so
easy to do this by hand.
I mean,
to go through all possible such orderings.
Well, this is not easy, but
we can teach a computer to do this, right?
So we can implement an algorithm that
goes through all possible orderings.
However, in general, this algorithm
will perform roughly n factorial steps,
where n is the number of arithmetic
operations, for exactly the same reason.
If you have n arithmetic operations,
then any of them can be the first one.
Any of the remaining n minus 1 operations
can be the second one, and so on.
So this is n times n minus 1,
times n minus 2, and so on.
This is equal n factorial, and n factorial
is an extremely fastly growing function.
For example, 20 factorial already
equals roughly 2 times 10 to the 18.
This means that if you implement such
an algorithm, it will not be able to
compute the maximum value of an expression
consisting of just 20 digits
in a reasonable time, even in one year,
not to say about one second.
Which means, as usual,
that we need another algorithm,
as you might well have guessed.
We will use dynamic programming to find,
to design a more efficient algorithm.
In the meantime, you might want
to check your intuition by trying
a few possible orderings to
perform in this small expression,
and by using our in video quiz.