As usual, we start designing our
dynamic program in algorithm
by defining a subproblem in
a way that allows us to solve
a subproblem by solving
smaller sub subproblem.
As we said already,
this is probably the most important step
in designing dynamic
programming solutions.
So before doing this,
we define our problem formally.
So the input consists of n digits.
d1, d2, and so on, dn.
And then -1 operations between them,
which we call op1, op2, and so on, opn.
Each operation is either summation,
subtraction, or multiplication.
And our goal is to find an order
of applying these operations so
that the value of the resulting
expression is maximized.
As we discussed already,
we can specify this order just by
placing parentheses into our expression.
We start building our intuition
by reconsidering our toy example.
So assume that the multiplication is the
last operation in some optimal ordering
in an ordering leading to an optimal
value in this toy example.
Well this means that in this expression
we already have to pairs of parentheses.
And our goal is to parenthesize
the initial sub-expression and
the second sub-expression,
so as to maximize the value.
This means that it would be good for
us to know what is an optimal value for
the first subexpression and
the second subexpression, right?
And in general if you
have an expression and
if you select a realistic operation,
which is the last one,
then it splits your initial expression
into two subexpressions, right?
And for both of them it would be
good to know an optimal value.
And, in turn, each of these two
subexpressions are split into two
sub subexpressions by the last
arithmetic operations, and so on.
So this suggests Very good problem in our
case would be find an optimal value for
any subexpression or
former initial expression.
So we've just realized that it would
be good to know the optimal values for
all subexpressions of
our initial expression.
What do we mean however, by saying
optimal values for all subexpressions?
Assume for example that we need to compute
the optimal, the maximal value for
the sum of two subexpressions,
subexpression one and subexpression two.
Well this obviously means that we
would like this subexpression to be
as large as possible and this
subexpression to be as large as possible.
If on the other hand we
would like to compute
the maximum value of subexpression
one minus subexpression two.
Well this means that we would
like subexpression one to be
as large as possible while we would
like the value of subexpression two
to be as small as possible, right?
Just because we compute subexpression
one minus subexpression two.
This suggests that knowing
just the maximal value for
each subexpression would not be enough.
And this usually happens when designing
a dynamic programming solution.
This also suggests that,
instead of computing just maximal,
we will maintain what is
the maximum value and
the minimum possible value for
each subexpression.
Let's illustrate this reasoning once
again with our previous toy example.
So in this case we are maximizing
the product of two small subexpressions.
In this case these two subexpressions, so
small, that it is not difficult to
compute their minimal and maximal values.
For example, for subexpression 5- 8 + 7,
the minimum value is- 10 and
the maximal value is 4, right?
At the same time, for
the second subexpression,
(4-(8+9)), the minimum value is- 13,
while the maximum value is 5, right?
Now we would like to parenthesis
both subexpressions, so
that their product is maximal.
Well it is not difficult to see, that in
this case the optimal way to do this is
to take the minimal values of
both sub expressions, right?
So this will give us- 10 multiplied
by -13, which is equal to 130.
Right?
Which is much larger than
the product of the maximum
values of these two sub expressions
which is 4 by 5, which is 20 in turn.
Okay, we are now ready to write down the
recurrent relation for our subproblems.
Before this, let's formally define E of
ij to be the subexpression of our initial
expression resulting by taking digits from
i to j and all operations between them.
Then our goal is to compute the maximum
value of the subexpression which we denote
by capital M(i,j) and the minimum value
of the sub expression denoted by m(i,j).
Okay, can you see that our initial
subexpression from I to J and
assumes that we would like to
compute one of the extreme
values of the subexpression and
implies there is a minimum or the maximum.
Well we know that in many ordering for
this subexpression there is some
last operation, say okay so
this separation splits our
initial subexpression into
two sub subexpression namely,
subexpression i, k and
subexpression k plus 1j.
Right?
To compute the maximum value,
we just go through all possible such case,
from i to j- 1, and through all possible
extreme values for two subexpressions.
I mean, either we apply operation k
to the maximum values of these two
subexpressions or
we apply operation K to minimum value,
the minimum values of
these two subexpressions.
Or we apply it to the maximum
value of one subexpression and
the minimum value of another or
vice versa.
To compute the maximum value
of sub expression i j,
we just select the maximum
among all these possibilities.
While to compute it's minimum value,
we simply select the minimum
among all such possibilities.