We'll conclude the lesson
by a few remarks.
First of all, for
implementing a binary heap in an array,
we can as well use zero based arrays.
In this case, the formulas for
computing the parent and
the index of the parent of two children
of a given node, I changed as follows.
So, the Parent of i, is given by
the number (i-1)/2 and rounded down.
The LeftChild is given by the number 2i +
1 and the RightChild is given by 2i + 2.
The next remark is that
you can implement the binary
min-heap in exactly the same way.
And binary min-heap is a heap where
each edge is value of their parent,
is at most the value of the child.
A case like this is useful for
the case when a iteration just in
your priority queue, you need to extract
an element not with maximum priority,
but with minimum priority.
The final remark is that binary heaps can
be easily generalized through d-ary heap.
In such a heap, each node has,
at most, d children.
And we require to call
a d-ary heap complete,
we again require that all the levels
are completely filled, except for
possibly the last one where all the nodes
are in leftmost position, okay?
So the height of this
tree is in this case,
log base d of n, not the binary log of n.
This in particular means that the running
time of the SiftUp procedure is,
at most, O of log base d of n, right?
Just because the height of the tree is,
at most, log base d of n.
And the element just goes down,
just goes up.
If needed,
we swap an element with its pairing.
However, the running time
of SiftDown procedure
increases through d when
supplied by a log base u of n.
This is because when we go down,
we always need to find a direction
where to go in reach of this to go.
And this is because, when we need to
replace, to swap a node with one of
its children we first need to select which
on of these children is the largest one.
Right, so for this reason the running
time of SiftDown procedure
in this case is O of d
multiplied by log base d of n.
Okay, time to conclude in
this segment of lessons we
started by introducing the abstract
data type called priority cues.
This abstract data types supports
the following two main operations
insert an element and extract
an element with the highest priority.
This priority queues find
a lot of applications.
We will see many other reasons that
you used efficiently this data type.
Then we explain that if implemented
naively using an array, or
at least sort it or not,
one of these two operations will take a
lenient amount of work, in the worst case.
Then we presented binary heaps.
So this is a way of implement
priority queues that gives
the worst case running time,
O of log n for all operations.
And also, finally, we explained that
this also can be made space efficient.
Namely, a binary heap is a tree,
however to store this tree
we do not need you to store connections
to a parent and to children.
It is enough to store
everything in an array.
Again, this makes binary heaps
both time and space efficient.