Hello everybody, welcome back.
Today, we're going to be talking about
the algorithm of a topological sort.
And we're going to talk about this,
we're going to show in fact that
any DAG can be linearly ordered, and
we're going to show you how to do it.
So remember from last time,
we were talking about directed graphs and
in particular we wanted to be able to
linearly order the vertices of this graph.
Such that every edge pointing to a prome
vertex with smaller index under this
linear ordering something that's larger.
Now we know that in order for
this to be possible, our graph needed to
have no cycles, it needed to be a DAG.
And today, we're going to show
that this is actually sufficient.
So one way to look at this is if
you have this linear ordering,
let's think about which vertex
comes last in this order.
Well if it comes last it can
have edges pointing to it, but
it can have no edges pointing out of it.
And so this gives a motivation for
useful definition.
We say that the source is vertex in
a graph that has no incoming edges.
So a source can have as many edges
as it likes going outwards, but
it can't have any going inwards.
Similarly a sync is a vertex
with no outgoing edges.
It can have a bajillion edges coming
into it, but nothing can escape.
So to be clear that
we're on the same page,
the following graph has nine vertices,
how many of them are sinks?
Well the following highlighted
three vertices are sinks.
They each have no edges coming out,
but every other vertex
in the graph does have a few or
at least one edge leaving it.
So here's the basic idea for how we're
going to produce our linear order.
We're going to first
find a sink in the graph.
There needs to be a sink,
because there needs to be
something at the end of the order.
And when we have a sink though,
we're perfectly fine putting
it at the end of our ordering.
And the reason for this is well, it's got
edges that point into it, but as long as
the vertex comes at the end, everything
pointing to it is coming from before it.
So once we put it at the end of the order,
it's sort of dealt with and
we just need to order
the rest of the graph.
So what we do is remove that vertex
from the graph and repeat this process.
So to see what this means,
we have this graph on five vertices.
D is a sink so we put it at the end of
our ordering and remove from the graph.
Now we find another sink, say C.
Put it at the end and
remove from the graph.
E is next, goes at the end,
then B, then A.
And finally we have this ordering,
A, B, E, C, D.
And this it turns out,
is consistent with the ordering
that we had in our original graph.
Now this is all well and good, but it
depends on us being able to find a sink.
And before we even ask that,
we should ask how do we even know
that there is a sink in our graph.
And it turns out that for DAG at least,
there's an easy way to show that there is,
and the idea is the following.
What we're going to do is just
start at some vertex v1 and
we're just going to follow a path.
We're going to follow
directed edges forward and
just keep going, finding vertices v2,
v3, v4, etc, and just keep going.
Now eventually one of
two things will happen.
Either we could hit a dead end, we could
end up at some vertex with just no
outgoing edges,
we just can't extend this path anymore.
And if that's the case, we found a sink.
We found a vertex with no outgoing edges.
The second possibility though is that
maybe this path just keeps going forever.
But if it does since there are only
finitely many vertices in our graph,
eventually we'll have to repeat something.
We'll have to find a vertex for
the second time.
But when we do that it means there was
a path that started at that vertex,
went forward a bunch and
eventually came back to itself.
That means we have a cycle, and so
at least if we're DAG
that can't ever happen.
So let's take a look at the algorithm.
What we're going to do is,
while G is non empty.
We're going to follow a path until
we can't extend it any further.
That vertex at the end is going
to be a sink which we'll call v.
We take the input at the very,
very end of our ordering and
then remove it from the graph,
and then we just repeat this.
So on this graph here, well we started A,
we follow a path A, B, C, D.
Now we're stuck.
D is a sink, so
we can remove it from the graph.
We now follow a new path, A, B, C.
C is a sink, we remove it from the graph.
A and E, E is a sink, we remove it.
Path A, B, B is in sync, so we remove it.
A is already in sync and so
we remove it and now we're done.
We have our order.
Now what's the run time of this outcome?
We need to compute one path for
each vertex in the grid and
so all of the many paths.
And each path could be pretty long,
it include up to all
the vertices in the graph.
It could take all of v time.
So the final run time of this algorithm
is O of V squared which is not great.
On the other hand we're doing
something a little bit inefficient
with this algorithm.
We started with this vertex,
we followed this huge long path
until we found the sync and
then we remove it from the graph.
Then what we probably did was we
started that same vertex again,
followed basically the same path
until we got almost to the very end,
until we get to right before
that vertex that we removed.
And we're sort of
repeating all of this work.
Why do we need to follow
this whole path again?
We could just back up one
step along the path and
then keep going from there, and
so that's what we're going to do.
Instead of retracing our entire path,
we're just going to back
up one step along our path.
So to see what this does in our example,
we go A, B, C, D.
D is a sink which we can remove, but
now instead of starting back at A,
we start at C which is already a sink.
And B which is already a sink now at
A we have to follow the path E to
could find the next sink and
then we're done.
And this algorithm reuses our steps a lot
less and so it's a lot more efficient.
In fact,
we think about with this algorithm does,
it's basically just adopt for search.
We're starting in a vertex where following
a path for until we can't anymore.
And then finally, once we're stuck,
we turn around and
we sort of, stop using that vertex again.
Then from that one step previous
we just keep going forward again.
This is exactly the depth for
search ordering.
And in particular when ever we finish
the post visit block at a vertex,
we put it at the end of our ordering.
So the order in which we're sorting our
vertices is just based on the post order.
In particular, vertices with small post
order go at the end of our ordering, and
ones with large post order
go at the beginning.
So the algorithm is now super easy.
We run depth for search on the graph and
then we sort the vertices based
on the reverse post order.
And note, we really don't actually
have to do any sorting here.
We just have to like, remember the order
in which we left our vertices.
So that's our algorithm,
let's take a look at the correctness.
So basically what we're saying
is that if we got g as a DAG.
Then we want to say, we can order
them by the reverse post order.
Now for this to be consistent
with our graph ordering,
it needs to be the case that whenever
we have an edge from u to v,
u comes before v which means that the post
of u is bigger than the post of v.
Let's prove this.
There are three cases to consider.
First, that we could explore
u before we explore.
Next, we could explore v
while were exploring u.
And finally, we could explore
v after were done exploring.
Of course, this last case can't happens
is there is edge u to v which means that
if we haven't already visited v we will
visit as part of our exploration view.
But okay the first two case is
still possible let's take a look.
Firstly, if we explore
v before we explore u,
well it turns out that we can't reach u
from v, and this is because we have a DAG.
If there was a path from v to u, and
then we add an edge to u back to v.
That would give us a cycle
which we can't take.
So it must be the case therefore, that we
can't discover u as part of exploring v.
We have to finish exploring v before
we can even start exploring u, and
that tells the post of u is
bigger than the post of v,
which is what we wanted
to show in this case.
Now in the second case the analysis
is a little bit different.
If we explore v while exploring u
remember that this means that our explore
of v is a subroutine of exploring u, and
therefore it needs to finish up first.
And that again, tells us that the post
of u is bigger than the post of v.
So that completes the proof of our
theorem and shows that this algorithm for
topological sort actually works.
So we've got now this nice algorithm for
the sorting.
Next time, we are going to talk about
something a little bit different,
we're going to talk about
connectivity in digraphs.
So I'll see you then.