Hi, in the previous lesson you learned
to find shortest paths in the graph
with non-negative edge weight.
In this lesson,
you will learn to find shortest paths
even in the graphs where some of
the edge weights can be negative.
We will explore that using
a problem about currency exchange,
which doesn't seem to have anything
to do with shortest paths.
But we will soon find out it does.
So the problem about
currency exchange is that
you are given some possibilities that
you can convert currency into another.
For example, US dollars to Russian rubles,
or rubles to Euros, or
Euros to Norwegian crowns.
And what you want to do is
take your initial $1,000 and
convert it into Russian rubles.
Potentially doing many
conversions on the way,
such that you get as many Russian
rubles as you can in the end.
So one question is what is the maximum
amount of rubles you can get?
And another question is actually
can you get as many as you want?
And the same question about US dollars.
Can you get as many US
dollars as you want?
It may seem that if you can get
as many rubles as you want,
then you will also be able to
get as many dollars as you want.
But that's not always the case,
it depends on your restrictions.
For example, if you lived in the USSR,
you might be able to get some rubles for
dollars you got from your
foreign country trip.
But it's very unlikely you could
buy some dollars inside USSR.
So in this problem we assume that
you have some restrictions on which
directions you can convert currencies and
what are the rates.
So this is an illustration from Wikipedia
article called Triangular Arbitrage
which illustrates the fact that sometimes
it is possible to make three trades and
exchange first dollars to Euros,
then Euros to Great Britain pounds.
And then pounds to US dollars, so
that you generate some profit.
In this case, given $5 million,
you generate a profit of 25,000,
just by doing those three trades.
These triangular arbitrages
exist very rarely and
only due to some market inefficiencies.
But in theory, this is possible.
And this example has some
numbers on the edges.
For example, the rate of conversion
from dollars to Euros is 0.81.
And you get 1.19 Euros per British pound.
And you get 1.46 dollars
per British pound.
So given these conversion rates and
of course those should also count for
commissions and any other money
that you actually don't get.
So given those numbers, you determine
exactly how many dollars will you get from
5 million initial if you do all
the trades shown on the picture.
So we will be discussing this problem,
how much you can get of each currency and
if it's actually possible
to get more of the currency you
had initially doing some trades.
So how does this conversion work?
If we have some path, if we convert first
from dollars to Euros then Euros to
pounds then some other conversions,
then we come to Norwegian crowns and
then we finally convert them to rubles.
Then how many rubles do
we get per 1 US dollar?
Well, it is determined by the product of
the conversion rates written on the edges.
So for example, if for $1,
we get 0.88 Euros and for
1 Euro we get 0.84 pounds,
and so one, and for
1 Norwegian crowns we get 8.08 rubles.
Then for 1 US dollar we will get the
product of all those numbers in rubles.
That's how conversion rates work,
if you account, again, for
commissions and
other payments in each trade
inside this number,
which right on the edge.
So what are the possibilities for
exchanges?
It may look that there is only one way.
You can just convert from
dollars to rubles, or
maybe use some intermediate currency.
But actually, there is an infinite
number of possibilities.
For example, in this particular case,
you could exchange dollars to Euros,
Euros to pounds, pounds to dollars,
and go through this cycle for
as many times as you want,
then convert to rubles.
Or convert to Euros and then to rubles.
So there are many, many possibilities, and
the result of each such
path through the graph
is the product of the numbers
written on the edges of this graph.
So the problem formulated
in mathematical terms,
is that if you're given a currency
exchange graph with weighted directed
edges denoted by ei,
between some pairs of currencies.
Maybe you can convert some
pairs of currencies but
you are not able to convert some others.
And this graph doesn't have to
be symmetrical or undirected.
So it is possible that you can convert
dollars to rubles but not vice versa.
And each edge has a conversion
rate corresponding to this pair
of currencies and it written as
a weight of this edge r with index ei.
And what you want to do
is maximize the product
of the weight of the edges
over all positive paths.
And a potentially infinite number of
paths, from the node corresponding to
US dollars to the node corresponding
Russian rubles in this graph.
Okay, and we could substitute these
two currencies by any other pair,
it doesn't matter.