So now, I want to reduce this problem to
the problem about shortest paths, and
we will do that using
two standard approaches.
First, we don't know what to do with
this product, so instead of products of
weights we want sums of weights,
like in the shortest paths problems.
And we will replace products with sums
by taking logarithms of weights, and
I will show that in a minute.
And another problem is that we need to
maximize something in this problem,
while shortest paths
are all about minimizing.
So we'll have to also negate
weights to solve minimization
problem instead of maximization.
First let's talk about taking
the logarithm is a known rule that x
is the same as two to the power
of logarithm of x over two.
So, we can take any product of two number,
like x and y and
rewrite x is two the logarithm of x and
y as 2 to the power of logarithm of y.
And then, x y is equal to 2 to the power
of logarithm of x by 2 of the power of
logarithm as y, and now we know
the rule of summing the powers.
So this is equal to 2 to the power of
logarithm of x plus logarithm of y
So if we want to maximize
product effects on Y.
This is actually the same of maximizing
the sum of logarithm of X and logarithm of
Y because if he sum becomes bigger then 2
to the power of the sum becomes bigger.
And if the sum becomes smaller, then 2 to
the power of sum also becomes smaller.
This is true not only for 2 numbers.
For example,
if we have 3 specific numbers.
4, 1, and 1 or 2 which one to multiply.
On one hand,
we get 2 which is 2 to the power of 1.
On another hand,
if we sum up the logarithm Terms of 4,
1, and one-half,
we get sum of 2, 0, and -1.
And the logarithms can be
both positive and negative.
They're positive when the number is
bigger than 1 and they're negative
when the number is smaller than 1, and
they're 0 when the number is equal to 1.
So in this case, we get the sum of 1,
which is the same as the power to which
we Exponentiate our 2.
So you see that it works not only for
2 numbers, but also for several numbers.
And in general, to maximize
the product of k numbers, r would EJ.
It is the same as to maximize
the corresponding the sum of
logarithms of these numbers.
And now that this only works if all these
numbers are positive, because we cannot
take logarithms of negative values and
we also cannot take logarithms of 0.
But if all the exchange rates
are positive numbers, hopefully then we
just take logarithms and
we reduce our problem of maximizing
product of some numbers to
maximizing sum of some numbers.
Now, we want to go from maximization
to minimization but that is easy.
If you want to maximize
the sum of logarithms,
it is the same as minimize minus the sum.
And we will also want to work just
with the sum, not with the minus sum,
so we can insert this minus
inside the sum incorporated.
And so finally, we get that maximizing
the sum of logarithms is the same as
minimizing the sum of minus logarithms.
Trading those two ideas,
we've got the following reduction.
We replace the initial edge weights,
conversion weights,
rei by minus algorithm of rei.
And we find the shortest path between
the nodes corresponding to USD and
the nodes corresponding
to RUR in the graph.
And this is equivalent to
the initial problem of how
many rubbles you can get from $1000.
So now,
it looks like we've solved the problem
because we can create the currency
exchange graph with the conversion rates,
we can replace those
rates with logarithms.
And we can find the shortest path from
USD to RUR using Dijkstra's Algorithm,
which were learned in the previous lesson.
And then, we can just do the exchanges
corresponding to the shortest path in
the graph which you found.
However, that doesn't exactly work.
Because Dijkstra's algorithm heavily
relies on the fact that the shortest path
from s to t goes only through
vertices that are closer to s than t.
And this is because the edge
weights are positive, but if
edge weights can be negative, this is no
longer the case and the example is below.
If we used Dijkstra's algorithm
as soon as it saw only two
edges from s to A and to B.
One of them with weight five,
and another with weight ten.
It would decide that the shortest
path to S to A is exactly five,
because we cannot improve it.
In this example, we can improve it.
We go from S to B, then from B to A, and
the path will be, already, minus ten,
which is much less than five.
So Dijkstra's algorithm
doesn't work in such cases.
Such an example is also possible
in the currency exchange problem.
Here is a graph with realistic conversion
rates between ruble, euros and U.S.
dollars.
And our goal is to convert rubles into
US dollars in the most profitable way.
And it turns out that if we take minus
logarithms of these conversion rates,
then although the number
on the edge from Rubles to
US Dollars is less than
the number from Rubles to Euros.
It is still beneficial to go
through Euros to US Dollars
because of the negative edge
between euros and US dollars.
And it's true that if you multiply
the conversation rate between rubles and
euros, and then between euros and dollars.
It will be slightly bigger than if we
convert directly from rubles to dollars.
So, all problems in the graphs with
negative weights come from
negative weight cycles.
For example, in this graph,
we have a negative cycle abc.
What it means is that we can go from a to
b than from B to C, than from C to A.
And if we add those weights we get -1.
So the sum of the edges
on the cycle is negative.
And because of that, if you want to
convert for example from S to A,
if you want to go from S to A and find
the shortest path, this is not possible.
Because we can go from S to A,
use distance of 4 But then we can just go
around the cycle A B C, A B C, A B C many,
many times, as many as we want.
And the distance will only decrease.
So the distance from S to node A is
actually minus infinity, is not defined.
You can do as short a path as you want.
And the same is true about nodes B and
C of course because they are on the cycle.
So you can do the same thing with them.
And the same is also true about node D
because it is reachable from the cycle.
So we can go to the cycle and
make a lot of round trips on the cycle and
then go to node D from either from B or
from C.
So all these nodes.
Are the infinitely close to S,
like the shortest path is minus infinity.
And it turns out that in the currency
exchange problem a cycle can potentially
make you a billionaire, if you are lucky
and if you have enough time for that.
But you'll learn how to do that
a little bit later in this lesson.