Hi!
In this video, you will finally learn how
to detect whether infinite arbitrage from
some source currency to some target
currency is currently possible.
And not only that,
you will also learn how to actually
implement it if it is possible.
But first, let's learn a criterion for
the existence of infinite arbitrage.
The lemma states that if we
consider some source currency S,
which we want to exchange into
some target currency u, and
get as much as we want of currency
u from a unit of currency S.
And it is possible if and only if
the node u corresponding to the currency
u in the currency graph is
reachable from some node w,
which was relaxed on
iteration number big V.
Where big V is the number of
nodes in the currency graph or
just the number of different
currencies which we consider.
So we run the Bellman-Ford Algorithm for
exactly big V iterations and
if some node w was relaxed
on the last iteration, and
some node u is reachable from it,
then it is possible to get
as much as you want of u from
the source currency S, and vice versa.
If it is possible to get as
much as you want of currency u,
then it must be reachable
from some node w,
which is going to be relaxed on the last
iteration on the Bellman-Ford's algorithm.
So let's prove this lemma.
First, we'll prove that if some
currency u is reachable from w,
which was relaxed on iteration number V,
then the infinite arbitrage is possible.
To see that, first note that,
as w was relaxed on iteration number V,
then we know from the previous
video that w is reachable from
some negative weight cycle, which in
turn is reachable from the node S.
It corresponds to
the picture on the slide.
And so we can get as much as we
want of currency w from currency S.
Because we can go from S,
to the node x of the negative cycle,
which is reachable from S,
then go as many times as we want,
through the negative cycle,
return to the node x, and
then go from this node x, to node w.
And using this way, we will get
as much as we want of currency w,
and then we know that
u is reachable from w.
We know that w is reachable
from the negative cycle.
The negative cycle is reachable from S.
So we can use this hallway
from S to negative cycle,
then go through the negative
cycle as many times as we want.
Then go to w from there,
then go from there to u and this way we
will get as much as we want of currency u.
So infinite arbitrage
is actually possible.
Now let's prove the other way around.
That if we can get as much as we
want of currency u from currency S,
then u must be reachable from some node w,
which is going to be relaxed on the last
iteration of the Bellman-Ford Algorithm.
So first, let L be the length
of the shortest path from
S to u with at most V- 1 edges.
Then we know that after V-1 iterations
of the Bellman-Ford's algorithm,
dist[u] is equal to exactly L.
And we know that exists infinite
arbitrage from S to u and so
there exists some path shorter than L,
strictly shorter, because we can get
a path for
any length which is arbitrarily small.
And so in particular there it is,
the path which is shorter than L.
And so the dist[u] will be
decreased at some point.
It will become less than L also.
But we know that by the iteration
number V- 1, it is still equal to L.
It is not less than L.
So it will be still decreased even more
on some iteration after iteration V- 1.
So it will be decreased either
on iteration number V or
on some of the further iterations.
Now let's note that if at some point,
some edge from node x to node
y was not relaxed, and also node x
was not relaxed itself, then edge (x,
y) will not be relaxed on the next
iteration because nothing has changed.
The dist[x] is the same.
And dist[y] is not bigger than
dist[x] plus length of edge (x,
y) and this didn't change from this
iteration to the next iteration.
So this edge won't be relaxed
on the next iteration.
And this means that if node y
was relaxed at some iteration,
then there is some node x from which
there is an edge to this node.
And this node x was relaxed
at some previous iteration.
So basically,
only those nodes which are reachable from
nodes relaxed on previous iterations can
be relaxed at the current iteration.
And so we know that the node u will be
relaxed at some iteration starting
from iteration V and further, and
this means that u is reachable from
some other node or maybe the same node.
But from node which was
relaxed on iteration number V,
note that u can be this node.
For example, u can be relaxed
exactly at iteration number V.
And as we consider node to
be reachable from itself,
then this is a particular case, in which
u was relaxed on iteration number V,
and u is reachable from itself so, it is
possible to get infinite arbitrage to u.
But in any case, we'll prove
that if infinite arbitrage from
S to u is possible, then u is
reachable from at least some node,
maybe the same u which was
relaxed on iteration number V.
So now we have a criterion for
existence of infinite arbitrage.
How to apply that criteria.
So this is an algorithm to
detect infinite arbitrage.
So we first do exactly V iterations
of Bellman-Ford algorithm, and
we save all the nodes which were relaxed
on the last iteration, iteration number V.
And let this set of nodes be denoted by A.
Now we'll put all the nodes
from A into the queue, and
we'll use this queue for
a breadth-first search.
So we'll start our breadth-first search
not from a queue which contains just
the first node, from which we want
to know all the reachable from it.
But we will put all
the nodes which were relaxed
on iteration number V into the queue,
and then start breadth-first search.
And then this breadth-first search will
find us all the nodes which are reachable
from at least one of
the nodes from the set A.
So those will be exactly those nodes for
which infinite arbitrage is possible.
So, all those nodes and
only those can have infinite arbitrage.
And this is a way to find
all target currencies for
which infinite arbitrage from a fixed
source currency S is possible.
But this is not enough.
What we want is to actually if
infinite arbitrage is possible,
is how to actually implement it.
And here is the next algorithm.
So let's suppose we already detected
that the infinite arbitrage
to some target currency u is possible, and
we determined that using
breadth-first search from the set A.
So we need to augment this
breadth-first search and we will
remember the parent of each visited node,
so that when a breadth-first search
discovers a new node, it discovers it from
some node which was discovered previously.
This is the parent of this node.
And this is what allows us to reconstruct
the path from the source node to the end
node in the regular
breadth-first search algorithm.
So we will do the same thing, and
this will allow us to reconstruct the path
to the target currency u from some node w,
which was relaxed on iteration number V.
Then we'll use the algorithm
from the previous video to find
the negative cycle from
which w is reachable.
Because we know that w was relaxed
on iteration number V, and so
it is reachable from some negative cycle,
which is in turn reachable from S.
And if we go back by the parent pointers
from w, we will find this negative cycle.
So we'll find both this negative cycle and
the path from it to w.
And of course we can also find a path
from the source currency to this
negative cycle by, for example,
launching a regular breadth-first
search from S until we encounter
some node of that negative cycle.
And then combining all that, we will have
a path from S to the negative cycle,
through which we can then go by
as many iterations as we want.
Then we'll go by a path from
this negative cycle to w.
And then we'll go by a path from w to u,
which you already know.
And that gives us a way
implement infinite arbitrage
from the source currency S
to the target currency u.
So in conclusion, we can now implement
the best possible exchange rate,
in the case it exists and
there is no infinite arbitrage.
And we can determine whether actually
infinite arbitrage is possible currently.
And we can actually implement infinite
arbitrage from a given source currency
to given target currencies.
And in a more general and
abstract way we can find shortest paths,
not only in the graphs where
all the edges are positive,
like graphs of navigation systems with
positive times to go through an edge and
length of the edge, but also in the graphs
where negative edge weights are possible,
such as the graphs of currency exchange.
So we can basically find
shortest paths correctly
in any graphs with weighted edges.
That's what we've learned in this lesson.