Okay, when merging two trees we're going
to hang the shorter one under the root
of a taller one.
This means that when
merging two trees we need
a way to quickly find
the height of both trees.
Instead of just computing them we're
going to keep the height of each
possible subtree in our forest
in a separate array called rank.
Name the rank of i is equal to
the height of the subtree rooted at i.
The reason we call it rank will
become clear a little bit later.
Let me also mention that this
way of merging two trees,
based on the height is called
the union by rank heuristic.
To keep the rank, we need a small
addition to our MakeSet implementation,
namely when creating a single set,
we also set rank of i to be equal to zero.
This reflects the fact that it is
currently just a root containing one node,
that just a tree containing one node,
that is a tree of height zero.
We do not need to change Find.
So the Find operation doesn't
need to change rank, and
it also doesn't use rank in any way.
To merge two trees containing the given
two elements i and j, we do the following.
We first find the roots of the point
in two trees by calling the Find
operation two times.
We store this root in variables i_id and
j_id.
We then check whether
i_id is equal to j_id.
If they are equal,
this means that elements i and
j already lie in the same set.
So we just return in this case.
So this is done in the following if loop.
We then check whether the height
of the tree containing element i
is larger than the height of
the tree containing element j.
If it is larger,
then we hang the tree with the root j_id,
and this root of element i_id.
This is done as follows.
Parent of j_id is set to i_id.
Otherwise, we do the opposite thing.
We just assigned parent of
i_id to be equal to j_id.
So the last thing is that
we need to check whether
the height of the corresponding
two threes are just equal.
Let me illustrate this
again with a small example.
Assume that we are merging
the following two trees.
In this case the height
of these two elements and
this element is zero and
this height of this element is 1.
So in this case roots are equal.
The ranks of the corresponding
roots are equal.
To merge these two trees
we do the following.
We just hang the left tree under
the root of the right tree.
If you can see, in this case,
the height of the resulting tree actually
increases and this is the only case
when the union operation
increases the height of this tree.
So in this case, initially,
the longest path contained just one edge.
In this case we go the path
that can contain two edges.
So we need to update this rank and
this is done in the last check.
So if initially the ranks of our two
trees that are going to be merged
are equal we hang one of them under
the root of the other one and
increase the rank of
the resulting tree by one.
Let's consider a small example,
in this case we have six elements.
Let's call MakeSet for
each of these elements.
These fields have a data
structure as follows.
So currently,
each element is its own parent, right?
So its current set is
just a single one set.
Also, the height of each sub-tree in our
data structure is currently equal to 0.
Now let's call Union(2,4).
In this case, the rank of the subtree
rooted at 2 is equal to 0.
The height of the subtree
rooted at 4 is equal to 0.
So it doesn't mean which one to hang
under the root of the other one, so
let's hang 2 under 4.
This changes the data
structure as follows.
Now it's a parent of 2 is 4 and
the rank of the subtree
rooted at 4 is equal to 1.
Okay, now let's call Union(5,2).
In this case the height of
the tree that contains the element
number 2 is equal to 1, right?
While the height of the tree that
contains element number 5 is equal to 0.
So, in this case we're
going to hang 5 under 4.
We do this as follows.
So, this change the data structure,
only this changes only this cell.
So now 4 is the parent of 5, and
it doesn't change any rank in
our sub tree, in our forest.
Okay, now lets call Union(3,1).
This is done as follows,
now 1 is rank 1, and
now the parent of 3 is equal to 1, okay?
Now, let's call Union(2,3),
and again, in this case, 2
lies in a set in the tree whose root is 4.
And currently,
the rank of 4 is equal to 1.
Also, 3 lies in a set whose root is 1.
And currently, rank of 1 is equal to 1.
Which means that after merging these two
trees we will get a tree of height 2.
So we do this as follows, now 1 is
the root of the resulting tree and
its rank is equal to 2.
Finally we call Union(2,6) and
this will just attach 6 to 1, as follows.
In our current implementation, we maintain
the following important invariant.
At any point of time and for
any node i, rank of i is equal
to the height of the subtree
rooted at this node, i, right?
We will use this invariant to
prove the following lemma.
The height of any tree in our forest
is at most binary logarithm of n.
This will immediately imply that
the running time of all operations
with our data structure is
at most logarithmic, right?
To prove this lemma we will prove
another lemma shown here on this slide.
We're going to prove that if we have
a tree in our forest whose height
is k then this tree contains
at least two to the k nodes.
This will imply the first
lemma as follows.
I assume that some tree
has height with more,
strictly greater than
binany logarithm of n.
Using the second lemma it
will be possible to show then
that this tree contains more than n nodes,
right?
Which would lead to a contradiction
with the fact that we
only have n objects in our data structure.
Here we are going to prove
the second lemma by induction on k.
Recall that we proved
that any tree of height k
in our forest contains at
least 2 to the k nodes.
We're going to prove
this by induction on k.
When k is equal to zero this means
that we have a tree just of height 0,
which means that it
contains just one node.
So, in this case,
the statement clearly holds.
Now, to prove the induction step, let's
recall that the only way to get a height,
to get a tree of height k, is to merge
two trees, whose height is equal to k- 1.
I mean to merge both trees such that
the height of the first tree is equal
to k- 1 and the height of
the second tree is equal to k-1.
By the induction hypothesis
the both of these two trees
contain at least 2 to the k-1 node.
Which means that our
resulting tree contains
at least 2 to the k- 1
+ 2 to the k- 1 nodes,
which is exactly equal to 2 to the k,
right?
Which means that the lemma is proved.
To conclude,
the running time of both Union and
Find operations in our current
implementation is at most logarithmic.
Why is so?
Well, just because we keep
our trees shallow, so
that the height of any tree in our
forest is at most logarithmic.
This immediately implies the time of any
Find operation is also
big O of logarithm of n.
Recall also that the Union operation
consists of two calls to the Find
operation and
also a few constant time operations,
which means also that the running
time of Union is also big O of log n.
In the next video, we will see another
beautiful heuristic which will just
decrease the running time of both
these operations to nearly a constant.