To build our Y intuition involves
a second characteristic for
the disjoint at the destruction.
Let's again consider the example
shown here on the slide.
Assume that we call find of six.
This will traverse the following path
from six to the root of this tree.
So let's know that in this
case we find the root of three
that contains element six,
but we also find the root
of the tree that contains element 12 and
contains element three.
In general, by reversing this
path we find the root for
all the elements on this path.
So, why lose this information?
Let's just store it somehow.
And one way to do this, for example,
is to re-attach all these notes directly
to the root, we can do this as follows.
Now as you can see
the parent of element 12 for
example is five, and also the parent
of element six is also five.
We've just attached them
directly to the root.
And this can not only save
us space in the future.
Save us time, I'm sorry, in the future.
For future calls of find operation.
So this heuristic is
called path compression.
Implementing this heuristic I
mean path compression heuristic,
don't sound to be surprisingly simple.
It is actually only three lines of code.
Here we do the following.
We first check whether i
is equal to parent of i.
If it is equal, if it is the root,
then we will just return the result.
If i is not the root,
if i is not the root, we do the following.
We call find recursively for
the parent of the node i.
This is done here.
So we call find for
the parent of the node i.
It will return the root of
the correspondent three.
And then we set parent of i to
be equal to the returned root.
That is, we attach the node
number i directly to the root.
And we do this recursively for
all the elements on this pass.
Finally we return the new parent of i,
which is now just the root
of the corresponding tree.
Before stating an upper bound on the
running time of operations of our current
implementations, we need to introduce
the so-called iterated logarithm function,
which is also denoted by log star of n.
So by definition, iterated logarithm
of n is the number of times the binary
logarithm should be applied to n before
we get a number which is at most one.
Let me illustrate this with an example so
n equal to one is a binary
logarithm of n is equal to zero.
We do not need to apply binary logarithm
to get a number which is at most one,
because n is already
almost one in this case.
For n equal to two,
we need to apply binary logarithm once
to get the number which is at most one.
Mainly, if we apply binary algorithm
to two we just get the number one.
Okay for n equals to three and four,
the binary algorithm is equal to two and
so on.
And for example, for
the numbers shown here,
two to the sixth,
5536 If we apply binary logarithm once,
then just by definition of binary
logarithm we get this number,
just 65536, which is two to 16, okay?
So if we apply the binary logarithm once
again we get 16, 16 is two to the four.
If we apply the binary logarithm
once again we get four.
If we apply, again, we get two, and if we
apply it finally once again, we get one.
And at this point, we stop.
So we applied the binary logarithm
five times to get a number which is at
most one, which ensures that for
this number,
two to the 65536 the log
star is equal to five, okay?
So, and this shows that for
any practical value of n, the binary log,
the log star function is, at most, five.
Because this number is extremely huge.
We will never see any value of
m which is greater than this
number in practical value.
We will never get an input, a sequence
that consists of so many elements.
So theoretically speaking,
the lock star function is not bound.
It is not constant.
So there are extremely huge numbers for
which lock star is equal to ten or
twenty or 100 and so on.
However, for all practical values of n,
log star of n is at most five.
We're now ready to state an upper bound.
Assume that we used both union by rank
heuristic and past compression heuristic,
and assume that we make m
operations with our data structure,
of which m are calls to the MakeSet
does a MakeSet operation.
Namely, we have n object, and
we make m operations with them.
Then the total running time of
all these calls is O(mlog*n).
Put it otherwise, the amortized running
time of a single operation is O(log*n).
And recalls it for all practical values
of n, log star of n is at most five.
Which means that we have
a constant average time for
a single operation for
all practical values of n.
So once again,
log star theoretically speaking,
log star function is not bound,
however it is at most five for
all practical values of n which makes our
data structure very efficient in practice.
We will prove this upper
bound in the next video.