Hello everybody.
Welcome back.
Today, we're going to be talking about
computing greatest common divisors.
So, in particular,
what we'd like to do this lecture,
is we're going to define
the greatest common divisor problem.
And, we're going to talk about
an inefficient way to compute them.
And, next lecture we'll talk
about how to do better.
So, okay.
What are GCDs?
So, suppose that you have a fraction,
a over b.
And, you want to put it in simplest form.
Now, the standard way of doing this,
is we want to divide the numerator and
denominator both by some d, to get
some equivalent fraction, a/d / b/d.
Fair enough.
Now, what d do we want to use for this?
Well, it needs to satisfy two properties.
Firstly, d had better divide both a and
b, since the new numerator and
denominator are both integers.
But, subject to that, we would like
this d to be as large as possible.
So, that we can reduce the fraction
as much as we possibly can.
So, turning this into a definition,
we say that for two integers, a and
b, their greatest common divisor, or GCD,
is the largest integer d
that divides both a and b.
Okay, so this is a thing that
you use to reduce fractions.
However, it turns out that GCDs
are a critically important
concept in the field of number theory.
The study of prime numbers, and
factorization, and things like that.
And, because it's so important to number
theory, it turns out that being able to
compute GCDs is actually very
important in cryptography.
And, the fact that you can perform
secure online banking is, in part,
due to the fact that we can efficiently
compute GCDs of numbers in order for
our cryptographic algorithms to work.
So, because of this importance, we're
going to want to be able to compute GCDs.
So, we'd like an algorithm that, given two
integers, a and b, at say, at least 0,
we can compute the GCD of a and b.
And, just to be clear as to what
kinds of inputs we care about,
we'd actually like to be able to
run this on very large numbers.
We don't just want something that works
for GCD of 5 and 12, or 11 and 73.
We'd like to be able to
do things like the GCD of
3,918,848 with 1,653,264.
In fact, we'd also like to be able
to compute much bigger numbers,
20, 50, 100, 1000 digits.
We'd still like to be able to get GCDs of
numbers of those sizes pretty quickly.
Well, let's get started.
Let's start by just finding
an algorithm that works.
What we'd like is the largest
number that divides both a and b.
So, one thing we can do,
is we can just check all of
the numbers that are candidates for
this, figure out which ones divide a and
b, and return the largest one.
So, there's an easy implementation for
this.
We create a variable called best,
and set it to 0.
This just remembers the biggest
thing we've seen so far.
We then let d run from 1 to a + b,
since this is the range of
numbers that are valid.
Now, if d divides a, and d divides b,
well, since d is increasing,
this has to be the new
best that we've seen.
So, we set best equal to d, and
then, at the end the of the day,
we return back the best thing we've seen.
So, that's a perfectly good algorithm.
It works.
Unfortunately, it's a little bit slow,
because we need to run through
this for loop a + b many times.
And, this means that, even once a and
b are, say, 20 digit numbers, it's already
going to be taking us at least thousands
of years in order to run this computation.
And, so that's not sufficient for the
sorts of applications that we care about.
We're going to need a better algorithm.
So, come back next lecture, and we'll talk
about how to find a better algorithm for
this problem, and what goes into that.