Hi, in this optional lesson we will learn
a bit about more than distributed systems.
And we will start with some interesting
inner working online storage services
which you probably use such as DropBox,
Google Drive and the Yandex Disk.
Have you wondered how
a very big file of tens or
hundreds of megabytes can be uploaded
almost instantly to your DropBox account?
Or maybe your interested,
how Dropbox, Google Drive and
Yandex Disk save petabytes
of storage space
using the ideas from this module
on hash tables and hash functions.
Or maybe you're interested
in distrusted systems and
distributed storage in general.
Then, this lecture is for you.
So services like Dropbox and
Google Drive used extra bytes of
storage to store data of millions and
millions of users worldwide.
And there's a very simple idea on how
to actually save some of that space and
save some of the cost so it sometimes
happens that users upload the same files.
The first user liked
the video with the cats and
uploaded it to his Dropbox account just
to save it and to show his friends.
And then another user also
loved this video file.
He may have called it different way but
still uploaded it to his Dropbox account,
the exactly same video.
And then another user also uploaded this
video, because this was a viral video and
many, many people liked it and
some of them decided to upload it
to their user accounts in Dropbox.
And then what we can do on the level
of the whole Dropbox service is instead
of storing all three copies of
the same video, just save one copy and
have links from the user's files to
this actual, physical, stored file.
And then we've just saved 66% of
the storage space because we
basically reduced three times.
And if you have some large videos
which are also very popular
that you can save this way significant
portion of this storage space
which all the users collectively use
in DropBox to store their files.
So the question is how to
actually implement that.
So, when you do a new file log,
you need to determine if there is already
the same file in the system or now, and
if there is, you just ignore the plot, and
sent a link to the register's file in the
user's account, instead of a real file.
So, there are a few ways to do that, and
we'll start with a really simple one.
Naive comparison.
You take the new file that
the user wants to upload.
You actually upload it
to a temporary storage,
then you go through all the storage files,
then you compare the new file with each
of the storage files, bye, bye, bye.
And if there is exactly the same file,
you store a link to this file instead of
the new file that user's wants to upload.
So, there are a few
drawbacks of this approach.
First, you have to first,
upload the file anyways.
So you won't see this miraculous
instant upload time of
large files with hundreds of megabytes.
And second is to compare a file
of size S with N other files,
it takes time proportional
to product of N and S.
And that can be huge because
the number of files in Dropbox or
Google Drive is probably on the order of
hundreds of billions or even trillions.
And the files uploaded are often
also very large like gigabytes.
And also, if we use the strategy,
then, as N grows, as service for
online storage grows,
the total running time of all uploads will
grow as N squared because each
new upload is big O(N) and
it's longer and longer and
longer as the number of files increases.
So, this approach won't
work long-term anyway.
So what can we do?
First idea is, instead of comparing the
files themselves, try to compare hashes.
As in the Rabin Karp's algorithm,
compare hashes of the files first.
If the hashes are different,
then the files are definitely different.
And if there is a file with the same hash,
then upload this new file that the user
wants to upload to his account, and
compare the new file with the old file
with the same hash directly byte by byte.
Still, there are problems
with this approach.
First, there can be collisions so
we cannot just say that if two files have
the same hash value then they're equal and
we don't need to store the new file.
Sometimes, different files can
have the same hash value and
we'll still have to compare the two files,
and also we still have to upload
the file to compare directly even
if the same file's already stored.
And we still have to compare
with all N already stored files.
So what can we do?
Another idea is we can use
several hash functions.
If we have two equal files, even if we
compute five different hash functions
there values on these two
files will be the same.
So the idea is choose several different
hash functions independently for example,
take functions from polynomial family
with different multiplier x or
with different prime numbers p.
And then compute all the hashes for
each file and
if there is a file which is already
stored and has all the same hash values,
then the new file is probably
the same as the file already stored.
In this case, we might want to not
even upload the new file at all and
save the time and
make the upload seem immediate.
And to do that we need to just compute
hashes locally before upload and only
send through the network, which can be
slow, the variants of the hash functions,
which are much, much less in terms
of space than the initial huge file.
So we can do the hash values locally.
We send those three or five hash values
over the network to the service.
They're compared to the hash values
of the files already stored.
And if there is a file with same set of
hash values, we don't upload our new file.
And this is how the instant
upload works sometimes.
When you try to upload file which is
already stored but by someone else.
Well of course,
there is a problem with collisions.
Because collisions can happen even if you
have several different hash functions.
Still, there can be two
different files which have
the same set of hash values even for
several hash functions.
And there are even algorithms
which on purpose find
two different files which have the same
value of a give hash function.
If you know for which hash function
you are trying to find a collision.
However, for
hash functions used in practice,
collisions are extremely rare and
hard to find.
And if you use more than one hash
function, if you use three or
even five then you probably won't
see a collision in a life time.
So this is actually done in practice.
You compute several different hash
functions which no body knows and
then it is so hard to find two files for
which all the hash functions
have the same values.
That a new file is considered to
be equal to the old stored file
if all the hash values coincide with the
hash values of the file already stored.
So we still have an unsolved
problem that we need to do and
comparisons with all
the already stored files.
So how can we solve this problem?
Well, we can first precompute hashes
because when a file is submitted for
upload, hash values for
this file are computed anyway.
So we can store the addresses of the files
which already stored in
the service in a hash table and
along with the addresses of the files will
store those hash values for each file.
So, we recompute them and store them and
when we need to search for
a new file We actually only need
to search in the hash table, and
we need only the values of the hash
functions on this file to search for it.
We don't need to provide the file itself.
So we search for
the hash values in the hash table.
And if we find some files stored in
this hash table with the same set
of hash values, then we know that there is
already such files stored in the system.
So the final solution is the following.
We choose from three to five
different good hash functions, for
which it is hard to find solutions.
So that we don't see
collisions in practice.
We store the addresses of the files and
the hashes of those files in a hash table,
and before we upload a new file,
we compute the hashes locally,
we send them over
the network to the service.
We check whether there is a file in
a hash table with the same hash values.
And if all the hashes for
some stored file coincide with
the hashes of the new file
then the search is successful.
And in this case we don't
even upload the file,
we just store a link in the user account
to the existing, already stored file.
So this how we can do instant upload
to Dropbox or Google Drive for
[INAUDIBLE] this, and this is actually
how they save a lot of space,
probably petabytes of
space in their services.
However, there are more problems to this,
because it turns
out that billions of files are uploaded
daily, for example, into Dropbox.
And that means that probably around
trillions are already stored there.
And that is just too big for
a simple hash table on one computer.
And also, millions of users upload
simultaneously their files, and so
this is also too many requests for
a single hash table.
And so you need some
more sophisticated solution to
cope with this those two things.
And see our next lecture to understand
how that problem is solved.