Hi.
In this video we will learn how
to store a whole lot of objects,
how to store big data,
using distributed hash tables.
So big data is when you need to
store trillions or more objects.
For example, trillions of file
addresses in Dropbox, or user profiles,
or emails and user accounts, for
example, in Gmail or services like that.
And you need fast search and
fast access to that data.
So hash tables, in general,
is a good solution for
that problem because they give a constant
time search access on average.
But for number of keys in the order
of ten to the power of 12,
the amount of memory that a single
hash table will store becomes too
big to store it in one computer and
so we need to do something else,
we need to use more computers probably.
And the solution to this
is distributed hash tables.
So the first idea for
distributed hash table is the following,
just get more computers.
Get 1,000 computers.
If you are Google or
Dropbox you can do that.
And then you will store your
data on many computers.
And you will do the following.
You create a hash table on
each of those computers.
And then you will separate
the data between those computers.
So each computer will store
its own part of the data.
And you need to determine quickly,
and automatically, and
deterministically which computer
should store some object O.
And there is a simple way, just compute
some hash function of this object,
modular 1000, so we get basically a value
from 0 to 999 for each object and
that will be the number of the computer
which should store this object.
And then you send a request to
that computer and search or modify
what you need to do with that object in
the local hash table of that computer.
And that seems to already solve
our problem because if a new
request comes you quickly compute
the hash function on the object and
you know where to send your request.
And then that computer just looks
up in its local hash table.
Each of the local hash tables
can be 1,000 times less
than the total amount of data stored,
and so it is scalable.
If you need more data, you just get
more computers and everything works.
Still there are problems
with this approach.
and the main problem is that
computers sometimes break.
And especially if you have a lot of
computers, then they break pretty often.
For example if a computer breaks once in
two years on average, then if you have
1,000 computers, on average,
more than one computer breaks every day.
Because there are less than 1,000 days in
two years, and you have 1,000 computers.
So what do you do in that case?
You don't want to lose your user's data.
So you need to store
several copies of the data.
So basically you can do it in a way that
every computer stores each part of data.
Each part of data should be
stored on several computers.
And what happens then when
some computer breaks?
Well, luckily the data which
is stored on this computer
is also stored somewhere else.
But if that's the only copy left after
this computer broke, you also need to also
copy that data to some other computer, so
that it is again stored in several places.
And you need to relocate the data
from the broken computer and
also sometimes your service grows and
you want to buy more computers.
You want to reply faster
to your clients and
new computers are added to the cluster.
And then this formula take hash
value of the object modular 1000.
And this is the number of computer
on which your object is stored.
It no longer works.
Because the numbers of
the computers always change.
New computers come in.
Broken computers come out.
And so you need something else.
And one way to solve this is
called consistent hashing.
So first, we choose some hash
function with sum cardinality m.
And we choose a circle,
a regular circle, and
you put numbers from zero to m minus
one on the circle in a clockwise order.
And then each object, O, is mapped
to some point on the circle corresponding
to the number hash value of this object.
Which is from 0 to m- 1, so it always maps
to some of the numbers on the circle.
And also, each computer ID is
mapped to the same circle.
We hash the ID of the computer and
we get the number of the points
to which this computer is mapped.
So let's look at the picture.
Here's our circle.
And, for example m is 12.
Then we put 12 points around the circle.
And we put numbers from 0
to 11 around the circle.
And then, objects, such as for example,
name Steve,
can be mapped to some of those 12 points.
And if hash value of Steve is 9,
then Steve is mapped to
the point with number 9.
And also computers can be mapped
to points, and for example,
this computer with ID 253.
If the hash value of 253 is 5, then
this computer is mapped to the point 5.
So what do we do then?
We make a rule that each object is stored
on the so-called closest computer,
closest in terms of
the distance along the circle.
And in this case,
each computer stores all objects
falling on some arc, which consists
of all objects which are closer to this
computer than to any other computer.
Let's again look at the picture.
This is the circle and
there are six computers and
these computers mapped to
some points on this circle.
And then the arcs of the same
color as the computers near them,
are the sets of points,
which are closer to the corresponding
computer than to any other computer.
And so each computer is responsible for
some arc of this circle.
For all the keys that
are mapped to this arc.
And so what happens when computers come
in because new computers are bought or
when computers are broken.
When a computer goes off when it is
broken, it's neighbors take its data.
So it has two neighbors, and it's arc
is divided into parts, and one part
goes to the right neighbor and the,
another part goes to the left neighbor.
And when a new computer is added
it takes data from its neighbors.
So it comes between some two
already existing computers, and
it takes a part of the arc of one of them,
and a part of the arc of another one,
and he gets its arc.
So let's look at an example.
For example, the yellow computer
breaks and it goes away.
And then the green and
the blue computer will take its arc and
divide it between themselves.
So that's what happens.
Another problem which still needs to be
solved is that when some computer breaks,
we need to copy or relocate the data.
And how will a node, a computer, know
where to send the data that is stored?
Well, we need another rule for that.
We cannot store the addresses
of all the other computers
on each of the computers
because that is inconvenient.
We will have to constantly
update that information.
But, each node, each computer will be so
called acquainted with a few neighbors.
So it will store the metric
addresses of some of its neighbors.
The rule is that for any key,
each node will either store this key
itself, or it will be acquainted.
It will know some other computer
which is closer to this
key in terms of
the distance on the circle.
And, that way, if a request comes to
some node, any node in the network,
about some key, it either can find
this key inside it's own storage, or,
it will redirect the request to another
node which is closer to this key.
And that that node will
either store the key, or
direct the code to the next node,
which is even closer to that key.
And in finite number of iterations the
request will come to the node that will
actually stores the key.
So that's the idea.
And in practice, what we can do
is we can put the computers,
the nodes on the circle.
And then each node will know its immediate
neighbors, its neighbors of neighbors.
And then its neighbors in distance of 4
and distance of 8, and distance of 16.
And for all powers of 2 it will
know neighbors to the right and
to the left at distance of this part 2.
Of course less than n over half.
And it's easier to see
on the picture again.
So suppose we have many, many nodes.
And then the upper node will have
links to its right and left neighbor.
To its right and
left neighbor on distance of two, and
to its right and left neighbor,
the distance of four, and so on.
So each node will contain algorithmic
number of links to other nodes,
which is much better than
storing all the other nodes.
And, if we need to come to some key
from some node that doesn't contain it
we'll first jump in the direction where
the distance to the key decreases.
And we will jump as much as we can.
If the computer at distance eight is
closer than our computer to the key,
we will jump at least by eight.
If computer with distance 16 is closer,
we'll jump at least 16.
If computer with distance 32 is farther,
then we'll jump just by 16.
In this way,
we will always jump by at least a half
of the distance which divides us from
computer that stores the key itself.
And so in algorithmic number of steps,
we will actually come from
the current computer, to the computer
that actually stores our key.
And this network of nodes
which know some neighbors and
they know some of their neighbors
is called, Overlay Network.
So in conclusion,
Distributed Hash Tables is a way to store
Big Data on many many computers and access
it fast, as if it was on one computer.
Consistent Hashing is one way to determine
which computer actually owns the data,
which computer stores
this particular object.
And to do that, consistent
hashing uses mapping of keys and
computer IDs on a circle.
And each computer stores
a range of keys on an arc,
which is closest to this computer in
terms of distance along the circle.
And also overlay network is used to route
the data to and from the right computer.
So when a computer is broken,
first, its data needs to be
copied to some other computer.
And its neighbors take its data.
So computer disappears, and
its arc disappears, but
this is actually divided
between two neighbor computers.
And each of those arcs increases a bit,
and
they cover the whole data and
then we proceed.
If a new computer appears, it takes
some data from its right neighbor,
some data from its left neighbor,
and assembles an arc for itself.
And I hope that after this lecture,
you understand how important are data
structures we study in this course,
to the modern technological industry,
distributed systems, and big data.