Before recording this lecture,
I stopped by the coffee shop.
This cappuccino is good.
And as soon as I gave $5 to the cashier,
she faced
an algorithmic problem of which coins
to select to give me the change.
And cashiers all over the world
use an algorithmic approach
called greedy algorithm
to solve this problem.
Today we will learn how cashiers and
computer scientists
use greedy algorithm for
solving many practical problems.
So the change problem is finding
the minimum number of coins
needed to make change.
More formally, input to the problem
is integer money and positive integers,
coin1, coin2, coind,
that represents coin denominations.
For example in the US,
coin1 will be 1 cents,
coin2 will be 5 cents, 10 cents,
25 cents, and 50 cents.
And the output is the minimum number of coins,
with denominations coin1,
coin2, coind that changes money exactly.
So today in the morning,
when cashier had to return me 40 cents,
she most likely used
the following algorithm.
First, finding the largest
coin denomination
that is smaller than 40 cents.
It will be 25 cents.
So she gave me 25, 15 cents left and
then the next challenge is
how to change 15 cents.
The next step is she probably found
the largest coin smaller than 15 cents,
it is 10 cents.
She gave me 10 cents, and
finally, she returned 5 cents.
As a result,
she changed 40 cents as 25 plus 10 plus 5.
Do you think it's the minimum number
of coins she could possibly return?
It is the minimal number of
coins in the United States.
But if you travel to Tanzania, it won't be
the minimum number of coins because
there is a 20 cent coin in Tanzania.
And therefore this greedy
approach to solving the change
problem will fail in Tanzania because
there is a better way to change 40 cents,
simply as 20 cents plus 20 cents,
using Tanzanian 20 cents coin.
Since the greedy approach to
solving the change problem failed,
let's try something different.
Let's try the recursive algorithm for
solving the same problem.
Suppose we want to change 9 cents, and
our denominations are 1 cent,
5 cents, and 6 cents.
What would be the optimal
way to change 9 cents?
Well, if we only knew what is the optimal
ways to change 9 minus 6 cents,
9 minus 5 cents and 9 minus 1 cents,
then we would know,
what is the optimal way to change 9 cents?
In other words, to change 9 cents,
we need to know how to change
small number of cents,
in our case, 3 cents,
4 cents, and 8 cents.
And therefore, an approach to
solving this problem would be
to use this recurrence to
write the recursive program.
This idea is implemented in
the program RecursiveChange.
To change money, cents using coins, coin1,
coin2, coind, we do the following.
We first recursively call RecursiveChange
with the amount of money,
money minus coin1, money minus coin2,
and money minus coind.
And find the minimum amount of money for
these d choices.
We have plus 1 because there is one
more coin to add and returns this way.
This looks like the right
approach to solve the problem,
but let's check how fast
the resulting program is.
So, when we're changing 76 coins,
there are actually three choices.
We need to recursively call
RecursiveChange for 70 cents,
71 cents, and 75 cents.
But for each of these values,
we need once again to call three choices.
And we will continue growing this tree and
very quickly it will turn
into a gigantic tree.
Let's check how many times we have
already tried to change 70 cents.
Three times, and
we only started expanding this tree.
In fact, if we continue further,
we will see that there were six
times when we needed to compute
RecursiveChange for 70.
How many times do you think we
will need to run recursive calls
when we compute the minimal
number of coins for 30 cents?
It turn out that we will need
to call it trillions of times,
which means that our
seemingly very elegant
RecursiveChange program will not finish
before the end of your lifetime.
So as simple as the change problem looks
like, neither a greedy approach nor
a recursive approach solve
it in a reasonable time.
60 years ago, a brilliant mathematician,
Richard Bellman, had a different idea.
Wouldn't it be nice to know all
the answers for changing money minus
coin i by the time we need to compute
an optimal way of changing money?
And instead of the time consuming
calls to RecursiveChange,
money minus coin i, that may require
to be repeated trillions of times,
they would simply look up these values.
This idea resulted in dynamic programming
approach that is applied in thousands
of diverse, practical applications
in a myriad of different fields.
And the key idea of dynamic programming
is to start filling this matrix,
not from the right to the left, as we
did before in the recursive change, but
instead, from the left to the right.
So, we will first ask
the trivial question,
what is the minimum number of
coins needed to change 0 cents?
And, of course, it is 0.
What is the minimum number
of coins to change 1 cents?
Obviously it is one, but
we can compute this number by finding what
is the minimum number of coins to
change 0 cents and adding one coin.
We will proceed in a similar fashion
to compute the minimum number of
coins to change 2 cents,
3 cents, and 4 cents.
There is only one possibility to derive
this number from the previous number.
And for 5 cents, actually there
are two possibilities, green and blue.
For green one, you can derive
it from 0 cents by adding 5 coins,
and for blue possibility, we can derive
it from 4 cents by adding one penny.
Well, which possibility would you select?
Of course the one that gives you
the minimum change for 5 coins.
And continue further and apply the code to
6 cents and there are three possibilities and once
again we select the optimal choice that
correspond to minimum number of coins.
Let's say it may be 0 coins plus 6 cents.
We continue for 7 cents,
continue for 8 cents, and finally,
very quickly, we actually found
the correct answer for 9 cents.
We need four coins to change 9 cents.
And this results in DPChange
algorithm that simply fills
up the table that I just
showed you from left to right.
DP change is the first dynamic programming algorithm
that you saw in this course,
and there will be thousands more.
You may be wondering why is this algorithm
called dynamic programming and
what does it have to do with programming?
Well, in fact programming and
dynamic programming has nothing
to do with programming.
Amazingly enough,
dynamic programming is one of
the most practical algorithms
computer scientists use.
But when Richard Bellman was
developing this idea for
Air Force project he was working on,
it looked completely impractical.
And he wanted to hide that he's really
doing mathematics from the Secretary
of Defense,
rather than working on Air Force project.
Therefore he invented a name
that basically has nothing to do with what
dynamic programming algorithms do.
In his own word, he said,
what name could I choose?
I was interested in planning but planning
is not a good word for various reasons.
I decided therefore to use
the word programming, and
I wanted to get across the idea
that this was dynamic.
It was something not even
a Congressman could object.