Another scheme that we know from
the previous lesson is chaining.
To use that we first select the hash
function with some cardinality m,
then we create an array
name again of size m.
But instead of storing the names
themselves in the array,
we store chains or lists.
And in these lists, we'll store
both names and the phone numbers.
And to determine where to put name and
phone number, we first convert the phone
number to integer, then we'll apply hash
function to it and get a hash value.
And put both name and
phone number in the chain corresponding
to the cell with such index.
Here is how it looks like.
For example, we have a contact of Steve
and his phone number is 223-23-23.
We first convert it to the number
2 million and a few thousand, and
then we compute the hash value of this
integer number and it turns out to be 1.
Then we put both Steve's name and
his phone number in
the chain corresponding to the cell
number 1 in our array Name.
Then we do the same for
Natalie and her phone number.
And it turns out that the hash value of
the integer corresponding to her phone
number is 6, so
we put her contact in the 6th cell.
And then we do the same for Sasha, and
the hash value of his phone
number turns out again to be 1.
So Sasha gets in the same cell as Steve.
There are the following parameters
of the chaining scheme.
First, n is the total number of phone
numbers stored in our phone book.
m is the cardinality of
the selected hash function,
which is the same as the size of our
area name, which works as a hash table.
c is the length of the longest
chain in our hash table.
We use big O(n + m) memory
to store the phone book.
And also alpha, which is n/m,
the number of phone numbers stored
divided by the size of the hash table,
which measures how filled up is our
hash table, is called the load factor.
And we will need it later.
So we know that the operations with
a hash table run in time big O(c + 1).
And so we want both small m to
use fewer memory and small c so
that everything works faster.
And here's a good example.
We see a hash table of size 8 with a few
chains and we see that the length of
the chains are relatively the same, with
the longest chain being of length just 2.
So everything will work fast.
And here's a bad example.
When we again have hash table of size 8,
but all the keys fell in the same cell 1.
And they make up a very long chain
of size m, in this case, it is 8.
So this is what we want to avoid.
Let's try a few hash functions
that come to our mind.
First, let's select cardinality of 1000.
And choose the first three digits as
the hash value for the phone number.
For example for
this phone number it will be 800,
because the first three digits are 800.
However there is a problem with this hash
function because the area code, which
is the first three digits will be the same
for many, many people in your phone book.
Probably because they live In
the same city with you, and so
they will have the same area code.
And the hash values for
their phone numbers will be the same, and
they will make up a very long chain.
Another idea is to take the last digits,
again the cardinality is 1,000, and
we take the last three
digits as the hash value.
So for this number, it will be 567.
But still, there can be a problem if there
are many phone numbers in your phone book,
which, for example, end in three zeros, or
in some other combinations
of three digits.
So, another approach is to just select
a random value as the hash function,
a random number between 0 and 999.
And then the distribution of
hash values will be very good,
probably the longest chain will be short.
However, we cannot use such
hash function actually because
when we'll call the hash function
again to look up the phone number we
stored in the phone book we won't find it
because we are looking in the wrong place.
Because the value of the hash function
changed because it's not deterministic.
So we learned that the hash function
must be deterministic, that is return
the same value if given the same
phone number as the input each time.
So good hash functions are deterministic.
Fast to compute because we do that every
time we need to store something or
modify something or
find something in our hash table.
And they should distribute the keys
well in different cells and
have few collisions.
Unfortunately, there is no
universal hash function.
Most specifically, the Lemma says
that the number of all possible keys,
the sizes of the universe
with keys is large enough.
Much larger than the cardinality of
the hash function that we want to use
to save memory.
Then for any specific deterministic
hash function there is a bad input,
which results in many, many collisions.
Why is that?
Well, let's look at the universe U and
select some cardinality for example, 3.
Then, our universe will be
divided into three groups.
All the keys that have hash value 0,
all the keys that have hash value 1,
and all the keys that
have hash value of 2.
Now, let's select
the biggest of those groups.
In this case,
it's the group with hash value of 1.
This group will definitely be of size at
least one-third of the whole universe and
it can be even bigger.
In this case for example, around 42%.
And then, if we take all these keys or
a significant part of
these keys as an input,
they will have the same hash value.
And so, all of them will make collisions
between themselves and they will
form a very long chain in the hash table
and everything will work very slowly.
Of course, if we change the hash
function for this particular input,
it will distribute the keys more
uniformly among hash values.
But for this particular hash function,
this will be a bad input.
And for any specific hash
function with any cardinality,
we'll be able to select
a bad input this way.
And in the next video,
you will learn how to solve this problem.