Hi, in this video we will prove that
the set of functions we suggested to you
with integers is really a universal
family of hash functions.
This video will be heavy on math but
it is optional.
We will use properties of prime
numbers of modular arithmetics.
We will use the concept of
one to one correspondence.
Properties of upper integral parts of
real number and probabilities of course.
So the theorem is that the set of
functions was suggested polygraphic H with
index B is the set of all
hash functions indexed by B,
A, and B where B is a prime number and
A and B are parameters.
And those parameters
generate hash functions.
So the formula for the hash function
is on the side, and parameters a and
b are from one to p-1 and
from zero to p-1, respectively.
So this is a family of hash functions
which contains p multiplied by p-1,
different hash functions for
different bayers ab.
So these functions is
the universal family for
the universe of keys,
which are integers from 0 to p- 1.
And of course, it will be also universal
family for any sub-set of this universe.
Now, let's prove this theorem.
To do that, we first need a Lemma.
So, select some hash function with
parameters a and b from our set, a b.
And fix some keys, x and y which are
different, then, the intermediate values,
which would compute while computing
the hash value of keys x and y.
So ax + b modular p and ay + b modular p,
those are the intermediate values
before we take the value modular m and
get the actual value of the hash
function from our family.
So those values are always different for
different keys in the universe.
We will prove this Lemma by contradiction.
So suppose is equal to s or
(ax + b) is equal to (ay +b) mod p.
We subtract the right part
from the left part and
we see that a(x-y) is equal to 0 mod p.
And that means that b divides
product of a and x minus y.
Now recall that b is a prime number and so
it means that either b divides a or
that b divides x minus y.
But a is between 1 and p minus 1 so
a is a positive integer less than p and
p is prime so p cannot divide a and
thus p must divide x minus y.
But x and y are between 0 and p minus 1.
So their difference is,
by absolute value, less than p.
And p divides x minus y.
So, the only value for x minus y,
for which it is possible is 0.
x minus y is 0.
And so x is equal to y.
But this contradicts our
initial assumption that x and
y are different keys.
And so we prove by contradiction
that r is not equal to s.
There is a corollary from that that for
hash function h
which is without taking modular m,
there are no collisions.
And an important corollary is that for
a hash function,
which is before taking modulo m,
there are no collisions for the universe
of integer keys from 0 to p minus 1.
Now we need another lemma.
That for
any pair of different keys x and y,
there is a 1 to 1 correspondence
between pairs of numbers a and
b which generally different
hash functions in our family.
And pairs of numbers r and s,
which are the intermediate values in
the computation of hash
function of keys x and y.
Let's prove that.
First know that different pairs a,
b generate different pairs r, s.
And that is because if we
have some pair r, s we can
uniquely solve for a and
b module b with these formulas.
So if there is any other pair, a prime
b prime which leads to the same r and
s, then actually a prime and
b prime have to be equal to a and
b respectively because of these equations.
So now we know that different pairs a and
b generate different pairs r, s.
And we know that the total number of
pairs a,b is p multiplied by p-1 because
there are p-1 values for a and
independently p values for b.
So total number of pairs
is p multiplied by p-1.
And also, it turns out that the total
number of pairs r,s is also p multiplied
by p-1 Because the total
number of pairs r,
s with values from 0 to p- 1 is p squared.
But r must be different from s so
we must subtract p from that,
and that will be p squared- p which
is the same as p multiplied by p- 1.
So the number of pairs a,
b is the same as the number of pairs r, s.
And different pairs a,b led to different
pairs (r,s) and that means that
there is a one to one correspondence
between these pairs and these pairs.
And the corollary from that is that if
we select some pair of different keys,
x and y and
we select any hash function at random.
For all our family with equal probability,
which is one of p multiplied
by p minus one, because they're all,
p multiplied by p minus 1,
different hash functions in our family,
then each pair of values are S.
Which are intermediate values,
happen with equal probability,
again, one over P multiplied by p- 1 so
why is that?
Well we know that there's a one to one
correspondence between pairs a, b and
pairs r, s and selecting the hash
function from our family is the same
selecting random pair a, b we know
that the probability of any pair a,
b is one over p by p -1.
And so the probability of any pair
r,s is the same as the probability of
the corresponding pair a,b.
So it is always 1/p(p- 1).
So we proved our corrollary.
Now let's prove the initial theorem.
The probability of collision for a fixed
pair of keys, x and y, which are different
is the same as the probability that
r module m is the same as s module m.
We know that r is different from s, but
they still can be equal module m
because m can be less than Pm.
In most cases it is actually less than b.
So we, again, know that each pair r,
s has probability 1 over p by p minus 1.
And we'll estimate the probability
of collision using this fact.
Know that for each fixed r from 0
to p minus 1, there are at most.
Upper integral part of p over m,
minus 1 such value of s that
s is different from r and
r modular m is the same as s modular m.
So why is that?
Well, let's assume, without loss of
generality, that r modular m is 0.
And look at the roll of numbers from 0-P-1
than the numbers which
have the same remainder
module m as r are 0 M, 2M, 3M, 4M and so
on up to a paranted real part
of P over M-1 multiplied by M.
We cannot multiply the next integer
by m because that is already
bigger than p minus 1, so
in total there are part of pure m,
different integers between 0 and
p minus 1 which have the same
remainder modular m as r.
But, s also needs to be different from r.
So, the number of such s', less by 1.
And now, the probability of collision
is equal to probability r module m,
equal to s module m, and that is,
at most, some of probabilities
of all such pairs are s for
which this equality holds.
So we sum over all different
values of r from 0 to p-1 and
then we sum over all pairs
which contain this r.
And for which s module m
is the same as r module m.
We estimated that their at most
integral part of p over m-1
such as for any fixed r.
And the probability of any
final pair of this r and
any s with the same remainder
module m is 1 over p
by p-1 so
the total probability is at most this sum.
And the sum has exactly p and
it has p in the denominator so
we can just remove the sum and
the denominator and
we get upper integral part of
p over m-1 divided by p-1.
Then we use the property of that upper
integral part of p over m at most
p plus m minus one over m.
And then, when we make the common
denominator, and remove
all the things that cancel out,
we see that it is equal to 1 over m.
So we just proved that the probability of
r modular m being the same as s
modular m is, at most, 1 over m.
And that proves that
the probability of collision for
some fixed pair of different keys,
x and y is, at most, 1 over m.
And that is the property of universal
family that we needed to prove.
So we finally proved our theorem.
In conclusion, we've just proved
that a suggested family is
really a universal family for
integers, but now the important thing
that integers are not unbounded
on the integers from 0 to p- 1.
So if you need to hash really,
really big integers,
you will need to select a prime number
that is bigger, even bigger than
the largest of those numbers and
then you will get universal family for
that prime number and
it will work for your integers.
We also proved in the previous
video the upper bound for
expected chain length using universal
family and constant amortized expected
running time of operations with hash
table, also provided in the last lecture.
So now we have the whole picture.
We have a universal family for integers.
And we have proofs that if
you use a universal family,
that your operations work fast.
So now we are confident that if
you use the suggested family for
integers, then the operations
with the hash tables storing
those integers will run fast in practice,
at least on average.