Hi, in the previous videos,
you've learned how to quickly look up name
in your phonebook given the phone number.
And we want to learn to solve
the reverse problem given a name,
look up a phone number of
the corresponding person.
To do that, we need to implement
the Map from names to phone numbers.
And we can again use hash tables and
we can again use chaining as
in the previous sections.
But we need to design a hash
function that is defined names.
And more generally, we want to learn to
hash arbitrary strings of characters.
And by the way in this video, you will
also learn how hashing of strings and
implemented in the Java
programming language.
But first, let's introduce a new notation.
Denote by lSl enclosed in vertical
lines the length of string S.
For example,
the length of string l"a"l is 1,
length of string l"ab"l is 2, and
length of string l"abcde"l is 5.
So now how do hash strings?
Well when we're given a string,
we're actually given
a sequence of characters from
S[0] to S length of S- 1.
We number the characters of
the strings from 0 in this lecture.
And S[i] Is an individual character that
is in the i-th position in the string.
I say that we should
use all the characters
when we compute our hash
function of a string.
Indeed, if we don't use the first
character, there will be many collisions.
For example, if the first symbol of the
string is not used, then the hash value
of strings ("aa"), ("ba") and so
on, up to ("za") will be the same.
Because however we compute
the value of the hash function,
it doesn't use the value
of the first character.
And if everything else in
the strings stays the same, and
we only change the first character that
doesn't influence the value of the hash
function then the value of the hash
function must be the same.
And so there will be a lot of collisions
and we want to avoid collisions.
So we need to use value of
each of the characters.
Now, we could do a lot
of things with that.
For example,
sum the values of all the characters or
multiply them, but
we'll do something different.
Well first,
to even compute something on a string,
we need to convert each character
of the string to an integer code.
For example,
that can be ASCII code or Unicode,
corresponding to that symbol on your
computer, that doesn't really matter.
And also we'll again need to
choose a big prime number p,
the same as we used in
the integer hashing.
So suppose we've chosen some big
prime number p, now we introduce
a new family of hash functions called
polynomial family of hash functions.
So calligraphy p is the family of hash
functions which is index by small p,
which is our big prime number.
And also index by x, and x is a parameter
which changes from 1 to p- 1.
So the value of a hash
function index by p and
x on a string S, is the following sum.
It is a polynomial sum where we multiply
the integer quote corresponding to
the ith character of S, which is noted by
S of i, the same as the character itself.
We multiply it by x to the power of i.
We sum all these things up, and
we take the value modular p.
So this is a family of hash functions, and
the chronology of all
those hash functions is p.
So any such hash function
returns value from 0 to p- 1.
And how many hash functions
are there in this family?
Well of course, there are exactly
p- 1 different hash functions,
because to choose to define a hash
function from this family you would just
need to choose the value of x.
And x changes from 1 to p- 1, and
it's an integer number of course.
So how can we implement a hash
function from this family?
S, the procedure PolyHash which
takes it's input string S,
prime number p and parameter x, implements
the hash function from our peril.
It starts with the signing values of 0
to the result to the hash value will
return to end.
And then it will go from right
to left in our string and
compute new value based on the value
of the corresponding character.
And there is a formula in
the code that does exactly that.
And I will show you by example
that what we get in the end
by applying this formula
is exactly what we want.
So basically,
we start with a hash value of 0, and
then we start with i equal to 2 if
the length of our string S is 3.
We start with length of S- 1 which is 2.
We have current value of hash = 0.
So we multiply the 0 by x and get 0,
then we add the value of S[i]
which is S[2], and take it mod p.
And so after first iteration of the for
loop, we get S[2] mod p.
What happens is the next iteration,
that i is decreased and i is now 1.
And we multiply the current
value S[2] by x.
And we add s[1], and
take everything modular p.
And what we get is the same as of
S[1] + S[2] multiply by x modular p.
And then the last iteration,
i is decreased to 0.
We multiply the current value by x.
What we get is S[1] multiply by
x + S[2] multiply by x squared.
And then we also add S[0] to the sum and
take everything modular p.
And the result is S[0] + S[1]
multiply by x + S[2] multiply by x2,
exactly as we wanted.
A polynomial hash function,
with prime P and prime parameter x.
And by the way, the implementation
of the built in hash code methods in
the class stream in Java,
is very similar to our procedure PolyHash.
The only difference is that,
it always uses x = 31.
And for some technical reasons,
it avoids the modular p operator It
just computes the polynomial sum
without any modular division.
So now you know how a function that is
used probably trillions of times a day by
thousands and
many thousands of different programs,
how this function is implemented.
So now about the efficiency
of our polynomial family.
First, Lemma says that for
any two different strings s1 and
s2 of length at most L + 1.
If you choose a random hash function
from the polynomial family by
selecting a random value of x,
parameter x from 1 to p- 1.
You can select a random hash
function from the family.
So if you select a random hash from the
polynomial family, then the probability
of collision on these two different
strings is at most L divided by p.
So that doesn't seem like a good
estimate because L can be big,
but actually it is your power to choose p.
If you choose very, very big prime number
p then L over p will be very small.
And know that it won't influence the
running time of the PolyHash procedure,
because the running time of this
procedure is big length of S.
It only depends on
the length of the string.
It doesn't depend on the length
of number p more or less.
So if you select a really big number p,
then the probability of collision
will be very small and the hash function
will still be computed very fast.
The idea of proof of this Lemma
is that the equation polynomial
equation of power L, modular prime number
p has at most L different solutions x.
Basically, when we consider
two strings S1 and S2.
The fact that the hash value or
some hash function from
the polynomial family is the same for
these two strings means
that x corresponding to our
hash function is a solution
of this kind of equation.
And the fact that strings are different
makes sure that at least one of
the coefficients of this equation is
different from 0, and that is essential.
If the strings were the same of course,
the value of any hash function
on them will be the same.
But if they're different then
the probability is at most L over p.
Because there are only L or
less different x for
which the hash function can give
the same value on these two strings.