Hello everybody, welcome back
to the Graph Algorithms course.
Today we're going to talk about algorithms
for exploring graphs, in particular,
ways to tell us which vertices
can be reached from which others.
So for an example of the type of
problem we're trying to solve here,
suppose that you're playing a video game.
And you found the exit to some level,
but you don't want to go there just yet.
You want to first sort of
explore this whole level and
make sure you found all the secrets inside
it, make sure you get all the loot and
XP that there is to be found.
And you can certainly wander around
between the various rooms and
find a bunch passageways and so on.
And you've been wandering around for
a while and
maybe haven't discover anything new yet.
But you'd like to make sure that you've
really found everything before you leave.
How do you accomplish this?
How do you make sure
that found everything?
And this sort of is a notion
of exploring a graph.
You've got theses rooms,
they're connected by passageways.
And you want to make sure that everything,
at least everything that's reachable from
where you started, you can actually get to
it and find, explore the entire region.
And this actually sort of,
this of related questions are actually
very useful in a number of applications.
For example, if you have a map and
you want to find a route between
some location on the map and
some other, it often depends on this sort
of exploration of the graph, making sure
that you can find some sequence of roads
to follow to get you where you want to go.
This could also be used if you're
sort of building a road system and
want to ensure that the entire
thing is connected.
You need to have some sort of algorithm
to tell what can be reached from what.
And finally, it has more recreational
things, the video game example, but
also if you want to solve the maze.
This is very much, well,
can I get from the start to the finish
in this sort graph that connects things?
But also various puzzles,
if you think of sort of vertices as
sort of possible configurations.
And then edges that describe
moves that you can make and
want to say, can I rearrange
the puzzle to end up in this location?
Again, this sort of exploration
algorithm becomes very important.
So before we get into this too much,
we really want to formalize what we mean.
In particular, we want to know what
does it mean to be reachable from
a given vertex.
And basically,
the idea is you start at the vertex and
you're allowed to follow
edges of the graph.
And you want to able to see
what you can end up at.
And so to formalize this,
we'd find a path in a graph G to be
a sequence of vertices v0, v1, v2,
etc., such that each vertex is connected
to the next one by an edge of the graph.
So we get some sequence
of edges to follow.
So the formal description of the problem
that we would like to solve is
given a graph G, and a vertex s in G,
we'd like to find the collection of
all vertices v in the graph such
that there is a path from s to v,
everything that we can reach from S.
So, just to get a little bit of practice,
if we have the following graph,
which vertices here are reachable from A?
Well think about it a little bit and
you find out that A, C, D, F, H,
and I are all reachable.
And it's easy to see that these vertices
sort of do all connect up from edges,
but you then can't get to B, E, G or J.
And this is sort of because
there are no edges that connect
any of these vertices we can reach
to any of these other vertices.
And so there's no way to escape,
except for these six.
And this is sort of the actual
idea behind the algorithm.
What you want to do is you want to
make sure that you can actually find
everything that you can reach.
And so what you do is you sort of expand,
you find a bunch of vertices.
These are a bunch that I can reach.
But then if there are any edges that
connect ones that you can reach to ones
that you can't reach so far, well, you
have to sort of explore those edges and
find the new vertices on the other end,
and
sort of add them to the list
that you know about.
And you sort of keep expanding this list
of vertices that you know you can get to
until you can't connect to
anything new and then you're done.
So to formalize this
algorithm a little bit,
we are going to keep
a list of DiscoveredNodes.
And this starts out just with the vertex
axis you're supposed to start at.
But then what you do is while there
is an edge e that leaves this set of
DiscoveredNodes that connects to something
you have discovered to something you
haven't discovered, then what you do is
you take the vertex at the other end of
that edge and
add it to your list of DiscoveredNodes.
And you just keep doing this until
there's nothing new to be found.
And then you return this
list of DiscoveredNodes.
Okay, that's a reasonable algorithm and
it does work.
But in order to really code this up,
you need to do
some work to handle the bookkeeping
that's required for this algorithm.
You need to do things like you
need to keep track of which
vertices you've discovered and
which edges you've dealt with,
which edges you've actually checked and
which ones you haven't.
You also need to know sort of which
order to explore new edges in.
If there are several possible edges to
follow, which one do you follow next?
And so, what we're going to do now is talk
about a specific way to implement this and
deal with these sort of bookkeeping isues.
The first thing that we need to do
is we need to keep track of which
vertices we've already found.
And for this, we're going to
associate a boolean variable to each
vertex visited(v) which basically
tells us have we visited it yet.
The next thing that we're going to
need to do is we need to,
most of the vertices that we visited will
actually will have already sort of checked
all of the edges relating to them.
But some we haven't and we somewhere need
to keep track of the list of vertices that
still have edges hanging off of them that
might connect this to something new.
Now this list isn't going to
appear explicitly in our program.
It'll actually sort of to be
hidden in the program stock so
this is that points a little bit sudden.
We'll sort of see it once
we introduce the algorithm.
The final thing is we need to
discover which order to discover,
to follow new edges in.
And for this we are going to use what
is known as the Depth First order.
What this means is we're just going
to start our initial vertex and
we're just going to start
following a chain of edges.
We're just going to follow
some really long path forward
until one of two things happens.
One thing is we could stumble across
a vertex that we have already seen before.
In which case there's no reason
to have followed that edge and
we'll just back up to
where we were before.
The second thing that could happen
though is that we hit a dead end.
And we actually hit a dead end and
can't go any further forward,
then we actually back up.
And then once we back up though, we don't
just back all the way to the beginning.
We just back up once step and
then try going forwards again from
that new vertex that we found.
Okay, so that's the basic idea.
How do we implement this?
Well part of the beauty about this is that
we have a very simple recursive algorithm.
So Explore(v),
the first thing you do is you set
the visited marker of v to be true.
We say we have visited it.
Next, for each neighbor w of v,
for each w that's adjacent to v,
if w has not already been visited,
we recursively explore w.
Okay, so this is a very compact program.
Let's sort of actually see
what it does on an example.
Right, also I should mention that in order
for this program to execute reasonably
efficiently, we really want an adjacency
list representation of our graph.
That's because we have this for
loop we want to iterate over all of
the neighbors of v in our graph.
And for that,
if you have an adjacency list, which
gives you a list of all the neighbors
of v, that's incredibly easy to do.
If you don't have an adjacency
list on the other hand,
this algorithm really
isn't that efficient.
Okay, fine.
So let's look at in the example.
Here's a graph, we're going to
start by exploring that vertex.
So we mark it as visited.
We then check for unvisited neighbors.
And hey, look there is one.
So we recursively explore
that other vertex.
We mark it as visited.
We search for unvisited neighbors.
And we have this one.
So remember now we're sort of three
layers into the program stack here.
This is sort of a sub
routine of a sub routine.
But now when we're exploring this
vertex it has no unvisited neighbors.
So after we've done
a little bit of checking,
we decide that we're done exploring
this guy and we pop the stack.
This other guy still we
visited both of his neighbors,
we pock the stock back to
the original explorer call.
Now this vortex does have some
unvisited neighbors left,
so let's visit one of them and
explore that.
Mark it as visited,
find an unexplored neighbor, explore that.
Mark as visited, unexplored neighbor,
mark it as visited, unexplored neighbor.
Now when we explore this vertex though,
once again we're stuck.
So we wrap up exploring that guy, pop
a level up the stack, go back to exploring
this other vertex, who now actually
does have another unvisited neighbor.
So we're going to go visit that one.
Now we've actually visited
everything in the graph.
So all we're going to
do is at each vertex,
we're going to note that all of
their neighbors have been visited.
We're going to pop up the stack and
get back to where we started and conclude.
So here we actually have
found all these vertices.
And in fact if you look at it,
we've actually figured out
how to reach them all.
If you look at sort of these darker edges
which are the ones our algorithm sort
of actually followed when you ran it,
these sort of connect up
to all the other vertices.
And they actually tell us if
you sort of follow these edges,
they give you a unique path to any
other vertex that we can reach.
Okay, so that's our algorithm.
Let's talk about correctness.
And the theorem is that if all the
vertices in our graph start as unvisited,
when we run Explore(v) it
marks as visited exactly
the vertices that are reachable from v.
And the proof here isn't so bad.
The first thing to note is that
we only ever explore things that
are reachable from v.
And that's because, well, the way our
recursive calls work are we either
start at v, or we explore a neighbor of
a vertex that we've already explored.
So any vertex that we end up
exploring has to be a neighbor of
a neighbor of a neighbor of a neighbor of
a neighbor of a neighbor of the original
vertex or something.
But that does basically give us a path and
say that wherever we got to was reachable.
The next thing to note is that a w,
vertex w,
is not marked as visited unless
it has already been explored,
which is just the only way we mark things
as visited is when we explore them.
But finally,
we should note that if w gets explored,
well, we then look at
all the neighbors of w.
And either those neighbors have
already been visited, in which case
it means they've been explored at some
point, or we end up exploring them.
So in other words, if w gets explored,
all of its neighbors also get explored.
So to finish things, suppose that we have
some vertex u that is reachable from v.
That means that we've got
a path from v going up to u.
And if we actually explored everything
along this path we'd be done.
We would have explored u at some point.
So let's assume that we don't.
Assume that w's actually the furthest
thing along this path that we've explored.
However, by what we had
on the previous slide,
if you explore a vertex you also
explore all of its neighbors.
So the next vertex z along this
path must also be explored.
And so this is a contradiction.
This says the only way this can work
is if we actually explored every
vertex along the path.
But that means we've explored u,
which is good.
Okay, so this explore algorithm is
actually really great if we just want
to find the vertices that
are reachable from a given one.
But sometimes you want
to do a little bit more.
You actually want to find all
the vertices of the graph G,
not just those coming from a given one.
So for this, we're going to use a slightly
more complicated algorithm called depth
first search.
And for this what we do is the following,
first we mark everything as unvisited.
Then for each vertex in the graph,
if it has not yet been visited,
we explore that vertex.
So to look at an example on this graph,
we find an unvisited vertex,
say that one, and we explore it.
So we find a neighbor and another neighbor
and then we pop back up the stack.
And then we find something adjacent
to our original vertex and come back.
And now we're done exploring
that first vertex.
So now we look for a new vertex we've
never visited before, like say that one.
We explore its neighbor, come back,
we're done exploring that guy.
We find a new vertex that we
haven't visited, that one.
We explore its neighbor and
his neighbor and then come back.
And now that we've actually
visited all the vertices,
only now do we sort of wrap up and
conclude our algorithm.
So to analyze the run-time of this
algorithm, we have to note a few things.
Firstly, whenever we explore a vertex,
we immediately mark it as being visited.
That's the first thing that we do.
The next thing to note is that no vertex
ever gets explored if it's
already been visited.
And in fact if you look at every time we
make an explore as even a recursive call,
then we always first check if it has
not been visited, then we explore it.
And this means that no vertex
gets explored more than once.
In fact, this means that each vertex gets
explored exactly once because the outer
loop in the DFS explores every vertex
if it hasn't already been visited.
But each vertex in our graph
gets explored exactly once.
But for each vertex, when we explore it,
there's this inner loop where we have
to check all neighbors of that vertex.
And so we have to do work for
each neighbor of each vertex.
And so we have to be more proportional
to the total number of neighbors
over all vertices.
And that's proportional to the number of
edges because each edge connecting A and
B says that A is a neighbor of B and
that B is a neighbor of A.
So it contributes to two neighbors.
But the total amount of work is
still O of the number of edges.
So total work we do, O of one work per
vertex and O of one work per edge and
the total run time is O of size of V plus
size of E, a nice linear time algorithm.
So that is depth first search.
Next time we're going to talk a little bit
more about reachability and graphs and
give some more applications
of this algorithm.
So, I'll see you then.