In this video, we'll provide the full
outline of the Greek word algorithm.
So as you remember that
algorithm is recursive, for
this reason we pass through this
procedure [INAUDIBLE] a and
also doing this is l and
r in this array for left and right and
this procedure saw the sub array
inside r within this is form l to r.
Well we first check
whether l is at least r.
And if yes then this means that they
can respond in sub array contains at
most one element.
And this in turn means that nothing
needs to be done so we just return.
Otherwise we call the partition
procedure with the same parameters.
It returns an index m between l and r.
So it rearranges all the elements inside
this sub array with
the following property.
After the call to this procedure,
A of m stays in its final position,
meaning that all the elements to the left
of an element A of m are at most A of m.
And all the elements to the right
are greater than A of m.
Well once again,
after the call to the partition procedure,
A of m stays in its final position.
So what remains to be done is to sort all
the elements that are at most A to m.
They stay to the left of A of m, and
all the elements that stay to the right.
So we do this just by
making two recursive calls.
So this is how the wall
algorithm looks pictorially.
Again, we are given an array A,
with two indices l and r,
and we are going to sort the sub
array inside from indices L to R.
So with first call the participation
procedure which parameter A, l and r.
And it gives us an index m between l and
r was the following property.
All elements to the left of them
are at most the element A of m.
All the elements to the right
are great as an A of m.
Then we make two recursive calls to
sort the left part within this is from
l to m- 1 and to solve the right
part within this is from m + 1 to r.
And immediately after these two
recursive call, we have a sorted array.
So before showing the actual
of the partition procedure,
we explain it's main ideas again,
on a toy example.
So first of all, we will take is
the element A[l] and denoted by x.
This will be called our pivot element.
So what pivot is exactly is
the element with respect to which
we're going to partition our sub array.
So x will be placed in its final position.
So our goal now is to rearrange all the
elements inside our current sub array so
that x stays in its final position and
all the elements to the left of x.
At most x and all the elements to
the right of x are greater than x.
So we will do this gradually increasing
the region of already discovered elements.
So for this we will use a counter i, and
we will maintain the following invariant.
So I will go from l + 1 to r, and
at each point of time when we
have already have the i element
we will keep to region in sizes
these region from l + 1 to i.
In the first region from l + y to j, we
will keep all elements that are at most x.
In the second adjacent region
within this is from j +
1 to i we will have all elements
that are greater than x.
Let's see it for example.
So I assume that we are somewhere
in the middle of this process.
In this case, x is equal to 6, and
we need to partition all
the elements with respect to x.
We already have two sub regions so
in the red region,
we keep all elements that are at most x.
There are at most 6 in the blue
region we have holds elements that
are greater than 6.
Okay, now we move i to the next
position and we discover the element 9.
So this element is greater than 6, so
we just need to extend the second region,
the blue region.
The region of elements
is at greater than 6.
So in this case we just do nothing.
Well the next case is more interesting,
we move i to the next position, and
we discover the element 4.
In this case, we need to somehow
move this element to the red region,
to the region of elements which at most 6.
So to do this we just
swoop it to currently
first element of the blue region,
in this case was 9.
So if we do this 4 will be the last
element of currently red region and
9 will go to the blue region.
So we do this and now,
we increase also the just
to reflect the fact that our red
region had just been extended.
Then we will find to the next element so
we discover element 7 which is
greater than 6 which means that we
can just extend the blue region,
then we discover another
element which is 6.
6 is at most 6 and
it is actually equal to 6, so
we need to move it to the red region.
Again, we swap it with the first
element of the blue region and
then we extend the red region.
We increase g to reflect the fact that
the red region has just been extended,
then we discover another element,
which is at most 6.
We move it to the end of the red region.
And finally, what we also need to do
in the very end is to move the pivot
element which is 6 in this
case to its final position.
And its final position actually
can easily be found in this case.
So we have red region and
we have blue region.
In red region, all the elements
are at most 6, and in blue region,
all the elements are greater than 6.
So we can just swap 6 with the last
element of the red region.
In this case it is 1, so
if we swap these two elements then you
can see that all the elements in the blue
region are indeed greater than 6.
All the elements in the red
region are smaller than 6.
So we are done with this
partition procedure.
Where now ready to present the Soutacot
of the petition procedure.
We called it what we're going to
do is to place some element x,
which is called the pivot, into it's final
place so that all the elements before
x are at most x and all the elements
after x is greater than x.
So as the pivot element in this procedure,
we are going to use just the first
element of the correspondence of rate,
so x is assigned A of l.
We're also going to remain
the following subregions.
So first of all, we will readily increase
the region of discovered elements.
So i goes from l +1 to r and
inside this region of
[INAUDIBLE] elements,
we will maintain two sub regions.
In the first region with
indices from l +1 to j,
we will keep all of
the elements at most x.
In the second region with indices from j+1
to i, we will keep all of the elements
that are greater than x and we will
gradually and freeze the value of i.
So when i is increased, so
I assumed that i has just been increase so
we discovered a new element of A of i.
So if A of i is greater
than x then just the second
of region of elements
that are greater than x,
is extended automatically and we do
not need to do anything in this case.
However, if the newly discovered
element is at most x,
then we need to move it
to the first region.
So we do this as follows.
So we just increase the value
of j to indicate the fact that
the first region has just been increased,
and then swap the elements.
A[j] and A[i], so this way,
we just maintain our invariant
each time when i is increased.
So in the very end,
when i reaches the value of r,
we also need to place our initial
element that states that at
the beginning our pivot
between our two regions.
So for this we just swap elements A[l],
so this is our pivot with element A[j].
And we then return the value j as
an index of our pivot element.