In this video we address the issue
of equal elements in the.
So recall that we proved the upper
bound on the running time of the render
Greek algorithm, in the assumption
that all the elements inside
the given array are prioritized different.
And actually,
we used essentially these assumptions.
So, recall that we estimated
the probability that two elements,
A prime of I and
A prime of J are comparative.
And we argued that if any element
between them is selected,
the appearance is that they
will not become period.
However, if they are equal, so
if A prime of A is equal to A prime of J,
this means actually that all
the elements in this range are equal.
So if we select any element inside this
range, in the middle of this range,
as a pivot, then it is not true that
these two elements will go into different
parts with respect to this element, this
is just because all of the elements inside
this range are equal, which means that if
we partition with respect of this element,
all of the elements in this range
will be [INAUDIBLE] this element.
So, they all will be in the left part
with respect to this element, okay?
So our analysis doesn't work for
equal elements but
let's see what happens in real life.
What happens if we run
the greek sort algorithm for
the array in which there
are equal elements.
For this, let's use the following
online visualization.
This visualization shows
how different selection,
different certain algorithms that
are formed on different datasets.
So there are eight
certain algorithms here where we are now
interested in this QuickSort algorithm.
And there are four different
types of datasets.
So the field datasets is
just random sequence.
The next one is in sorted sequence,
the next one is a reversed sequence and
the next one which is most interesting to
us at the moment is a sequence that
contains a few unique elements.
So let's see how the greek sort
algorithm performs on the last dataset.
So for this let's just run all
the algorithms, on all data sets.
So let's see what happens here.
So you, you may notice now that, for
example, have already sorted everything.
And while greek sort have just finished
to sort the last, the last data set.
So Greek sort is not, is not so
fast on data sets that contains few
unique elements and this is why.
So just consider a dataset that consists
of elements that are all
equal to each other.
So all elements are equal to each.
This means that the selection,
the partition procedure always
partitions the array with
respect to the element x, right?
And then in this case, one of the parts,
namely the part of the elements that
are greater than x, is just empty.
It has size zero.
And the other part has size n minus one.
So the records and equalities, the records
equalities on the running time of
how a algorithm on such a data set
always satisfies the following relation,
T of n is equal to T of n minus 1
plus a linear term plus T of 0.
And we know already, so
this is an unbalanced partition.
We know the responds to
the quadratic right in time so,
which means that the running time of the
quick sort algorithm a very simple array.
So it contains all the elements
of this array are equal.
Which means that actually
this array is already sorted.
In this array our quick sort
algorithm spends a quadratic
time to sort it to overcome this
difficulty we'll do the following.
Instead of partitioning
our rate into two regions.
Namely these regions contain all elements
that contain all x and
all elements that are greater than x.
We are going to partition
into three parts.
The corresponding partition procedure
is usually called three-way partition.
Formally, it returns two indices.
m1 and m2, such that,
all the elements inside the region
from m1 to m2 are equal to x.
All the elements to the left of
this region are smaller than x.
All the elements that are to the right
of this region are greater than x.
So this is how it looks pictorially.
We have three regions.
So, from l to m1 minus 1, we have all
elements that are smaller than x.
In the region from m1 to m2,
we have all elements that are equal to x.
In the region from m2 plus 1 to r, we have
all elements that are greater than x.
This procedure actually can be
implemented in a similar way
to their regional partition procedure.
It can be implemented ties with a single
kind of area with maintaing their regions
or it can be implemented with two counts.
So we first split our rate
into regions which contain
elements of most x or greater than x and
then we split the region into two parts.
Well, this is how the modified randomized
quick sort algorithm is going to apply.
So we just replace it,
the cold partition procedure by
a cold two partition suite procedure.
Now we have three regions, and, actually
the middle region is in its final place,
so we do not touch it after
the partition procedure.
We make two recursive calls to the first
region and to the last region.
So, let's see whether the resulting
algorithm is indeed Greek.
And for this,
let's use the same visualization.
The resulting algorithm is
shown here in the last column.
Let's, once again, run all the algorithms
and see what happens in the last column.
Well we see that now, the results in
Greek algorithm, is indeed Greek.