The previous video ended on
an unsuccessful attempt to submit our
solution to the max
pairwise product problem.
Even worse, we don't know what is
the test on which our program fails
because the system doesn't show it to us.
This is actually a pretty
standard situation when
solving algorithmic programming assignments.
In this, and the next few videos, we will
learn how to overcome this situation and
to even avoid it in the first place.
I will explain to you and
show you in action a powerful
technique called stress testing.
By the end, you will be able
to implement a stress test for
your solution of an algorithmic problem,
use it to find a small and
easy test on which your program fails,
debug your program, and
make sure it works correctly
afterwards with high confidence.
Also, you will be able to list and apply
the set of standard testing techniques,
which should be always applied when
solving algorithmic programming
assignments.
So what is stress testing?
In general, it is a program that generates
random tests in an infinite loop, and
for each test,
it launches your solution on this test and
an alternative solution on the same
test and compares the results.
This alternative solution you also have
to invent and implement yourself, but
it is usually easy, because it can be any
simple, slow, brute force solution, or
just any other solution that
you can come up with.
The only requirement is that
it should be significantly
different from your main solution.
Then you just wait until you find
a test on which your solutions differ.
If one of them is correct and another is
wrong, then it is guaranteed to happen,
because there is some test for which your
wrong solution gives the wrong answer, and
your correct solution gives correct
answer, and so they differ.
If, however, both of your solutions
are wrong, which also happens often,
they are still almost guaranteed to have
some test on which one of them gives
wrong answer and another one gives
correct answer because they're probably
wrong in different places.
When you find a test on which
your solutions' answers differ,
you can determine which one of
them returns wrong answer and
debug it, fix it, and
then repeat the stress testing.
Now let's look at
the practical implementation.
I've already implemented
the stress test for this problem.
It is in the file called stress_test.cpp.
Let's look into that.
So it is almost the same as
the solution that we've sent
in the previous video, but
I've added some things.
First, we add this #include .
And this include just
allows us to use a part of
standard library to generate
some random numbers.
And we will use it to generate
some random tests automatically.
Then we have the same
code of two functions,
MaxPairwiseProduct and
MaxPairwiseProductFast,
which we used in our last solution
which was submitted in the system.
But now in the main function,
we have a whole additional while loop.
Here it is, and
this is where the stress test itself is.
So what do we do in principle is
we generate some random tests,
then we launch both solutions,
MaxPairwiseProduct and
MaxPairwiseProductFast on this random test,
and we compare the results.
And the idea is if you have a correct
solution and another correct solution and
the correct answer for
your problem is the only correct answer,
then any two correct solutions will
give the same answers for any test.
And if you have some wrong solution and
some correct solution,
then on some tests,
their answers will differ.
And also if you have two wrong solutions,
then probably they're
wrong in a different way, and
then there will also be some test,
hopefully, on which their
answers differ.
If you generate a lot of tests,
then with some probability, at some point,
you will generate a test for which
the answers of the solutions differ.
You can detect that situation, and then
look at the input test and at the answers.
And you can determine which of the
algorithms was right, and which was wrong,
maybe both were wrong.
But anyway, you will find at least one of
the algorithms which are wrong because if
their answers are different, then at
least one of them gives wrong answer.
And then you will be able
to debug that algorithm,
fix the bug, and
then run the stress test again.
And either,
you will again find some difference, or
you won't find any difference anymore,
and then hopefully,
you fixed all the bugs in
all the solutions, and you can submit it.
So how it works in practice.
First, we need to generate the test for
our problem.
We'll start with generating number n,
the number of numbers.
And our problem states that
n should be at least 2.
So we first generate a big random
number using function rand.
Then we take it modulo 10, and
it gives us some random number
between 0 and 9, and then we add 2.
And so
we get a random number between 2 and 11.
Why is it so small?
Well, we first want both our
solutions to work fast enough.
And also if we create a big random test,
it will be hard for
us to debug it, so we start with
some relatively small value of n.
We immediately output it on the screen,
so that if we find some tests for
which our solution is wrong,
we immediately see it on the screen.
After generating n, we should generate
the array of numbers, a, itself.
So we iterate n times,
and we add random numbers
from 0 to 99,999 to the end of array a.
So these are the numbers in
the range which is allowed.
And then we also output all
these numbers in one line,
separated by spaces and
a newline character.
So by this time, we've already output
the whole input test on the screen.
Now what we need to do is
actually need to launch
both our solutions on this input test and
get two results,
the result of the main solution and
the result of the fast solution.
After that, we compare those two results.
If they are different, it means that at
least one of the solutions was wrong.
So we output words Wrong answer
on the screen, and we also output
the first result, a space, and the second
result and a newline character.
After that, we break our loop.
We can notice that our while loop
is a so-called infinite loop, but
we actually end it as soon as we find
some test for which our solutions differ.
If we don't find the different sum test,
we just output the word OK on the screen,
to denote that actually both solutions
have already computed the answers,
but the answers are the same.
And then we continue.
So we continue our infinite loop,
in the search of the test
that will save us,
that we can use to debug our solution.
And we wrote that code just in front
of all the code to read the numbers
from the input, to compute the answer,
and to output it to the screen.
So we basically inserted this
code in our regular program.
But instead of reading
numbers from the input,
it will first try to find the test for
which our two solutions differ.
And in the next video, we will launch this
stress test to find a test in which our
solutions differ,
debug our fast solution, and fix it.