In this video, we're going to
continue talking about trees.
And in particular, look at walking a tree,
or visiting the elements of a tree,
or traversing the elements of a tree.
So often we want to go through the nodes
of a tree in a particular order.
We talked earlier, when we were looking
at the syntax tree of an expression,
how we could evaluate the expression
by working our way up from the leaves.
So that would be one way of walking
through a tree in a particular order so
we could evaluate.
Another example might be
printing the nodes of a tree.
If we had a binary search tree,
we might want to get the elements
of a tree in sorted order.
There are two main ways
to traverse a tree.
One, is depth-first.
So there,
we completely traverse one sub-tree
before we go on to a sibling sub-tree.
Alternatively, in breadth-first search we
traverse all the nodes at one level before
we go to the next level.
So in that case, we would traverse
all of our siblings before
we visited any of the children
of any of the siblings.
We'll see some code examples of these.
In depth-first search, so we're going to
look here at an in-order traversal.
And that's really defined best for
a binary tree.
This is InOrderTraversal is
what we might use to print
all the nodes of a binary search
tree in alphabetical order.
So, we're going to have a
recursive implementation,
where if we have a nil tree,
we do nothing, otherwise,
we traverse the left sub-tree, and then do
whatever we're going to do with the key,
visit it, in this case,
we're going to print it.
But often there's just some
operation you want to carry out, and
then traverse the right sub-tree.
So let's look at an example of this.
We've got our binary search tree.
And we're going to look at how these
nodes get printed out if we do
an in-order traversal.
So to begin with, we go to the Les node.
And from there, since it's not nil,
we're going to do an in-order traversal
of its left child, which is Cathy.
Similarly now we're going to do
an in-order traversal of its left child,
which is Alex.
We do an in-order traversal of its left
child which is nil, so it does nothing.
So we come back to Alex, and
then print out Alex, and
then traverse its right sub-tree
which is nil and does nothing.
We come back to Alex.
And then we're finished with Alex and
we go back to Cathy.
So, we have successfully
completed Cathy's left sub-tree.
So we did an in-order traversal of that, so
now we're going to print Cathy, and
then do an in-order traversal of its
right sub-tree, which is Frank.
So we go to Frank, similarly
now we're going to print out Frank.
We've finished with Frank and
go back to Cathy, and
now we've completed Cathy totally,
so we go back to Les.
We completed Les' left sub-tree, so
we're now going to print Les and
then traverse Les' right sub-tree.
So that is Sam,
traverse its left sub-tree which is Nancy.
Print it out, go back to Sam,
we've completed Sam's left sub-tree, so
we print Sam, and then go ahead and
do Sam's right sub-tree which is Violet,
which will end up printing Tony,
Violet, and then Wendy.
We're completed with Wendy.
We go back to Violet.
We completed her right sub-tree, so we go
back to Sam, completed his right sub-tree,
go back to Les, completed his
right sub-tree, and we're done.
So we see we get the elements
out in sorted order.
And again, we do the left child.
And then the node and
then the right child.
And by our definition of
a binary search tree,
that then gives them to us in order
because we know all the elements in
the left child are in fact less than or
equal to the node itself.
The next depth-first
traversal is a pre-order traversal.
Now the in-order traversal really is
only defined for a binary tree because
we talk about doing the left child and
then the node and then the right child.
And so it's not clear if you
had let's say three children,
where it is you'd actually
put the node itself.
So you might do the first child and
then print the node, and then second and
third child.
Or first child and then second child and
print the node, and then third child.
It's kind of undefined then,
so not well-defined.
However, these next two, the pre-order and
post-order traversal are well defined.
Not just for binary trees, but for
general, arbitrary number
of children trees.
So here the pre-order traversal says,
we're going to go ahead
first if it's nil we return.
We print the key first, that is, we visit
the node itself and then its children.
So we're going to, in this case,
go ahead and go to
the Les tree and then print out its
key and then go to its children.
So we're going to first go to its
left child which is Cathy, and for
Cathy, we then print Cathy, and
then go to its left child which is Alex,
print Alex, we go back to Cathy.
And we finished its left child, so then
we go do its right child, which is Frank.
We finished Frank.
We finished Cathy.
We go back up to Les.
We've already printed Les.
We've already visited or
traversed Les' left child.
Now we can traverse Les' right child,
so it'll be Sam, which we'll print out.
And then we'll go to Nancy, which we'll
print out, we'll go back up to Sam and
then to Violet, and we will print Violet,
and then print Violet's children,
which will be Tony and
Wendy and then return back.
A post-order traversal is like
a pre-order traversal expect instead of
printing the node itself first, which is a
pre, we print it last, which is the post.
So all we've really done is move
where this print statement is.
And here then,
what's the last of these notes
that's going to be printed?
Well it's actually going to be Les,
because we're not going to be able
to print Les until we've finished
completely dealing with Les' left sub-tree
and right sub-tree.
So we'll visit Les, and
then visit Cathy, and then Alex,
and then we'll actually print out Alex.
Once we're done with Alex, we'll go
back up to Cathy and down to Frank, and
then print out Frank, and
then once we're done with both Alex and
Frank we can then print Cathy.
We go back up to Les, and
we now need to go deal with
Les' right child which is Sam.
In order to deal with Sam we go to Nancy,
print Nancy, go back up to Sam and
down to Violet, and deal with the Violet
tree, which will print out Tony, and
then Wendy, and then Violet.
And on our way back up, then, when we get
up to Sam, we have finished its children,
so we can print out Sam.
When we get up to Les, we've finished
its children, so we can print out Les.
One thing to note about
the recursive traversal
is we do have sort of under the covers,
a stack that's being used.
Because in a recursive call, every time
we make a call back to a procedure,
we are invoking another
frame on the stack.
So we are saving implicitly our
information of where we are on the stack.
Breadth-first, we're going to actually
use a queue instead of a stack.
So in the breadth-first, we are going to
call it level traversal here,
we're going to go ahead and
instantiate a queue,
and on the queue first
put the root of the tree.
So we put that in the queue and
then while the queue is not empty,
we're going to dequeue, so pull a node
off, deal with that by printing it and
then if it's got a left child,
enqueue the left child, if it's got
a right child, enqueue the right child.
And so this will have
the effect of going through and
processing the elements in level order.
We see the example here, and
we're going to show the queue.
So here let's say we're just before
the while loop, the queue contains Les.
And we're going to now dequeue Les from
the queue, output it by printing it, and
then enqueue Les' children
which are Cathy and Sam.
Now, we visit those in order, so
first we're going to dequeue Cathy, print
it out and then enqueue its children.
Remember when we're enqueuing
we go at the end of the line, so
Alex and Frank go after Sam.
So now we're going to dequeue Sam,
print it, and
then enqueue its children Nancy and
Violet.
So we can see what we've done then is,
we first printed Les,
that's level one and then we printed the
elements of level two, which are Cathy and
Sam, and now we're going to go on
to the elements at level three.
So notice,
all the elements in level three,
Alex, Frank, Nancy, and
Violet are in the queue already.
And they're all going to be processed
before any of the level four nodes
are processed.
So even though they'll be pushed in the queue,
since the level three nodes got there first
that they're all going to be processed
before we process the level four ones.
So here, we dequeue Alex,
print it out, and we're done.
Dequeue Frank, print it out,
we're done with Frank.
Dequeue Nancy, print it out,
we're done with Nancy.
And Violet, we print it out, but
then also enqueue Tony and Wendy, and
then dequeue those and print them out.
So this is a breadth-first search,
with an explicit queue,
you can do depth-first searches
rather than recursively,
iteratively, but you will need
an additional data structure which
is a stack to keep track of
the work still to be done.
So in summary, trees are used for lots
of different things in computer science.
We've seen that trees have a key and
normally have children, although there
are alternative representations of trees.
The tree walks that are normally
done are traversals,
are DFS: depth-first search,
and BFS: breadth-first search.
There are different types of
depth-first search traversals,
pre-order, in-order, and post-order.
When you work with a tree,
it's common to use  recursive algorithms,
although note that we didn't for the
breadth-first search where we needed to
go through the elements of the tree
in kind of a non-recursive order.
And finally, in computer science,
trees grow down.