Hello everybody, welcome back.
We're still talking about
binary search trees but
today we're going to talk about AVL trees.
And AVL trees are just sort of a specific
way of maintaining balance in your
binary search tree.
And we're just going to talk
about sort of the basic idea.
Next lecture we're going to talk
about how to actually implement them.
But okay, what's the idea?
We learned last lecture that in order for
our search operations to be fast,
we need to maintain balance of the tree.
But before we can do that we first need a
way to measure the balance of the tree so
that we can know if we're unbalanced and
know how to fix it.
And a natural way to do this is by
what's called the height of a node.
So if you have a node in the tree,
its height is the maximum length of a path
from that node to a leaf of your tree.
Fair enough.
So for
example if we have the following tree,
what's the height of the highlighted node?
Well, this node has height six, the
following path of length six leads down
from this node and
it turns out to be nothing longer.
So, we can define height
recursively in a very easy way.
If you have leaf its height is
one because you're just there and
you can't go any further.
Otherwise, well the longest path downwards
you can have, it's either through
the longest path on your left side or
the longest path on your right side.
So you want to take the maximum of
the height of your left child and
the height of your right child, and
then you need to add one to that because
n sort of gets added to this path.
Okay, that's fine.
Now, in order to actually make use of this
height we actually are going to want to
add a new field to our nodes.
So, the nodes that made up our
tree previously stored a key and
are pointed to the parents on the left
child and the right child, and
now they also need to store another
piece of data, the height of node.
And note that we are actually
going to have to do some work, and
we'll talk a little bit
about how to do this later,
to insure that this height field
is actually kept up to date.
We can't just store it as a number and
leave it there forever.
If we rearrange the tree,
we might need to change its heights.
In any case, back to balance.
Height is a very rough measure
of the size of a sub-tree.
For things to be balanced, we want the
size of the two sub-trees of the left and
right children of any given
node to be roughly the same.
And so there's an obvious way to do this.
We'd like to force the heights of
these children to be roughly the same.
So the AVL property is the following.
For all nodes N in our tray,
we would like it to be the case
that the difference between
the height of the left child and
the height of the right
child is at most one.
And we claim that if you can maintain
this property for all nodes in your tree,
this actually ensures that your
tree is reasonably well balanced.
Okay and so, really what we'd like to
know is that if you have the AVL property
on all nodes, then the total height
of the tree should be logarithmic.
It should be O(log(n)).
So basically what we want to say
is that you have an AVL tree and
it doesn't have too many nodes.
Then the height is not too big.
But it turns out that the easier way to
get at this is to turn this on its head.
We want to show instead that
if you have an AVL tree and
the height isn't too big,
then you can't have too many nodes.
And this we can do.
So we're going to prove
the following theorem.
Suppose that you have an AVL tree,
a tree satisfying the AVL property, and
N is a node of this tree with height h.
THen the claim is that the sub-tree
of N has to have size at
least the Fibonacci Number F's og h.
And so just to review,
we talked about Fibonacci Numbers way back
in the introductory unit for this, but
for the previous course in this sequence.
But this is just a sequence of numbers.
The zeroth one is zero,
the first is one, and
from there after each Fibonacci number
is the sum of the previous two.
Now, these are a nice predictable
sequence, they grow pretty fast,
the end Fibonacci number's at least two
to the n over two for all n at least 6.
Okay so let's look at the proof,
we're going to do this by induction
on the height of our node.
If the node we're looking at
has height one, it's a leaf.
And it's sub-tree has one node which
is the first Fibonacci number, great.
Next we need an inductive hypothesis
if you've got some node of height h.
By sort of definition of the height,
at least one of your two children
need to have height h minus one.
Then, by the AVL property,
your other child needs to have
height at least h minus two.
So by the inductive hypothesis,
the total number of nodes in this tree is
at least the sum of the h -1 Fibonacci
number plus the h- 2 Fibonacci number,
which equals the h Fibonacci number.
And so that completes the proof.
So what does this mean?
It means that if a node
in our tree has height h,
the sub-tree of that node has height
at least two to the h over two.
But if our tree only has n nodes, two
to the h over two can't be more than n.
So the height can't be more
than two log base two of n.
Which is o of log n.
And so the conclusion is if we
can maintain the AVL property,
you can perform all of your find and
operations in such in O(log(n)) time.
And so next lecture we're going to talk
about how to maintain this property but
this is the key idea.
If we can maintain this property, we have
a balanced tree and things should be fast.
So I'll see you next time as we discuss
how to ensure that this happens