Hello, everybody, welcome back.
Today, we're going to continue talking
about AVL Trees, and in particular,
we're going to talk about the actual
implementation and what goes into that.
So, as you recall, the AVL Tree was this
sort of property that we wanted our binary
search tree to have,
where we needed to ensure that for
any given node, its two children
have nearly the same height.
So the following is an ideal tree
everything's labelled by their height,
it all works out.
Now, there's a problem that if we update
this tree it can destroy this property.
So if we try to add a new
node where the blue node is,
then what happens is, a bunch of nodes in
the tree, their heights change because
now they have a longer path
which leads to this new node.
And now there are a couple locations at
which the AVL property fails to hold.
So, in other words,
we need a way to correct this issue.
And there is one thing that actually helps
a little bit here, which is that when we
do an insertion the only heights of nodes
that change are along the insertion path.
The only time when a height
can get bigger is because
the new path from it to a leaf
ends up at the leaf you staggered.
So we only need to worry
about nodes on this path, but
we do actually need to worry.
Okay, just sort of review what it is,
we have this AVL tree, we want to
insert a new node either A B C or D.
Which one of these will require
us to do some rebalancing?
It turns out that D is the only place
where we have a problem, but if you insert
D it changes a bunch of these heights and
that destroys AVL program.
The other inserts it
turns out would be fine.
Okay, so
let's actually talk about how to do this.
So we need a new insertion algorithm that
involves some rebalancing of the tree
in order to maintain our AVL property.
And the basic idea of
the algorithm is pretty simple.
First you just insert your
node as you would before.
You then find the node
that you just inserted and
then you want to run
some rebalance operation.
And this operation should start down at
N and should probably work its way all
the way up to the root, sort of
following parent pointers as you go.
Just to sort of make sure that everything
that could have been made unbalanced has
been fixed, and we're all good.
So the question is how do we
actually do this rebalancing?
And, well, the idea is the following.
At any given node, if the height of your
left child and the height of your right
child differ by at most 1, you're fine,
you're already satisfied the AVL property.
On the other hand it could be the case
that your children's heights differ
by more than one.
In that case you actually do
need to do some rearranging.
If your left child is two taller than
your right, you need to fix things and
probably what you need to do is move
your left child higher up in the tree
relative to your right to compensate for
the fact that it's sort of bigger.
Fortunately for us,
you can actually show that these inserts,
the height difference is never
going to be more than 2.
And that simplifies things a little bit.
Okay, so the basic idea is the following.
In order to rebalance N,
first we need to store P,
the parent of N just because
we're going to, after we fix N,
we're going to want to fix things at P,
and so on recursively.
Now, if the height of N's left child
is bigger than the height of its
right child by more than one,
we need to rebalance right-wards.
If the height of the right child is bigger
than the height of the left child by more
than one we need to rebalance left-wards.
Then after that, no matter what happens,
we maybe need to readjust the height of N,
because
the height field that was stored might be
inaccurate if we inserted things below it.
And then if the parent that we
fixed wasn't the null point,
if we weren't already at the root,
we need to go back up and
we need to rebalance
the parent recursively.
So quickly, this AdjustHeight function,
this sort of just fixes the number that
we're storing in the height field.
All it does is we sort of set the height
to be one plus the maximum of the height
of the left child and
the height of the right child.
Just given by this recursive
formula we had for the height.
Okay!
But the key thing we still
haven't really touched.
We need to figure out how
to do the rebalancing.
So you have a node, its left child
is heavier than its right child.
Its left child has exactly
two more height to it.
And the basic idea is the left child
is bigger, it needs to be higher up, so
we should just rotate everything right.
And it turns out that in a lot of
cases this is actually enough to solve
the problem.
There is one case where it doesn't work.
So B is the node we're
trying to rebalance.
A is its left child which is too heavy,
and we're going to assume that A is
too heavy because its right child
has some large height, n+1.
The problem is that if we just rotate B
to the right, then this thing of height,
n+1, switches sides of the tree
when we perform this rotation.
Switches from being A's
child to being B's child.
And when we do this we've switched
our tree from being unbalanced at B
to being unbalanced at A now,
in the other direction.
And so, just performing this
one rotation doesn't help here.
In this case the problem is that A's right
child, which we'll call X, was too heavy.
So the first thing we need
to do is make X higher up.
So what you can do is,
instead of just doing this rotation at B,
first we rotate A to the left one,
then we rotate B to the right one.
And then you can do some case analysis and
you figure out after you do this
you've actually fixed all
the problems that you have.
And it's good.
The operation for
rebalancing right is you let M
be the left child of N and then you check
to see if we've to be in this other case.
If M's right child has height more
than M's left child, then you
rotate M to the left, and then no matter
what you did, you rotate N to the right.
And then no matter what you did,
all the nodes that you
rearranged in this procedure,
you need to adjust their heights to
make sure that everything works out.
Once you do this, this rebalances
things at that node properly,
it sets all the heights to what
they should be, and it's good.
Okay, so that's how insert works.
Next, we need to talk about delete.
And the thing is deletions can also
change the balance of the tree.
Remember generally what we do is
the deletions we removed the node.
But, we replaced it by its successor and
then promoted its successor's child.
And the thing to note is that when you do
this, sort of the space in the tree where
the successor was, the height of that
denoting that location decreased by one.
Because instead of having successor and
then its child and then some such,
you just have the child and such.
And this of course can cause your tree to
become unbalanced even if it were balanced
beforehand.
So, we of course need a way to fix this,
but there's a simple solution.
You delete the node N as before.
You then let M be this left child of
the node that replaced N this thing
that might have unbalanced the tree.
And then you run the same rebalance
operation that we did for
our insertions starting on M and
then filtering its way up the tree.
And once you've done that,
everything works.
And so what we've done is we've shown that
you can maintain this AVL property and
you can do it pretty efficiently,
all of our rebalancing work was only sort
of O of 1 work per level of the tree.
And so if you can do all of this,
we can actually perform all of our basic
binary search tree operations in O of log
n time per operation, using AVL trees.
And this is great.
We really do have a good data structure
now for these local search problems.
So that's all for today, coming next
lecture we are going to talk about
a couple of other useful operations that
you can perform on binary surgeries.