Hello everybody, welcome back.
Last time, we talked about AVL trees and
showed that they can perform your
basic binary search tree operations.
But now we're going to introduce
a couple of new operations and
talk about how to implement them.
So, another useful feature of binary
search trees is in addition to being
able to search them, there's also a bunch
of sort of interesting ways that you could
recombine them.
And so we're going to discuss
here two of these operations.
One of them is merge,
which takes two binary search trees and
combines them into a single one.
And the other one is split,
which takes one binary search tree and
breaks it into two.
So, let's start with merge.
And the idea is, in general,
if you have two sorted lists and
want to combined them into
sort of a single sorted list.
This is actually pretty slow,
it's going to take O(n) time,
because you sort of need to figure out
how the lists interweave with each other.
This is the thing you do in merge sort.
However, there is a case where
you can merge them a lot faster.
And that's the case where they're
separated from each other,
where they're sort of, one's on one side,
one's on the other side.
And so, this is the case that
merge is going to work with.
So you're giving two trees, R1 and
R2, or the roots of these trees.
And they're going to need to have the
property that all the keys in R1's tree
are smaller than all of
the keys in R2's tree.
And if we're given this, we should then
return the root of a new tree that had
all of the elements of both of the trees.
So just to review this condition that
we have, of the three trees below,
which of them can be properly
merged with the one above?
The answer is that only A can because
all of the elements of A are less than
all of the elements of the guy above.
B has this problem that it's got a 9,
and 9 is between 8 and
10 so
it can't really be separated from them.
And C has the problem that it has both 2,
which is smaller than everything above,
and 12 which is bigger
than everything above.
So, A is the only guy
that actually works here.
Okay, so
how do you do this merge operation?
Well, there's actually a case where
it's super easy to merge trees and
that's if,
instead of just being given the two trees,
we also have an extra node
that we can use as the root.
Because then you just have the node
up top, you have the guys in R1,
the small guys on the left of it, the guys
in R2, the big guys on the right of it.
That's your tree.
So, the implementation,
we'll call this function MergeWithRoot,
is you let R1 be the left child of T,
R2 be the right child of T.
Let T be the parents of these two.
If you need to do things
involving restoring heights,
you adjust those as appropriate,
and then you return T.
This takes O(1) time, very simple.
The problem is, well,
what if we're not given this extra node?
Then there's actually
a pretty simple solution.
You find the largest element,
of say, the left subtree.
You remove that, and
then turn it into the root of the new guy.
And that works.
So now if we want to merge R1 and
R2, we're going to find the largest
element of R1, call that T.
You're going to delete T from its subtree,
and then you're going to merge with root.
And that works.
The run time's a little bit worse.
You have to spend O of the height
time to find this node T, but
other than that it's pretty efficient.
So, just to review,
we've got this tree, we find
the biggest element to the left tree 8.
We then delete it, and
then we merge with root.
That's all there is to it.
Now if we didn't care about balance,
that would be all we'd have
to say about this operation.
Unfortunately, this merge operation
doesn't preserve balance properties.
And the problem is that,
well, the two trees,
you didn't really touch them very much,
so they stay balanced.
But when you stick them both
together under the same root,
well, if one tree is much, much bigger
than the other, suddenly the root is very,
very unbalanced, and this is a problem.
So we need a way to fix this.
And there's actually a not
very difficult way to do that.
The idea is that we can't merge the, say,
left subtree with the right subtree
because the left one is way too big.
So what we're going to do is not merge
the whole guy with the whole guy here.
We're going to have to find some node of
approximately the same height as this guy
on the right so that we can merge that.
And so what we're going to do is, we're
going to sort of climb down the sort of
right edge of the bigger tree
until we find a sub tree of
the right height that we can merge
with our guy on the other side.
Okay, so how do we implement this?
AVLTreeMergeWithRoot.
What we're going to do is, if the heights
of the two trees differ by at most 1,
we can just merge with root as before.
We then figure out what the height
of T needs to be and return it.
That simple.
Otherwise though, what happens if say
R1's height is bigger than R2's height?
Well, what we want to do is we want to
step down to instead of merging R1 with
R2, we merge R1's right child with R2.
So, we use merge with root to merge
the right child with R2 at this T,
and we get some new
tree with root R prime.
R prime we set back to be
the right child of R1,
and similarly set R1 to be the parent.
And then we need to
rebalance this at R1 because
things might be off by a little bit, but
it turns out not more than about one.
We knew how to deal with that
with our old rebalance operation.
And than we return the root of the tree.
If, on the other hand,
R1's height is smaller than R2's height,
we sort of do the same operation but
on the opposite side.
Okay, so, let's analyze this.
Every step we take down the side
of the tree decreases the height
difference by either 1 or 2.
So we're just going to keep decreasing
the height difference until we're off by
at most 1.
Then we merge, and
we soon have to go back up the chain.
But the amount of time this takes
isn't the depth of the tree,
it's sort of the number of steps
we need to take down the side.
And that's approximately
the difference in the two heights.
And this will actualy
be important in a bit.
Okay, so that was the merge operation.
Next, we're going to talk about sort
of the opposite operation, split.
Merge takes two trees and
turns them into one.
Split breaks one tree into two.
What you do is you pick an element,
say 6, and
then you've got the tree consisting
of all the elements less than 6, and
then another one from all
the elements bigger than 6.
So split should take the root of a tree
and the key x, and the output should be
two different trees, one with all
the elements less than x in your tree, and
one with all of
the elements bigger than x.
Okay now,
the idea is actually not so hard.
What we're going to do is
we're going to search for
x, and then the search path,
well it's got a few nodes on the path.
And then it has a bunch of trees
hanging off to the left of the path.
These things are all going
to be smaller than x.
And it's going to have a bunch of trees
hanging off to the right that are all
going to be bigger than x.
And so all we have to do is take
these trees that are smaller than x,
merge them all together,
take these things bigger than x,
and then we have two trees.
So let's see how this works.
So we're going to do this recursively.
We're going to split at R,
at this point x.
If our root is null,
if we just have the null tree,
we just return a pair of null vectors,
whatever.
Next if x is less than
the key at the root,
what that means is that everything
on the right is bigger than x.
That's sort of all on the right.
But the left side of the root,
we need to split that in two.
So we're going to recursively
run split on R.Left, and
that gives us two trees, R1 and R2.
Now R1 is actually everything in
the whole tree that's smaller than x.
That half is done, but
R2 needs to be combined with the whole
right subtree of our original tree.
So we run MergeWithRoot on R2 and
R.Right with R as the root.
Fortunately we have this extra nodes,
uses the root.
And this gives us an R3.
And we can return R1 and R3 as our split.
If X is bigger than the key, we can do
the same thing on the opposite side.
Hopefully you can figure that out.
Okay, so
the first thing to note is that if we,
instead of just doing a MergeWithRoot,
we used AVLMergeWithRoot.
This insures that the two trees we
produce are both balanced, which is good.
Also if you look at the run
time of this algorithm, well,
the run time of AVLMergeWithRoot is O,
the difference in the two heights.
So we have to look at the difference
between the biggest type and
the next biggest and the next biggest and
the one after that and so on.
This sum actually telescopes, and the
total run time is O of the maximum height
of one of these trees we're trying
to merge, which is just O(log(n)).
And so we've got these two operation,
merge combines trees,
split breaks them in two, and
both operations can be implemented
in O(log(n)) time using AVL trees.
So that's these two operations.
Next time we're going to talk
about a couple of applications.
One of them's going to sort of talk about
a way that we can make use of these split
and merge in an interesting way.