Hi, in this video we'll consider another
better way to find a good potential for
A star.
It will be based on landmarks.
So first, a landmark.
Let's fix some vertex A and
we will call this vertex a landmark.
Then we choose the potential function,
pi of v equal to distance from
this landmark to the target,
minus distance from this
landmark to the node V.
And by distance, I mean the distance
in the graph we're looking at.
So we can of course not know this
distance beforehand because to
find this distance we need to launch
some shortest path algorithm.
But let's suppose we know
the distance from the landmark to
all other vertices beforehand.
Then we can use such potential.
And I say that this potential is feasible.
And that the value of this potential
on the target vertex is zero.
So let's prove this.
First we write the length of the edge
with this potential by definition.
And then we write it as length
of the initial edge, minus
distance from landmark to the target plus
distance from landmark to distance u.
Then plus distance from
the landmark to the target.
And so this cancels out with the minus
distance from the landmark to the target.
And minus distance from
the landmark to node v.
And this is in turn equal to
distance from landmark to u plus
length of the s from u to v minus
distance from the landmark to v.
And now this is non-negative due
to triangle inequality
because distance from A to V
cannot be bigger than distance from A to U
plus length of the edge connecting U to V.
So we have just proven that
the edge weight for any U and
V and the new graph is non negative.
So the potential we provide
is indeed feasible.
And also the value of this potential on
the target vertex is just difference of
d from A to t,
with d from A to t which is zero.
So this is a physical potential
with zero value on the target.
And so this is actually a lower bound for
any node V,
on the distance from V to the target.
So what can we do with this.
We can select several landmarks which
are basically any vertices of the graph.
So we can select them any way we want.And
we can optimize how good do we select
those landmarks and hopefully our reason
will become better because of that.
So we select those landmarks,
maybe 10 landmarks for example, and
we precompute the distances from those
landmarks to all other vertices.
So to do that we'll need
to launch something like
algorithm which will find the distances
from one node to all the others.
We cannot really save
anything on this one,
because we need distances
to all other vertices.
So bidirectional storage or
a star won't help us here.
We will need to find distances
to all other vertices, and
we will need to scan the whole graph.
But this can be done on
the pre-computation state.
And then for anyone marked A.
We have the following inequalities.
The distance from any vertex v
to the target is greater than or
equal to distance from A to
the target minus distance from A to v
due to triangle inequality.
And also due to another triangle
inequality, we have another low end bound,
that distance from v to t
is greater than or equal to
distance from v to the landmark, minus
distance from target to the landmark.
We can use both if we can precompute
the distances not only from landmarks
to all the other nodes but
also two landmarks from all other nodes.
But to do that we just need to
reverse the graph and run algorithm
from landmarks from each
of the landmarks again.
We can use the tightest lower bounds out
of all those lower bounds for each node v.
So we take maximum over all
landmarks A that we selected
of both differences, and this will
be the tightest lower bound we have.
And this will still be visible but
I'll show, we can show that and
you know that the tighter the bounds,
the better the algorithm works,
the faster your A star search
will find the target verdicts.
So by choosing the landmarks wisely and
maximizing the lower bounds over them,
we can speed up our a star search a lot.
And now let's think how should
we select the landmarks.
The intuition is that a good landmark
appears either before the starting vertex
or after the target vertex and
then the lower bound
Induced by this landmark will
actually improve something.
And this is if we fix the source
vertex v and the target vertex w,
then the landmark is the one which is
either before before v or after w.
But we need to select a set of landmarks
that will work best for any query.
So for any query from service to target,
we need some landmarks which are before
s and some landmarks which are after t.
And so it makes, for example, to choose
the landmarks on the border of our map.
For example, here on a map of US,
we have landmarks in the rectangles,
which are red and yellow.
And in this particular search, in
the middle, from green area to blue area,
we used the four yellow landmarks,
meaning that only
the lower bounds from those four landmarks
actually improved our search in some way.
And this just supports
the idea that the landmarks
should be before the starting point and
after the ending point in some sense.
And here's another example
of a start with landmarks.
And again, red and
yellow rectangles are landmarks.
And again, yellow rectangles are those
landmarks which are used in the search.
And you see that how much less
vertices do we really visit
with an a star search, which is by the way
also bi-directional A star search,
than with the regular
bi-directional search.
Because in the regular bi-directional
search we had those a fat
circle surrounding each of the starts and
targets rectangles.
And here we have only small
tiny streams of scant
vertices colored in green and blue.
So this set of only something like
21 marks significantly reduces
each sequential search but
with the cost of pre-processing.
So to do fast we need to
pre-process our graph and
to compute distances from 20 vertices
to all other vertices in the graph.
So either we have a separate time
to pre-process our graph and
save the results, or
this is only applicable if we know that
we'll get a lot of queries in our problem.
So if we get just one query it's
faster to find the shortest
path from source to target directly
without first trying to find a shortest
path from 20, versus through all
other vertices on the graph.
But if you have 1,000 queries
to find the shortest path,
then already we're competing for
21 marks can be beneficial because it
will only take us 20 searches
from those landmarks.
And then each of the subsequent
1000 searches which were giving us
queries will be significantly faster.
In the problems of this project, in the
programming assignment, you will have both
problems where you need just to
compute the results for queries.
And you will have problems
where you will have a separate
time to pre-process
your graph as you want.
And then you will answer the queries.
And there we will offer you another
algorithm in the next lesson, which
works really well for huge rod networks.
But you could also try, instead of or in
addition to implementing data algorithm,
to also implement this A star
with landmarks algorithm.
And you can try different
ideas on landmarks selection.
And it is known that really,
a very good choice of landmarks can
lead to very fast algorithms for
subsequent queries on the shortest path.
In conclusion,
we've introduced A star algorithm,
which is basically a direct search.
And direct search can scan fewer vertices,
a lot fewer,
as you just saw on the pictures.
A star is a direct search algorithm based
on Dijkstra and potential functions.
And we can also make A star be directional
to make it the best of both worlds,
both a bidirectional and
a with potentials.
The Euclidean distance is one example of
a potential for road network on a plane.
And, we can also use landmarks to
create a good potential function.
And if we create several landmarks, and
we choose them wisely, so that there
are landmarks before and after source and
target verdicts, for any source and
target verdicts, then, this can speed up
our algorithm even more significantly.