Hi, in this lecture, you will learn
the algorithm for finding fastest routes,
which is used, for example, when you open
your navigation app to get home from
work faster or by logistics
companies when they want to deliver
the goods to their customers in time,
but use less cars and less people.
So let's first state the problem.
It's really easy to do.
For example, what is the fastest
route to get home from work, or
more generally, what is the fastest
route from point A to point B right now?
And below, you see a screenshot
from a popular navigation app,
Yonix Navigator, which is given
a task of getting the fastest
route from the point you are currently in,
which is marked by a circle
with the letter y in it, to the finish,
which is your destination.
And it suggests to you a few variants.
So the default suggestion is the fastest
route, but there are two others.
And there may be, for example,
a route which uses less turns or
the route which is easiest for
a novice driver.
And sometimes,
there can be a shorter route,
which is not the fastest one, but
shortest one in terms of distance.
So in this problem, we can represent
the city or the country as a graph,
where nodes are some
positions in the country.
For example, the crossroads and
the edges are the roads that
connect those crossroads.
And there are some weights
on those edges and
the weight on an edge is,
in this case, the time in seconds or
in minutes you need to get from start
of the edge to the end of the edge.
And what you need to find is
the shortest path in this graph,
but not shortest path in the graph
in terms of the number of edges,
shortest path in terms of the sum
of the weights of those edges.
So if you want to get from A to B in
the smallest amount of time possible,
then you get those by sum
paths with sum edges and
sum weights on those edges
corresponding to the time.
And you just sum up those
weights of the edges, and
you get the total time it will
take you to get from A to B.
You want the fastest route?
So you need the shortest path in
terms of the sum of the weights of
edges on this path.
Let's see now,
does the breadth-first search algorithm
from the previous lesson maybe help us?
So let's look at this graph, here,
we see that node A has a direct edge from
A to point B, where you need to get.
And so, what our breadth-first search
would say is that you already know
the optimal path from A to B because
there is a direct edge, and so there is
no point in getting to some other nodes,
just go directly from A to B, right?
Well, this doesn't work,
for example, in this case,
let's suppose that it takes 5
hours to get from A to B, and
the corresponding weight of
the edge from A to B is 5.
And let's suppose there is another node,
C,
such that there is an edge from A to C,
which takes 2 hours to go through it.
And another edge from C to B, which
also takes 2 hours to get through it.
And of course,
this looks a little bit strange, but
if there is a traffic jam on the road
from A to B, and roads from A to C and
from C to B are free roads, where there
is no traffic jam, then this can happen.
And so, then we see that going from
A to B through C will take just 4 hours,
while going directly from
A to B takes 5 hours, and so
our breadth-first search
algorithm doesn't work.
So maybe it's vice-versa,
maybe it's always better to work around,
to go around some node,
not to go directly.
But that's also not the case, because
if the edge from A to B is 3 hours,
and edges from A to C and
from C to B didn't change, and
we just removed the traffic jam from A to
B and it became 3 hours instead of 5,
it is now better to go
directly from A to B.
So there is now universal rule to
go directly or not to go directly.
We need something more clever than
that to solve our shortest or
fastest through the problem.
Now let's gain some intuition
about this problem.
So let's look at this graph below.
And assume that we stay at origin node S.
And we only know that the edge from
S to B is going to take 3 hours and
from S to C is going to take 5 hours.
So can we be sure that the distance
from S to C is equal to 5,
that it will take 5 hours for
the optimal route from S to C, okay?
So no, this is not the case,
because for example,
the edge from B to C can have weight 1,
and
so, the shortest route from S
to C will be from S to B and
from B to C, which is only 4 hours
instead of 5 hours if we go directly.
So we cannot be sure that the fastest
route from S to C is 5 hours.
Now, another question is can we be
sure that the distance from S to
B is equal to 3?
And in this case, the answer is yes,
because if we don't go directly from S
to B, what other options do we have?
We can go only from S to C and
then go by some other edges to come to B,
but if we go from S to C,
we spent already 5 hours.
And after that,
we also spend some time to get to B.
And the time is now negative.
So we cannot spend less than
3 hours time in the end.
We actually cannot spend less
than 5 hours in the end.
So going from S to B directly
by 3 hours is beneficial for us.
In terms of the graph and
the weights of the edges in it,
it means that there are no
negative weights on the edges.
All the weights are non-negative numbers.
And so, we cannot decrease the length
of the path by going through them.
So if we have already
a path of length 3 and
all other paths start
from spending more time,
we cannot improve this direct buff.
And in the next video,
we'll use this idea to create a negative
algorithm that solves our
fastest route problem.