Now let's implement this algorithm.
So the procedure Dijkstra takes again
graph G and origin node S as input.
It will also use dist values and
prev values.
It will initialize dist values with
infinities, but for the origin node S for
which dist value is 0.
And it will initialize breadth
values with pointers to nowhere.
It will use also some data structure which
can be an array or a priority queue.
It depends on your choice
of data structure.
And the writing time will
depend heavily on that but
any way this is a data structure, for
which we need just three operations.
To create it from a set of these values.
To extract the minimum value from
it to get the node outside of
known origin with a minimum dist value.
And, to change the dist variable of some
node which is currently
in this beta structure.
So we will talk later about
which data structure to choose,
but for example, we can use an array here
just to create an array from all
the dist values and then work with it.
So while this data structure is not empty,
we'll take out of it
the node with the minimum dist value,
and this data
structure will contain only those nodes
which are not in the known region.
So it will contain initially node s and
all the nodes, but then after we
make the first iteration we will
extract node s from this data structure H.
Because node s has dist value of 0 and all
other nodes have dist value of infinity,
so node s has the minimum dist value.
So we extract minimum from it,
which means that we take
the node with the minimum dist value and
remove it from the data structure.
And then we'll process this node u,
basically we take all the outgoing
edges from u in the graph and
we try to relax them.
To relax them, we check if it's
possible to relax the edge.
And if it's possible we update
the distance to the end of this edge,
the dist value to the end of this edge.
We update the prev value
of this node V and
most importantly we change the priority
of this node V in our data structure H.
What it means is that we improved
the dist value for this node V.
And now this node could become potentially
the node with the minimum dist value,
for example.
So we need to account for that.
So you know in data structure
we need to do something, for
example if we store
everything as an array,
we just need to decrease the value of
this array corresponding to node V.
And then if we store everything in
an array then when we do extract mean,
we just go through all
the values of this array and
find the minimum value and the node
corresponding to this minimum value.
So this all happens while our
data structure is not empty.
But basically it will happen at
most the number of nodes times,
because it starts with all
the nodes in the data structure.
And then just extract next node for
each time, and
the size increases one by one.