Now let's estimate the running
time of Dijkstra's algorithm.
In the beginning it just initializes
dist values and prev values and
that takes time proportional
to the number of nodes.
But our estimate will be bigger than that,
so we just ignore this part.
And other than that, it creates a data
structure to store dist values and
extract minimums from it.
It extracts the minimum node
from this data structure.
V times, where V is the number of nodes in
the graph, and also it examines the edges.
Each edge is examined, at most once,
when the start of this edge is processed.
And during processing,
it updates dist value,
pref value, and
changes priority in the data structure.
Updating dist value and
pref value is constant time,
so the main part is in
the ChangePriority part.
So now this running time estimating
depends on how do you actually
implement The data structure
from which you do ExtractMin,
ChangePriority, and
we should build by MakeQueue.
One way to implement it
is just using an array.
Actually we'll need two arrays.
First array is just the size V,
where you store
in the cell number i, you store
the dist value of the node number i.
But you also need to remove
nodes from this array, so
you'll use another boolean array,
where you store a flag.
Whether this node is still in the data
structure or is is not already.
So to build such arrays you need time
proportional to the number of nodes,
because it's basically, write down
these values for all the nodes and
you Write all the flags,
you say that they are true.
Then, each ExtractMin operation in the
time proportional to the number of notes.
because you need to go through the whole
array, check whether this particular node
is considered to be in
the data structure or not.
Just look up in the secondary, and then
if it is then try to proof the minimum,
and after you found the minimum,
you just mark the flag as false,
it's now it's no longer in
the data structure, and
you take the minimum
value from there array.
So each extractment of operation
works in time proportional to v and
we make v times, so
this is v squared time.
Now, change priority operation
is very easy in case of array,
because to priority you just need to
change the disvalue of one node so
you just get the number of that node And
you just change the value
in the first array corresponding to
that node, so that takes constant time.
And so in this case,
the total complexity is V + V squared + E.
And V squared is bigger than V obviously,
and
also V squared is bigger
than the recall to E,
because There can be at most one
edge between each pair of nodes so
V squared is the leading term and so
our running time is big O V squared for
the array implementation; and
there is another way to implement
this data structure using a binary heap or
priority cube built on top of binary heap.
We know that to build a binary heap
from an array of size V we need
time proportional to V.
We now that ExtractMin works
in the logarithmic time, so
the total time for
ExtractMin will be V log V.
And the tricky part is
ChangePriority ChangePriority operation
can be implemented in the binary heap,
but it is a little bit tricky.
So instead of implementing additional
operation in the binary heap,
we can actually cheat and
we can just insert a new element
in the heap each time we need to
decrease the dist value for some node.
So We need to improve our dist value and
to improve it means to decrease it.
What we can do is we can just insert
another element, a pair of a node and
its dist value estimation
into the priority queue.
So, then when the time
comes to extract that node
The pair with the minimum dist
value will be selected and
you will extract it with the minimum
dist value which was found by this time.
And if at some other point of
time you will also try to extract
this same node but with different
dist value, you can just ignore it,
you can just write down that you
already processed this node.
Extract it again from the q, and
just don't do anything with it.
So, this will increase
the size of the heap and so
refreshes will be slower a little bit, but
they won't be much slower because how many
elements can be in the and
in this priority queue?
It will be no more than the number
of edges because each time
you change priority you examine some edge,
and you examine some edge at most once.
So total number of change priority
operations is the number of edges.
And so you will add at most
E new elements in the heap.
In addition to the values
which were there initially.
And we know that e is at most v squared.
So logarithm of v is on the same,
it's like at most
two logarithms of v because logarithm of
v squared is just two logarithms of v.
So the last part, the total time for
ChangePriority is proportional to
E multiplied by logarithm of V.
And the final estimation
is V + E logarithm V.
Which is much better than v squared
in the case when there are no edges.
Because there are very many edges
like on the order of v squared
than v squared will be
equal to v squared log v.
Which is worse than in the case
of area implementation.
But if the number of edges less than v
squared the graph is far from being.
Full graph with all the edges,
then this can be much,
much faster than
the array-based implementation.
In conclusion, you now know the algorithm
to find the minimum time to get from
work to home for example.
And actually you also know the algorithm
to find The fastest route itself, because
the reconstruct path algorithm will be the
same as you have in the prev first search.
Because you have the same prev values and
you can just reconstruct
the path from them.
And you know that this algorithm works for
any graph with non-negative edge weights.
So you can not only find, Fastest routes
but you can also find shortest routes and
routes which are minimum in some
other senses and you know that
it works either in time quadratic and
number of nodes in the graph or
in time V plus E log V depending
on the implementation.
Either array based implementation or
binary heap based implementation.