Hi.
In this video, we'll solve the fastest
route problem using the idea
from the previous video, but
we will do it using a naive
algorithm in which we will need
to improve in the next video.
First, let's make an observation
that if we have some optimal path,
some fastest route or some shortest route.
Than any part of it between
some note in the middle and
some other note in the middle.
It's also optimal in the same sense.
Let's prove it.
Consider an optimal path from
some origin S to some note T and
consider some two vertices u and
v on this path.
They can coincide with s or t or
they can be somewhere in the middle.
Suppose there was some shorter path
from u to v which is marked with green.
Then we would be able to go from
s to u as there is no path.
Take a shorter path from u to v,
take a shortcut and
then go where there is
no path from v to t.
And in total,
this new path will be shorter than
the initial path, which was optimal.
So this cannot happen.
And so we know that actually any part of
an optimal path is also optimal itself.
Corollary from that is that if
there is some shortest path from
S two nodes and
u is the previous node on that path.
Then, distance from the origin
to the final destination,
t, is equal to the distance
from origin to node u,
which is the previous node,
plus wight of the edge between u and t.
And we will use this property
to improve our estimates
of distances from origin
to some nodes gradient.
You remember that in the breath
research algorithm we had an area or
map called dist, and
we use these dist values to store.
Our estimation from the distance to
the region to this particular now.
In the reference research we found
distance of started from Infinity.
As soon as they get update they
became correct distances formal
region to the corresponding note.
This will not be the case in algorithm.
These distances will change Several
times maybe before they become correct.
But in the end they will become correct.
And during the process
these distances will be upper
bounds on the actual distance.
So they will be more than or
equal to the real distance from
origin to the corresponding node.
[INAUDIBLE] the procedure called Edge
relaxation, and it means the following.
We take the edge U, V.
We check, is it better to go to V,
through the optimal
currently known path from S to U, and
then following the edge from U, to V.
Does it improve our current upper
ont he distance to v, or not?
So, we have some upper bound dist value,
dist of v, and
we achieve that,
maybe using u on the way or not.
We might have come to v in a different
way, and we might have come
using the same distance as if we go
from s to u, and then follow huv.
Or we could use longer path.
So we just check whether it is possible
to improve our current estimation of
distance of feet.
We are using distance of U
plus weight of the edge to U.
So here is the code of
relaxation procedure.
It takes one edge from U to V.
As input and it checks if
the current distance estimate of
v is bigger than the current distance
estimate of u plus weight of the edge.
That means that definitely
we can come to know
u from s with a path with
a length at most dist of u.
And if we then follow edge
uv with a weight w of uv we
will improve the distance estimate of v.
So in this case we update this distance
estimate we decrease always as you see And
we also remember that the node from
which we came into v is now u.
Remember that in the breadth for
search algorithm,
we start in pref the node from
which this node was discovered.
In this case, we use the same
data structure to the store
the node from where we've updated
the distance to our node last time.
Now, we're ready to suggest
a naive algorithm to solve our
fastest route problem.
Procedure naive takes graph g and
origin node S as inputs.
It uses dist values and prev values
the same as in the breth first search,
and we initialize these values
with infinity as dist[u].
And the prev[u] value with
point resting no where,
we also initialize the dist of
the original nod withe zero.
And then, the only thing we
do we relax all the edges.
More specifically,
on each iteration of the do while loop,
we try to relax each of
the edges in the graph.
And if at least one is effective, that is,
some dist value changes,
then we continue to the next iteration.
And we only stop When the whole iteration,
after going through all the edges in
the graph, couldn't relax anything.
And we state that this Naive algorithm
works, basically that it stops and
when it stops it finds correct
distances to all the nodes.
To prove that assume for the sake of
contradiction, that at some point
no edge can be relaxed and there is
a vertex v such that the distance to
the vertex is bigger than the actual
distance from origin to the note.
We know that this estimation
of distance cannot become less
than the actual distance because
this is always an upper bound.
It starts from infinity and
it is only decreased when we find
a better path from origin to this node.
So there is some path from origin to
this node of length exactly dist[v],
so it cannot be less than the actual
distance from origin to this node.
And this also means that there can
actually be no such situation that we
do relaxations [INAUDIBLE] and we do many
iterations and we don't stop at any point.
Because after any successful relaxation,
some distance estimation is
decreased by at least one.
And if we started with infinity
then the value just becomes finite,
but that can happen at most
a number of nodes times.
And if the value was already finite
it just decreases by at least one.
And if we started with some
number of finite values,
which are bigger than
the actual distances and
that each iteration we decrease at
least one distance by at least one.
This process cannot be infinite.
It will at some point come to
the stage when the distance, and
the distance estimate are the same, and
so this edge cannot be relaxed anymore.
And if that happens for
all the edges our algorithm will stop.
So our algorithm definitely stops.
The question is whether it
comes to exactly the same
dist values as distances from
origin To the corresponding nodes.
So for
contradiction we assume that it does not.
And for that for
at least some node v dist value is bigger
than the actual distance from our agent.
And then, we consider some shortest
path from S to this node v.
V definitely is a broken note, in
the sense that [INAUDIBLE] is bigger than
the correct distance, but there can be
some other notes on this path from S to V,
which have the same property,
which are broken.
U, V the first note of counting from S on
this path, which is broken in some sense.
U is definitely not the same as S,
because for
S we know that the [INAUDIBLE] value is
zero, and the correct distance is zero.
U is at least the second note on the path,
or maybe much later then.
There is a previous note
on the path before U.
And what is denoted by p.
And let's look at S, p, and u.
What we know is that p is
not a broken node, and so
its dist value is the same as
the distance from origin to this node p.
And so
we know that the distance from S to u
Is actually equal to the distance from S
to p plus weight of the edge from p to u.
Why is that?
Because the part of path from S to u
is optimal because it is a part
of an optimal path from S to v.
And also part of path from S
to p is also optimal, and so
this equality It's true that distance from
S to u is equal to distance from S to P.
And then add the weight
of the S from p to u, but
we also know that distance from S
to p is equal to this value of p.
And so, the second quality is true that it
is equal to dist value of p plus
weight of the S from p to u.
But we also know that note u is broken and
the dist value of u is strictly bigger
than the correct distance from s to u.
Is equal to dist value of p plus
weight of the edge from p to u.
But this inequality is exactly the
property we checked to determine whether
an edge from b to u can be relaxed or not.
And so, from one hand we know
that this edge can be relaxed and
from the another we know that we cannot
relax anymore edges in our graph and
our nef algorithms stopped and
this is a contradiction.
So now, we proved by contradiction
that our nef algorithm returns
correct distances from orignal to.
So now it's in the graph.
We won't analyze the running time of this
algorithm, because in the next video
we'll improve this algorithm and
then we'll estimate its running time.