Hi, in this video,
you will learn Dijkstra's Algorithm,
which is an efficient algorithm to find
shortest paths from original node in the
graph to all the nodes in the graph with
weighted edges where all
the weights are non-negative.
First, let's improve our intuition.
So let's say we're in the node S,
and this is the origin node.
What we know exactly is that the distance
from this node to itself is 0.
We don't need to see
anything else to decide that
because all the edges are non-negative,
so it's better just to stay in s, and
this is the shortest path
from S to itself, okay?
And now, let's look at all
the edges outgoing of node S.
And let's relax all those edges.
So now we see that there
are edges of length 5 and
10, and they go to nodes A and B.
And so, we can determine that
the dist value of A is 5,
and the dist value of B
is 10 after relaxation.
Now if there are no more
edges outgoing from S,
we already know that the distance
from S to A is exactly 5.
Because we cannot go around it and
spend less time.
So we're sure about distance for A.
So now, let's relax all the edges from A.
And we will see that the distance
to B will improve, and
the distance to B becomes 5 plus 3,
which is just 8.
And also, we'll discover two more nodes,
C and D, and
we will relax the edges from A to them.
And C will get an estimate of 12
because it's 5 plus 7, and D will
get an estimate of 6, which is 5 plus 1,
which is the way of edge from A to D.
So the question is what
is the next node for
which we already know
the correct distance for sure?
And this node is D.
Because it has the smallest
dist value estimate, and
it means that there is
no way to go around it.
We can go directly to it from
S through A in distance 6,
but if we go through any of the other
nodes, it will take us at least
8 to get there and
also some non-negative amount after that.
So we cannot really improve
this dist value estimate of 6.
So we now know exactly
the distance to D is 6,
and we can continue by
relaxing edges from D.
While for B and C,
it is still possible that their dist
values are larger than actual distances.
For example, if there is an edge
from D to B of length 1,
then the dist value of B will
improve even better, it will be 7.
And if we get an edge
from D to C of length 1,
then the distance to C will be just 7,
also, which is much less than 12.
So now we have this intuition
that at any moment of time,
if we have relaxed all the edges outgoing
from some known set of nodes for
which the distances are already known
correctly, then the node with the smallest
dist value estimate is also a node for
which we know the distance correctly.
So, the main idea of
Dijkstra's Algorithm is that we maintain
some set R of vertices for
which dist value is already set correctly.
We call this set R, known region.
And initially, we only have node S,
the region in the set R,
because for this node, we definitely
know that the distance to it is 0.
And then on each iteration, we take
the node outside of this region with
a minimum dist value out of all
nodes in this outside region, and
we add this node to the known region and
relax all the outgoing edges.
And so, after a number of iterations,
which is equal to the number
of nodes in the graph,
we will know all the correct distances
from origin to all the nodes in the graph.
Let's see how it works in an example.
Here, we have six nodes, some edges, and
the edge weights are written
nearby the corresponding edges.
And on top of each node,
and under the bottom nodes,
we have the current dist value.
So we start with infinities
in all the nodes,
but the origin node to the left,
which has dist value of 0.
Now we add this 0 node to the known
region, and we now know for
sure that the distance from
the origin to it is 0.
And so we color the dist value by green,
because we are sure that this is the
correct distance from origin to this node.
And then we color our node in black,
and we start processing it.
So we color nodes in black when we start
processing them in the same way we did in
the breadth-first search.
Now relax all the outgoing
edges from this node.
First relax the edge of length 3, and we
improve the dist value from infinity to 3.
And next,
we traverse edge of length 10 to improve
the dist value from infinity to 10.
Now what do we know?
We know that the node with
a minimum dist value outside of
the known black region is
the node with dist value of 3.
So this node actually has a distance of 3,
and we color the distance with green and
the node with black, and
we start processing this node.
So we process the outgoing edges.
First, edge of length 8, which goes
to the node with distance 10, but
new estimate is 3 plus 8,
which is 11, which is bigger than 10.
So, nothing changes because of this edge.
And I also have an edge of flag 3, and we
improve the dist value from infinity to 6.
And there is also an edge of flag 5,
which improves the dist
value from infinity to 8.
And now, what we see is that the node
with the minimum dist values,
the node in the top right corner,
which has this value of 6.
So we color it with black color and
the distance with green and process it.
This edge gives us improvement
from infinity to 8.
This edge gives us
improvement from 8 to 7,
and this edge gives us
an improvement from 10 to 9.
Now the best node is in the bottom
to the right and has distance 7.
And it improves the distance estimate for
the right most node from 8 to 7,
and notice that there is
an edge of weight exactly 0.
This is allowed because 0 is non-negative.
We'll only forbid the edges
from being negative, but
non-negative, including 0, is okay.
So now,
we don't have any more outgoing edges from
these nodes to the right and the bottom.
And so it's like the next node process,
which is the right most node
with an estimation of 7.
But we don't have any outgoing edges from
it, so we process the last remaining node,
which has distance of 9.
And we can try to relax some edges,
but they don't work
because this is the farthest
node from the start.
So now we know all the distances from
the origin to all the nodes in the graph.
And this is how Dijkstra's
algorithm works on this example.