Now let's prove that Dijkstra's
algorithm actually finds correct
distances from the original node
to all the nodes in the graph.
And the lemma states that
when a node is selected
as the node with a minimum dist value out
of all nodes outside of a known region,
it's dist value is actually equal to the
correct distance from origin to this node.
Let's prove that.
Again, by contradiction.
Let's assume this rule
is broken at some point.
Let's select first such moment.
So this moment, we have some known region,
R, which contains node S and
maybe some other nodes colored in black.
And all the nodes colored in white
are outside the known region.
So C, D, E, F, and G, in this case.
And they have some dist
values which are written in
blue near the corresponding nodes.
What will happen next is node C
will be selected as the node with
the minimum dist value out of all
the nodes outside known region.
And we suppose that this
dist value of six is wrong.
What we know about dist values is that
they are upper bounds on the correct
distances, that is if we have
some dist value then we can
also show some path of exactly
the length equal to this dist value.
And so the shortest path to this node
Is less than or equal to this value.
So there can be only two cases.
Dist value is equal to the correct
distance, but we assume it is not.
And in this case it is strictly
bigger than the correct distance.
So we know that dist value of six is
strictly bigger than the length of
the shortest path from origin to node C.
Now let's think about this shortest path.
It starts in the node S,
which is inside known region, and
it ends in the node C, which is
outside of the current known region.
So there is some edge
which goes from inside
known region to outside of the known
region in this shortest path.
Let's consider this edge.
This can be an edge, for
example, from B to F.
It can also go directly into C,
that doesn't matter.
What matters is what happens next.
After it goes from known region
to outside, it also goes through
some path of known negative length,
or maybe this
path is empty with the edge from known
region outside of it goes directly to C,
but anyway this rest of
the path is non-negative.
What it means that if we just considered
the first part of this path which ends
in the end of the edge from known region
to outside, now this part of the path
is also strictly less than the dist
value of C, strictly less than six.
So we know that there is a path which
goes from S,
goes somewhere inside the known region and
then goes outside and
its length is strictly less than six.
But it means that actually
some of the edges,
it means that this edge could be
relaxed in the current situation,
because we know for
sure that the distance estimate for
node B is equal to the shortest
path from S to B, because the first
moment when this rule breaks is with
node C, it was not broken with node B.
Okay?
So, the distance estimate of node B
is exactly equal to the shortest path
from S to B.
When we add the length of
the edge from B to F to it,
we will get this same thing as we
get when we go by shortest path
from S to C, but take only the part of it,
which adds in the node F.
So if we add to the value of B,
the value of the length
of the edge from B to F.
We will get value very which
is strictly less then six.
And so it is strictly less
than this value of F because
this value of F is greater than or
equal to the dist value of E.
So we could relax this edge but
we didn't do it for some reason.
That's we know that we've relaxed
all the edges from the known
region to outside of the known the region.
So this contradicts our algorithm.
Now this contradiction proves that this
rule is actually not broken and when we
select the node with the minimum distance
value outside of the known region,
it's dist value is actually equal to the
correct distance from origin to this node.
And this proves that Dijkstra's algorithm
finds correct distances from the region to
all the nodes in the graph.