Hi, in this lesson you will learn
how to solve the problem of
organizing children into
groups more efficiently.
Most specifically, we will come up
with a polynomial time algorithm for
this problem as opposed to the exponential
type algorithm from the previous lesson.
But in order to do this,
we first need to do a very important thing
that you should probably do every time
before solving an algorithmic problem.
You should reformulate it
in mathematical terms.
For example,
in this problem we will consider points
on the line instead of children.
For example, if we have a child of age
three and a half years we will instead
consider a point on the line with
coordinate 3.5 and if we have another
child of age 6, we will instead consider
a point with coordinate 6 on the line.
Now, what do groups of
children correspond to?
If we have a group of children,
it consists of several children and
several points on the line correspond
to this group and the fact that the age
of any two children in the group differs
by at most one, means that there exists
a segment of length one on this line
that contains all those points.
Now the goal becomes to select
the minimum possible number of segments
of length one, such that those
segments cover all the points.
Then, if we have such segments,
we can just take all the points from
that segment in the same group,
and any two children in the group
who differ by, at most, one year.
Now let's look at an example.
We have a line with a few points on it and
we want to cover all the points
with segments of length one.
Here is one example of such covering.
All the segments on the picture
are of the same length and
we consider that this
is length one of this line.
This is not the optimal solution because
below there is another example of covering
and we have only three segments and
they still cover all the points.
Now we want to find a way to find
the minimum possible number of segments to
cover all the points in any configuration.
We want to do that using greedy
algorithm and you probably remember
from the previous lessons that to come up
with a greedy algorithm, you need to
do a greedy choice and to prove that
this greedy choice is a safe move.
I state that in this problem,
safe move is to cover the leftmost point
with a segment of length one which
starts or has left end in this point.
To prove that this is really a safe move,
we need to prove that there exists an
optimal solution with
the minimum possible number of
unit length segments such
that one of the segments
has its left end in the leftmost point.
Let's prove that.
To do that, let's consider any
optimal solution of a given
problem with a given point.
Let's consider the leftmost
point colored in green.
It is covered by some segment.
Colored in red.
Now, let's move this red segment
to the right until it's left
end is in this leftmost point.
I say that we didn't miss any of the
points in the process, because this green
point is the leftmost point so there
are no points to the left from it and
while we are moving the segment to the
right, we didn't miss any of the points.
It means that what we have now is
still a correct covering because
all of the points are still covered and
the number of segments in this covering is
the same as in some optimal
solution from which we started and
that means that it is also
an optimal covering.
So we have just found an optimal solution
in which there is a segment which
starts in the leftmost point.
So, we proved that
covering the leftmost point with a
segment which starts in it is a safe move.
Now that we have a safe move,
let's consider what happens after it.
We have the leftmost point covered, and
also maybe some other points covered.
So we don't need to consider
these points anymore.
We are not interested in them and
we need to cover all the other points with
the minimum possible number
of unit length segments.
So this is the same kind of problem
which we started with, so
this is a subproblem.
Basically it means that we
have a greedy algorithm.
First, make a safe move. Add
a segment to the solution
with the left hand starting
in the leftmost point.
Then remove all the points which
are already covered by the segment
from the set and if there are still
points left, repeat the process and
repeat this process until there
are no points left in the set.