Now let us consider the pseudocode
that implements this algorithm.
For the sake of simplicity we assume that
the points in the input are given in
sorted order from smallest to largest.
We'll start with an empty set
of segments denoted by R and
we start with index i
pointing at the first point
which is the leftmost because
the points are sorted.
Now we go through the points,
and we find the leftmost point.
Currently i is pointing to
the leftmost point in the set.
And at the start of the while loop i will
always point to the leftmost
point which is still in the set.
Now we cover it with the segment
from l to r which has unit length,
and the left end in the point xi, so
this is a segment from xi to xi+1.
We add this segment to the solution set,
and
then we need to remove all the points
from the set which already covered.
Instead of removing the points, we will
just move the pointer to the right and
forget about the points,
which are to the left from the pointer.
So the next while loop, does exactly that.
We know that for any i that is
larger than the current i, xi
is to the right from the left end of the
segment, because the points are sorted.
So if xi is also to the left from R,
then it is covered by the segment.
So we just go to the right, and
to the right with pointer i.
And while xi is less than or equal to r,
we know that the point is covered.
And as soon as we find some xi which is
bigger than r, it means that this point is
not covered and all the points further
in the array are also not covered.
So we stop.
And then we repeat again the iteration
of the outer while loop.
Or maybe our pointer i is already out
of the array of the input points.
And then we stop and
return R, which is the set of segments
that we've built in the process.
Now let's prove that this
algorithm works in linear time.
Indeed, index i changes just from 1 to n.
And we always increase it by one.
For each value of i, we add at
most one segment to the solution.
So overall,
we increase i at most n times and
add at most n segments to the solution.
And this leads to a solution
which works in Big-O of n time.
Now, we had an assumption that the points
in the input are already sorted.
What if we drop this assumption?
Then we will have to sort
the points first, and
then apply our algorithm
PointsCoverSorted.
Later in this module, you will learn
how to sort points in time n log n.
Combining that with our procedure
PointsCoverSorted will give you
total running time of n log n.
Now let's look at our improvement.
We first implemented
a straightforward solution,
which worked in time at
least 2 to the power of n.
And it worked very, very slowly.
So that even for 50 children,
we would have to spend at least 2
weeks of computation to group them.
Our new algorithm, however,
works in n log n time.
And that means that even if we had 10
million children coming to a party,
it would spend only a few seconds grouping
them optimally into several groups.
So that's a huge improvement.
Now let's see how we went to this end.
First, we've invented a naive solution
which worked in exponential time.
It was too slow for us so
we wanted to improve it.
But to improve it,
the very first important step was to
reformulate it in mathematical terms.
And then we had an idea to solve
it with a greedy algorithm.
So, we had to find some greedy choice and
prove that it will be a safe move.
In this case, the safe move turns
out to be to add to the solution
a segment with left and
in the leftmost point.
And then we prove that this
is really a safe move.
It is very important to prove your
solutions before even trying to
implement them.
Because otherwise, it could turn out that
you implemented the solution, tried to
submit it, got wrong answer or some
other result, different from accepted.
And then, you've made a few more changes,
but it still didn't work.
And then, you understand that
your solution was wrong,
completely from the start.
And then you need a new solution, and you
will have to implement it from scratch.
And that means that you've wasted all
the time on implementation on the first
wrong solution.
To avoid that, you should always
prove your solution first.
So after we've proved the safe move,
we basically got our greedy solution.
Which works in combination with
a certain algorithm in time n log n.
Which is not only polynomial, but
is very close to linear time, and
works really fast in practice.